<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1579</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">scirep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title>Sci Rep</abbrev-journal-title></journal-title-group><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12644863</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12644863</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12644863</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41286042</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-25510-6</article-id><title-group><article-title>Mannitol <italic>versus</italic> furosemide for prevention of cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity in a multicenter retrospective cohort study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="author"><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Harimitsu</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yudai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="_eqcntrb93pmc__">#</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names initials="T">Toshinobu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="_fncrsp93pmc__">✉</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="_eqcntrb93pmc__">#</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimokawa</surname><given-names initials="M">Mototsugu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="_fncrsp93pmc__">✉</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyoshi</surname><given-names initials="T">Takanori</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names initials="A">Akari</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Uchiyama</surname><given-names initials="M">Masanobu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Ushio</surname><given-names initials="S">Soichiro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Shiraishi</surname><given-names initials="C">Chihiro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuo</surname><given-names initials="K">Koichi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Egawa</surname><given-names initials="T">Takashi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Pharmacy, National Hospital Organization Kyushu Medical Center, 1-8-1, Jigyohama, Chuo-ku, Fukuoka, 810-8563 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Pharmaceutical Sciences for Health Crisis Management, Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Fukuoka University, 8-19-1, Nanakuma, Jonan-ku, Fukuoka, 814-0180 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Biostatistics, Yamaguchi University Graduate School of Medicine, 1-1-1, Minamiogushi, Ube, Yamaguchi 755-8505 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Pharmacy, National Hospital Organization Beppu Medical Center, 1473 Ooazauchikamado, Beppu, 874‑0011 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label>Department of Oncology and Infectious Disease Pharmacy, Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Fukuoka University, 8-19-1, Nanakuma, Jonan-ku, Fukuoka, 814-0180 Japan </aff><author-notes><fn id="_fncrsp93pmc__"><label>✉</label><p>Corresponding author.</p></fn><fn id="_eqcntrb93pmc__"><label>#</label><p>Contributed equally.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date><day>24</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><fpage>41537</fpage><page-range>41537</page-range><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>26</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><license><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/" ext-link-type="uri">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41598_2025_Article_25510.pdf" content-type="pmc-pdf"><?cloudpmc-path caa7/12644863/53ce22ae7bd3/41598_2025_Article_25510.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 1397809?></self-uri><abstract id="Abs1"><title>Abstract</title><p id="Par1">Cisplatin (cis-diamminedichloroplatinum [CDDP]) is a widely used anticancer drug with a significant risk of nephrotoxicity. This study aimed to compare the nephroprotective effects of mannitol and furosemide as forced diuretics in patients receiving CDDP-based chemotherapy. This multicenter retrospective study analyzed 472 patients with cancer receiving CDDP (≥ 60 mg/m<sup>2</sup>) with either mannitol or furosemide as forced diuretics. Patient characteristics were balanced using inverse probability treatment weighting. Nephrotoxicity was assessed using the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (ver. 5.0) criteria. The results showed that the incidence of nephrotoxicity was significantly lower in the furosemide group than in the mannitol group (6.2% vs. 23.2%, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.007). The mean serum creatinine increase was significantly lower with furosemide (21.7% ± 19.3%) than with mannitol (29.5% ± 40.7%, <italic>p</italic> = 0.007). Hypertension, cisplatin dose ≥ 75 mg/m<sup>2</sup>, absence of magnesium supplementation, and mannitol use were associated with a higher risk of nephrotoxicity. Stratified analysis demonstrated furosemide’s superior nephroprotective effects regardless of nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drug use. Thus, furosemide was associated with superior renoprotective effects compared with mannitol in CDDP-based chemotherapy regimens, thereby making it a viable therapeutic alternative to mannitol. Large randomized controlled trials are warranted to further validate our findings.</p><sec id="sec1" disp-level="2"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41598-025-25510-6.</p></sec><sec id="kwd-group1" xml:lang="en" sec-type="kwd-group" disp-level="2"><p><bold>Keywords:</bold> Cisplatin, Nephrotoxicity, Furosemide, Mannitol, Forced diuretic, Acute kidney injury</p></sec><sec id="kwd-group2" sec-type="kwd-group" disp-level="2"><p><bold>Subject terms:</bold> Cancer, Cancer therapy</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>status</meta-name><meta-value>released</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>display-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-journal-matter</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-scanned</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-retracted</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes notes-type="article-notes"><sec id="historyarticle-meta1" sec-type="history" disp-level="2"><p>Received 2025 May 29; Accepted 2025 Oct 21; Collection date 2025.</p></sec></notes></front><body><sec id="Sec1" disp-level="1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par18">Cisplatin (cis-diamminedichloroplatinum [CDDP]) is a platinum-containing agent and an effective anticancer drug for a wide range of solid tumors that inhibits DNA replication by forming DNA cross-links. Numerous serious adverse effects of CDDP have been reported, including nephrotoxicity, bone marrow suppression, hearing loss, tinnitus, and nausea/vomiting<sup><xref rid="CR1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="CR2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>. Specifically, CDDP-induced nephrotoxicity necessitates discontinuation or dose reduction of CDDP and significantly impacts subsequent drug therapies<sup><xref rid="CR1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="CR2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>. A factor contributing to CDDP-induced nephrotoxicity is that CDDP is excreted from the kidneys via both glomerular filtration and tubular secretion, resulting in CDDP concentrations in the kidneys exceeding blood levels and accumulation in renal parenchymal cells<sup><xref rid="CR3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="CR4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>. Additionally, some unbound CDDP that is not filtered by the glomeruli may be excreted from the kidneys through tubular secretion<sup><xref rid="CR5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>. During this process, CDDP is actively transported into cells via the organic cation transporter 2 (OCT2), which accumulates in tubular epithelial cells and causes tubular necrosis<sup><xref rid="CR3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>. The main methods used to prevent CDDP-induced nephrotoxicity include hydration, diuretic administration, and magnesium (Mg) supplementation<sup><xref rid="CR7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>–<xref rid="CR12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup>. Importantly, hydration and diuretics are thought to mitigate renal injury by increasing urine output, thereby diluting CDDP concentration within the kidneys<sup><xref rid="CR7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="CR8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>, while Mg supplementation addresses hypomagnesemia, which is a common side effect of CDDP<sup><xref rid="CR13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup>. Hypomagnesemia reportedly upregulates OCT2 expression, potentially increasing renal CDDP accumulation and exacerbating nephrotoxicity<sup><xref rid="CR14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par19">The diuretics currently used in clinical practice are the osmotic diuretic mannitol and loop diuretic furosemide<sup><xref rid="CR7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>. Mannitol reportedly exerts protective effects against nephrotoxicity in vivo<sup><xref rid="CR2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup>. Additionally, furosemide prevents CDDP-induced nephrotoxicity, and in vivo studies evaluating renal function via blood urea nitrogen have reported that the estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) is partially preserved in rats administered furosemide<sup><xref rid="CR16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="CR17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>. Although the preventive effect of diuretics on nephrotoxicity has been reported, evidence regarding the relationship between diuretic type and nephroprotective effects is insufficient, and an appropriate type of diuretic for preventing nephrotoxicity has not been established. Several previous studies comparing mannitol and furosemide have been published<sup><xref rid="CR16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="CR18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>–<xref rid="CR20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>; however, the results were derived using small sample sizes and are not conclusive regarding their superiority in preventing nephrotoxicity. Here, we examined the effects of mannitol and furosemide on the prevention of cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity in a relatively large cohort of patients with adjustments for patient characteristics using inverse probability treatment weighting (IPTW), albeit in a retrospective analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" disp-level="1"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec50" disp-level="2"><title>Setting and patients</title><p id="Par21">We analyzed patient-level pooled data from a multicenter, retrospective observational study<sup><xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup>. The study protocol was approved by the Institutional Review Boards of all participating institutions and by the Ethics Committee of Beppu Medical Center (approval No. 2016-011). All participants were treated in accordance with the principles outlined in the Declaration of Helsinki. The Ethics Committee of Beppu Medical Center, the coordinating center, waived the requirement for informed consent owing to the retrospective nature of the study. Patient data were used after allowing patients to refuse to participate using an opt-out form. We analyzed 472 cancer patients with Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status (PS) of 0–2 and creatinine clearance of ≥ 60 mL/min who received CDDP (≥ 60 mg/m<sup>2</sup>) for the first time and were administered furosemide (20 mg) and/or mannitol (20% 300 mL) as forced diuretics along with conventional high-volume hydration per cycle. Patients treated with the short hydration method were excluded to ensure comparable hydration conditions for evaluating the effects of the diuretics.</p></sec><sec id="Sec51" disp-level="2"><title>Data collection</title><p id="Par23">Data on the following patient characteristics were collected: Mg supplementation, sex, age, ECOG PS, presence of cardiac disease, presence of diabetes, presence of hypertension, chemotherapy regimen, CDDP dose, regular use of nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), diuretic type, number of chemotherapy courses administered, serum creatinine (SCr) level, occurrence of renal failure, and Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) ver. 5.0 grade. Cardiac disease was defined as angina pectoris, myocardial infarction, atrial fibrillation, arrhythmia, or valvular disease. SCr was measured using an enzymatic method at least 2 weeks after the start of CDDP administration and was used to determine the presence of nephrotoxicity. Based on the CTCAE ver. 5.0 grades for creatinine elevation, the development of nephrotoxicity was defined as an increase in the SCr after CDDP administration of at least one grade higher than that before CDDP administration. All patients received conventional high-volume hydration, and none of them received short hydration. The exclusion ensured a more homogeneous hydration context for evaluating diuretic strategies.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3" disp-level="2"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par24">We used an IPTW model derived from a logistic regression model to balance observable characteristics among the administered diuretics (covariates: age, male sex, cardiac disease, diabetes, hypertension, albumin level, CDDP dose, Mg supplementation, regular use of NSAIDs, ECOG PS, and cycle of chemotherapy). Inclusion of variables in the model was based on existing knowledge of risk factors for nephrotoxicity and the literature<sup><xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>–<xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>. The cutoff values for age (63 years), albumin level (3.9 g/L) and cisplatin dose (75 mg/m<sup>2</sup>) were based on a previous study<sup><xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup>. The incidence of nephrotoxicity was compared between the mannitol and furosemide groups using the Wilcoxon rank-sum test or Chi-square test. Analysis of covariance, with baseline values as covariates, was performed compare the rate of change in SCr. The rates of SCr change were calculated using the following formula:</p><p id="Par25">(maximum SCr - baseline SCr) × 100/baseline SCr.</p><p id="Par26">Additionally, to assess risk factors for nephrotoxicity, we performed a multivariate logistic regression using backward elimination method, adjusting for potential confounding by age, sex, albumin level, diabetes, hypertension, cardiac disease, Mg supplementation, regular use of NSAIDs, CDDP dose, and cycle of chemotherapy. The selection of variables for inclusion in the model was determined a priori, based on the existing literature and their clinical relevance.</p><p id="Par27">Statistical significance was set at <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 (two-sided). All statistical analyses were performed using SAS 9.4 (SAS Institute, Cary, NC, USA).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec60" disp-level="1"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec61" disp-level="2"><title>Patient characteristics</title><p id="Par29">We included 472 patients receiving CDDP in this analysis. The types of cancer in the study population are summarized in Supplementary Table 1. Baseline characteristics, including sex, age, albumin level, cardiac disease, hypertension, diabetes, ECOG PS, CDDP dose, Mg supplementation, NSAID use, and chemotherapy cycle, are presented in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, listing the unadjusted and adjusted patient characteristics stratified by mannitol or furosemide. The visual plot for the balance diagnostics of IPTW is presented in Supplementary Fig. 1. However, an imbalance in NSAID use was observed.</p><table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Unadjusted and adjusted baseline characteristics of patients.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Unadjusted</th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Adjusted</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Mann</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Furo </th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SMD</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mann</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Furo</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SMD</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">Sex</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">191</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(77.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">189</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(83.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.152</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.425</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(22.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(16.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">Age (years)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 63</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">125</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(50.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">113</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(50.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.016</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.054</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> &lt; 63</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">121</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(49.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">113</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(50.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">Alb (g/L)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> &lt; 3.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">131</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(53.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">130</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(57.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.086</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.143</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 3.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">115</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(46.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(42.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">Cardiac disease</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(7.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(4.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.123</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.229</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">228</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(92.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">216</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(95.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">Hypertension</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">69</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(28.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(24.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.085</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.303</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">177</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(72.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">171</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(75.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">85.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">Diabates</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(10.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(10.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.013</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.063</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">220</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(89.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">203</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(89.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">89.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">91.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">ECOG PS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">168</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(68.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">181</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(80.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.272</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.189</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">78</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(31.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(19.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">CDDP dose (mg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 75</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">140</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(56.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">152</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(67.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.214</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.069</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> &lt; 75</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">106</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(43.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(32.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">Mg supplementation</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">225</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(91.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(19.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.126</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">91.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">89.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.019</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(8.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">183</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(81.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">NSAIDs (regular use)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(24.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(15.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.246</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.113</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">185</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(75.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">192</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(85.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">Number of chemotherapy cycles</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> &lt; 3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(27.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">181</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(80.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.237</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.302</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">178</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(72.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(19.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">85.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="_fn_p14"><p>Alb, albumin; CDDP, cis-diamminedichloroplatinum (cisplatin); ECOG PS, Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group Performance Status; Mg, magnesium; NSAIDs, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs; SMD, standardized mean difference.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="Sec62" disp-level="2"><title>Severity of nephrotoxicity</title><p id="Par32">The severity grades of nephrotoxicity (CTCAE v5) in each group after IPTW adjustment are presented in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. We compared the severity grades of nephrotoxicity between patients treated with mannitol (<italic>n</italic> = 246) and furosemide (<italic>n</italic> = 244). The Wilcoxon rank-sum test revealed a statistically significant difference in the distribution of nephrotoxicity severity grades between the two groups (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001).</p><table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Severity of nephrotoxicity.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mann (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Furo (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WNL</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76.83</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93.80</td><td align="center" rowspan="4" colspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Grade 1</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.98</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Grade 2</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.44</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Grade 3</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="_fn_p18"><p>SD, standard deviation. WNL, within normal limit.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="Sec63" disp-level="2"><title>Changes in SCr in all subsequent cycles</title><p id="Par35">The mean rates of SCr change of the mannitol and furosemide groups were 29.5 ± 40.7 and 21.7 ± 19.3 mg/dL, respectively, with a significant difference in the rate of change in SCr between the two groups (<italic>p</italic> = 0.007) (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Mean change rate of serum creatinine level.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean (SD)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95%CI</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mann</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.5 (40.7)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.4–34.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.007</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Furo</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.7 (19.3)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.4–24.0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="_fn_p22"><p>SD, standard deviation.CI, confidence interval.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="Sec64" disp-level="2"><title>Risk factors for CDDP-induced nephrotoxicity</title><p id="Par38">The results of univariate and multivariate logistic regression analyses of the risk factors for nephrotoxicity are shown in Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>. Presence of hypertension (<italic>p</italic> = 0.017), CDDP dose ≥ 75 mg/m<sup>2</sup> (<italic>p</italic> = 0.005), no Mg supplementation (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001), and mannitol use (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) were associated with a higher risk of nephrotoxicity.</p><table-wrap id="Tab4" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Risk factors for CDDP induced nephrotoxicity.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Univariate</th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Multivariate</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OR</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95%CI</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">p-value</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OR</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95%CI</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Sex</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Female vs. male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.805</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.552–5.069</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Age (years)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 63 vs. &lt; 63</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.849</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.519–1.389</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.515</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Alb (g/L)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> &lt; 3.9 vs. ≥ 3.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.238</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.758–2.024</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.394</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Cardiac disease</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes vs. no</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.239</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.320–7.950</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.010</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Diabetes</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes vs. no</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.756</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.349–1.638</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.479</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Hypertension</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes vs. no</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.158</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.875–5.318</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.430</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.394–4.234</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.017</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">CDDP dose (mg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 75 vs. &lt; 75</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.596</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.948–2.687</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.079</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.321</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.289–4.181</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Mg supplementation</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No vs. yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.615</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.894–6.900</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.420</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.536–11.583</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">NSAIDs (regular use)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes vs. no</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.632</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.543–4.488</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Chemotherapy cycle</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 3 or more vs. 2 or less</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.297</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.348–3.915</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Diuretics</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Mann vs. Furo</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.564</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.590–8.042</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.833</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.665–8.765</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="_fn_p26"><p>Alb, albumin; CDDP, cis-diamminedichloroplatinum (cisplatin); CI, confidence interval; Mg, magnesium; NSAIDs, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs; OR, odds ratio.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="Sec65" disp-level="2"><title>Stratified analysis</title><p id="Par41">A stratified analysis of the incidence of nephrotoxicity was performed by comparing the mannitol and furosemide groups by each risk factor after IPTW adjustment. Among NSAID users, the data showed a significantly higher sum of scores in the mannitol group than in the furosemide group (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001). Similarly, among NSAID non-users, the mannitol group showed a significantly higher sum of scores than did the furosemide group (<italic>p</italic> = 0.090). These findings suggest that, after adjusting for patient backgrounds, outcomes in the mannitol group were significantly higher than those in the furosemide group, regardless of NSAID use (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>). Furthermore, in a multivariate analysis stratified by NSAID use (yes/no), conducted as a sensitivity analysis, mannitol use was identified as a factor associated with the occurrence of nephrotoxicity, irrespective of NSAID use (Supplementary Table 2).</p><table-wrap id="Tab5" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Incidence of nephrotoxicity stratified by risk factor.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mann (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Furo (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Sex</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Female</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.45</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.452</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Male</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.51</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.47</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Age (years)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 63</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.60</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.31</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> &lt; 63</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.66</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.07</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Alb (g/L)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> &lt; 3.9</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.90</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.87</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 3.9</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.48</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.76</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Cardiac disease</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.22</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.48</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.049</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.25</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.97</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Hypertension</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.09</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.726</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.03</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Diabetes</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.23</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.44</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.722</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.64</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">ECOG PS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 0</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.36</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.54</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 1</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.62</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">CDDP dose (mg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 75</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.86</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.87</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> &lt; 75</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.98</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.17</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0043</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Mg supplementation</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.33</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.85</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.86</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.219</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">NSAIDs (regular use)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.23</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.82</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.16</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.68</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.090</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Chemotherapy cycle</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> &lt; 3</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.12</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.192</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥ 3</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.72</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="_fn_p30"><p>Alb, albumin; CDDP, cis-diamminedichloroplatinum (cisplatin); Mg, magnesium; NSAIDs, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="Sec5" disp-level="1"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par43">Herein, we compared the protective effects of mannitol and furosemide on cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity. The incidence of nephrotoxicity was 23.2% in the mannitol group and 6.2% in the furosemide group, with a significant difference observed (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.007). Additionally, the incidence of Grade ≥ 2 nephrotoxicity was 2.8% in the mannitol group and 0.2% in the furosemide group. The presence of hypertension, CDDP dose ≥ 75 mg/m<sup>2</sup>, absence of Mg administration, and mannitol use were associated with a higher risk of nephrotoxicity. Notably, mannitol use has been identified as a risk factor for CDDP-induced nephrotoxicity, along with the following well-known risk factors: hypertension<sup><xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup>, high CDDP dose<sup><xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="CR26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup>, and absence of Mg supplementation<sup><xref rid="CR9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="CR27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup>. Our study cohort exhibited a non-negligible imbalance regarding the regular use of NSAIDs, which have been reported to worsen nephrotoxicity<sup><xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="CR27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup>. Therefore, we conducted a stratified analysis based on NSAID usage. The results demonstrated that the furosemide group showed significantly better preventive effects against nephrotoxicity regardless of whether NSAIDs were used or not. Furthermore, consistent results were observed in a multivariate analysis stratified by NSAID use (yes/no), which was conducted as a sensitivity analysis. Loop diuretics can decrease effective circulating volume and, in combination with NSAIDs, may increase the risk of prerenal acute kidney injury (AKI) because NSAID-mediated cyclooxygenase inhibition reduces prostaglandin-dependent afferent arteriolar vasodilation and can blunt the natriuretic effect of furosemide. However, in our IPTW-adjusted stratified analysis by NSAID use, furosemide was associated with significantly lower nephrotoxicity than mannitol among both NSAID users and non-users, suggesting that the observed benefit of furosemide is unlikely to be driven by an NSAID–furosemide interaction. Nonetheless, residual confounding cannot be excluded, and future prospective trials should pre-specify interaction analyses for NSAID exposure. Additionally, among female patients, patients with cardiac disease, those with hypertension, and those who received fewer than three cycles of chemotherapy, the mannitol group tended to have a lower incidence of nephrotoxicity. However, across all other strata, the furosemide group exhibited a lower incidence of nephrotoxicity, consistent with the overall findings. Although there is limited evidence for a direct potentiation of cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity by furosemide, it can reportedly pose an indirect risk through the deterioration of hemodynamic status in patients having cancer with comorbid cardiac disease<sup><xref rid="CR28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup>. The findings suggest that furosemide may pose a potential risk in patients with cardiac disease, which should be clarified in future research. Furthermore, the subgroups of female sex, patients with cardiac disease, patients with hypertension, and those with fewer than three chemotherapy cycles had very small sample sizes, which may have influenced these results.</p><p id="Par44">The nephrotoxicity observed in this study was predominantly Grade 1 and was generally manageable with supportive care and dose modification. While statistically significant, the clinical relevance of this predominantly mild toxicity may be limited at the individual patient level. Nevertheless, even Grade 1 declines in renal function can accumulate over successive treatment cycles, potentially constraining the cumulative cisplatin dose. Therefore, we recommend caution against overinterpretation of these results and underscore the need for an individualized risk–benefit assessment for each patient.</p><p id="Par45">Previous studies have compared mannitol and furosemide for cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity prevention. A small randomized controlled trial found no significant difference in nephrotoxicity incidence between mannitol and furosemide groups<sup><xref rid="CR16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>. However, the furosemide group showed greater urine output at 1 h post-administration, with lower rates of unplanned furosemide administration, fluid loading, and vomiting, but higher incidence of hyponatremia compared to the mannitol group<sup><xref rid="CR16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>. A retrospective observational study comparing the nephroprotective effects of mannitol and furosemide with low-dose cisplatin (40 mg/m<sup>2</sup>) reported no significant differences in SCr changes or hypomagnesemia incidence between groups<sup><xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>. Furthermore, a small randomized controlled trial comparing normal saline, mannitol, and furosemide showed significant differences in decreased 24-h creatinine clearance between the normal saline group and the mannitol group, and between the furosemide group and the mannitol group, suggesting that furosemide and normal saline provided superior nephroprotection compared to mannitol<sup><xref rid="CR29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par46">A single-center, open-label, randomized phase II study demonstrated that although mannitol is the standard diuretic in CDDP-based chemotherapy according to conventional CTCAE grading, furosemide can also be considered when assessed by actual SCr level and Cr clearance<sup><xref rid="CR18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup>. Additionally, mannitol may cause phlebitis, which adversely affects patients’ quality of life. Although the difference was not statistically significant, the incidence of phlebitis was 1.7 times higher in the mannitol arm<sup><xref rid="CR18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par47">Furosemide inhibits Na–K–Cl cotransporter 2 in the thick ascending limb, reducing tubular sodium reabsorption and medullary oxygen demand, potentially mitigating ischemic susceptibility during cisplatin exposure<sup><xref rid="CR30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup>. Altered tubular chloride handling may influence cisplatin aquation kinetics and cellular uptake<sup><xref rid="CR26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="CR31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup>. Additionally, diuretic-induced changes in luminal flow and sodium delivery can modulate expression/activity of transporters implicated in cisplatin handling (e.g., OCT2, copper transporter 1, multidrug and toxin extrusion 1/2-K) and reduce contact time with proximal tubular cells<sup><xref rid="CR4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="CR32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup>. In contrast, mannitol’s osmotic diuresis may transiently raise intratubular pressure and, in the presence of tubular injury, potentially promote back-leak without directly modulating transporter activity<sup><xref rid="CR33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup>. These mechanisms could plausibly contribute beyond urine output alone.</p><p id="Par48">Considering the convenience of furosemide administration, furosemide may also be considered in CDDP-based chemotherapy owing to similar serum Cr changes, lower skin toxicity, shorter administration time, and simplicity of the procedure. The optimal choice for individual patients should be made after comprehensively evaluating not only renoprotective effects but also patient characteristics, side effect profiles, feasibility, cost, and other factors.</p><p id="Par49">This study had some limitations. First, it was a retrospective observational study rather than a randomized or prospective study. Despite IPTW and multiple sensitivity analyses, residual and unmeasured confounding cannot be eliminated in this non-randomized design, and the results should be interpreted with caution. Second, individual quantifiable data on heart disease (e.g., cardiac output and ejection fraction) were not available; therefore, heart disease was defined solely based on a history of heart disease, such as angina pectoris or myocardial infarction. Third, data on serum Mg levels, blood glucose and blood pressure, urine dipsticks for hematuria or proteinuria, and urine volume were unavailable, and adjustment for the timing of blood creatinine measurement was not possible due to the observational nature of the study. Fourth, data on potential risk factors, including the use of aminoglycosides, metformin, angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors, and angiotensin II receptor blockers, were not at our disposal. Fifth, the safety profile could not be determined in this pooled analysis because adverse event data were not recorded in the medical records. Sixth, clinical testing was conducted in all cases immediately before each chemotherapy cycle, whereas testing during the treatment cycle varied among cases. Consequently, the Kidney Disease Improving Global Outcomes (KDIGO) criteria for AKI could not be used to assess nephrotoxicity in this study. Moreover, eGFR was not used as an outcome measure. Although eGFR is an informative renal function metric, the retrospective design limited our ability to consistently capture all variables necessary for accurate eGFR computation (e.g., body weight contemporary with each creatinine measurement) across all patients. Although we recognize the importance of the KDIGO criteria or eGFR in assessing the details of the development of renal injury, the CTCAE is a standard measure of chemotherapy-induced toxicity in clinical oncology, and we believe it has some relevance in this study. We adopted CTCAE grading as the primary endpoint on the basis of a previous study; however, future studies to assess CDDP-induced nephrotoxicity should pay more attention to this point. Finally, the inclusion of only conventional high-volume hydration and not the short hydration method as a method to prevent nephrotoxicity other than forced diuresis limits the generalizability of the study results. Furthermore, since this study was limited to a high-dose, single-day cisplatin regimen, further investigation is required to determine the applicability of these findings to other malignancies or alternative administration protocols, such as fractionated multi-day schedules. The findings of this study should also be considered in the context of our patient cohort, which primarily consisted of patients with head and neck cancer, esophageal cancer, and lung cancer.</p><p id="Par50">Despite the limitations, our multicenter sample size was relatively large compared with prior single-center studies, thereby improving statistical precision and increased the potential for application across diverse clinical settings. In this retrospective analysis, furosemide was associated with improved renoprotection, suggesting that it may be a viable therapeutic option. Nevertheless, confirmatory evidence from larger randomized controlled trials is warranted.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6" disp-level="1"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p>
<supplementary-material id="MOESM1" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41598_2025_25510_MOESM1_ESM.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document"><?cloudpmc-path caa7/12644863/0c872988e2e8/41598_2025_25510_MOESM1_ESM.docx?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 21523?><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>

<supplementary-material id="MOESM2" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41598_2025_25510_MOESM2_ESM.tiff" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><?cloudpmc-path caa7/12644863/5af37d3288b7/41598_2025_25510_MOESM2_ESM.tiff?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 2686980?><caption><p>Supplementary Material 2</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</sec><sec id="ack1" sec-type="ack" disp-level="1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We wish to thank Miyuki Uoi, Fuyuki Ohmura, Sachi Maesaki, Kyouichi Tsumagari, and Chiaki Yokota for providing support as the investigators of the multicenter observational study that collected the data used in this study. We also thank all the participants in the study and their families.</p></sec><sec id="glossary1" sec-type="glossary" disp-level="1"><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>Alb</term><def><p id="Par2">Albumin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CDDP</term><def><p id="Par3">Cis-diamminedichloroplatinum (cisplatin)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CI</term><def><p id="Par4">Confidence interval</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Cr</term><def><p id="Par5">Creatinine</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CTCAE</term><def><p id="Par6">Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ECOG PS</term><def><p id="Par7">Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group Performance Status</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IPTW</term><def><p id="Par8">Inverse probability treatment weighting</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>KDIGO</term><def><p id="Par9">Kidney Disease: Improving Global Outcomes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Mg</term><def><p id="Par10">Magnesium</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NSAIDs</term><def><p id="Par11">Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OCT2</term><def><p id="Par12">Organic cation transporter 2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OR</term><def><p id="Par13">Odds ratio</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SCr</term><def><p id="Par14">Serum creatinine</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SD</term><def><p id="Par15">Standard deviation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SMD</term><def><p id="Par16">Standardized mean difference</p></def></def-item></def-list></sec><sec id="notes1" disp-level="1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>T.H. conceptualized the study. T.H., Y.H., and M.S. analyzed the claims data. MS performed the statistical analyses. T.H., M.S., Y.H., T.M., and T.E. contributed to the interpretation of data and assisted in the preparation of the manuscript. Y.H., T.H., and M.S. prepared the initial draft of the manuscript. Y.H., T.H., M.S., A.Y., M.U., S.U., C.S., T.M., K.M., and T.E. conducted the critical revision of the manuscript. All authors reviewed the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="notes2" disp-level="1"><title>Data availability</title><p>The data that support the findings of this study are available from the study group. However, restrictions apply to the availability of these data, which were used under a license for the current study and are thus not publicly available. Data is, nevertheless, available from the corresponding authors upon reasonable request and with the permission of the study group.</p></sec><sec id="notes3" disp-level="1"><title>Declarations</title><sec id="FPar2" disp-level="2"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par52">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar1" disp-level="2"><title>Ethical approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par51">All procedures performed in studies involving human participants were conducted in accordance with the ethical standards of the institutional research committee and the 1964 Declaration of Helsinki and its later amendments or comparable ethical standards.</p></sec></sec><sec id="fn-group1" sec-type="fn-group" disp-level="1"><title>Footnotes</title><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><p>Yudai Harimitsu and Toshinobu Hayashi contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="_ci93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="contrib-info" disp-level="1"><title>Contributor Information</title><p>Toshinobu Hayashi, Email: toshinobu@fukuoka-u.ac.jp.</p><p>Mototsugu Shimokawa, Email: moto@yamaguchi-u.ac.jp.</p></sec><sec id="Bib1" sec-type="ref-list" disp-level="1"><title>References</title><sec id="Bib1_sec2" disp-level="2"><ref-list><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Hartmann, J. T. &amp; Lipp, H. P. Toxicity of platinum compounds. <italic>Expert Opin. Pharmacother.</italic><bold>4</bold>, 889–901 (2003).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1517/14656566.4.6.889"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="12783586"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Hartmann, J. T. &amp; Lipp, H. P. Toxicity of platinum compounds. Expert Opin. Pharmacother.4, 889–901 (2003)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wensing, K. U. &amp; Ciarimboli, G. Saving ears and kidneys from cisplatin. <italic>Anticancer Res.</italic><bold>33</bold>, 4183–4188 (2013).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="24122981"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Wensing, K. U. &amp; Ciarimboli, G. Saving ears and kidneys from cisplatin. Anticancer Res.33, 4183–4188 (2013)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Yao, X., Panichpisal, K., Kurtzman, N. &amp; Nugent, K. Cisplatin nephrotoxicity: A review. <italic>Am. J. Med. Sci.</italic><bold>334</bold>, 115–124 (2007).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1097/MAJ.0b013e31812dfe1e"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="17700201"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Yao, X., Panichpisal, K., Kurtzman, N. &amp; Nugent, K. Cisplatin nephrotoxicity: A review. Am. J. Med. Sci.334, 115–124 (2007)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Pabla, N. &amp; Dong, Z. Cisplatin nephrotoxicity: Mechanisms and renoprotective strategies. <italic>Kidney Int.</italic><bold>73</bold>, 994–1007 (2008).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/sj.ki.5002786"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="18272962"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Pabla, N. &amp; Dong, Z. Cisplatin nephrotoxicity: Mechanisms and renoprotective strategies. Kidney Int.73, 994–1007 (2008)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Nagai, N. &amp; Ogata, H. Quantitative relationship between pharmacokinetics of unchanged cisplatin and nephrotoxicity in rats: Importance of area under the concentration-time curve (AUC) as the major toxicodynamic determinant in vivo. <italic>Cancer Chemother. Pharmacol.</italic><bold>40</bold>, 11–18 (1997).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s002800050618"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="9137523"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Nagai, N. &amp; Ogata, H. Quantitative relationship between pharmacokinetics of unchanged cisplatin and nephrotoxicity in rats: Importance of area under the concentration-time curve (AUC) as the major toxicodynamic determinant in vivo. Cancer Chemother. Pharmacol.40, 11–18 (1997)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Filipski, K. K., Mathijssen, R. H., Mikkelsen, T. S., Schinkel, A. H. &amp; Sparreboom, A. Contribution of organic cation transporter 2 (OCT2) to cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity. <italic>Clin. Pharmacol. Ther.</italic><bold>86</bold>, 396–402 (2009).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/clpt.2009.139"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC2746866"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="19625999"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Filipski, K. K., Mathijssen, R. H., Mikkelsen, T. S., Schinkel, A. H. &amp; Sparreboom, A. Contribution of organic cation transporter 2 (OCT2) to cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity. Clin. Pharmacol. Ther.86, 396–402 (2009)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Crona, D. J. et al. A systematic review of strategies to prevent cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity. <italic>Oncologist</italic><bold>22</bold>, 609–619 (2017).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1634/theoncologist.2016-0319"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC5423518"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="28438887"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Crona, D. J. et al. A systematic review of strategies to prevent cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity. Oncologist22, 609–619 (2017)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Pinzani, V. et al. Cisplatin-induced renal toxicity and toxicity-modulating strategies: A review. <italic>Cancer Chemother. Pharmacol.</italic><bold>35</bold>, 1–9 (1994).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/BF00686277"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="7987972"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Pinzani, V. et al. Cisplatin-induced renal toxicity and toxicity-modulating strategies: A review. Cancer Chemother. Pharmacol.35, 1–9 (1994)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Saito, Y. et al. Premedication with intravenous magnesium has a protective effect against cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity. <italic>Support Care Cancer</italic><bold>25</bold>, 481–487 (2017).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s00520-016-3426-5"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="27699503"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Saito, Y. et al. Premedication with intravenous magnesium has a protective effect against cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity. Support Care Cancer25, 481–487 (2017)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Hase, T. et al. Short hydration with 20 mEq of magnesium supplementation for lung cancer patients receiving cisplatin-based chemotherapy: A prospective study. <italic>Int. J. Clin. Oncol.</italic><bold>25</bold>, 1928–1935 (2020).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s10147-020-01755-1"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32740717"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Hase, T. et al. Short hydration with 20 mEq of magnesium supplementation for lung cancer patients receiving cisplatin-based chemotherapy: A prospective study. Int. J. Clin. Oncol.25, 1928–1935 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Miyoshi, T. et al. Preventive effect of 20 mEq and 8 mEq magnesium supplementation on cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity: A propensity score–matched analysis. <italic>Support Care Cancer</italic><bold>30</bold>, 3345–3351 (2022).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s00520-021-06790-w"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34984552"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Miyoshi, T. et al. Preventive effect of 20 mEq and 8 mEq magnesium supplementation on cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity: A propensity score–matched analysis. Support Care Cancer30, 3345–3351 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Takagi, A. et al. Comparison of preventive effects of combined Furosemide and mannitol versus single diuretics, Furosemide or mannitol, on cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>14</bold>, 10511 (2024).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41598-024-61245-6"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11076568"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38714773"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Takagi, A. et al. Comparison of preventive effects of combined Furosemide and mannitol versus single diuretics, Furosemide or mannitol, on cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity. Sci. Rep.14, 10511 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Vickers, A. E. M. et al. Kidney slices of human and rat to characterize cisplatin-induced injury on cellular pathways and morphology. <italic>Toxicol. Pathol.</italic><bold>32</bold>, 577–590 (2004).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1080/01926230490508821"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="15603542"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Vickers, A. E. M. et al. Kidney slices of human and rat to characterize cisplatin-induced injury on cellular pathways and morphology. Toxicol. Pathol.32, 577–590 (2004)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Yokoo, K. et al. Enhanced renal accumulation of cisplatin via renal organic cation transporter deteriorates acute kidney injury in hypomagnesemic rats. <italic>Clin. Exp. Nephrol.</italic><bold>13</bold>, 578–584 (2009).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s10157-009-0215-1"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="19629622"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Yokoo, K. et al. Enhanced renal accumulation of cisplatin via renal organic cation transporter deteriorates acute kidney injury in hypomagnesemic rats. Clin. Exp. Nephrol.13, 578–584 (2009)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bégin, A. M. et al. Effect of mannitol on acute kidney injury induced by cisplatin. <italic>Support Care Cancer</italic><bold>29</bold>, 2083–2091 (2021).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s00520-020-05703-7"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32862356"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Bégin, A. M. et al. Effect of mannitol on acute kidney injury induced by cisplatin. Support Care Cancer29, 2083–2091 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Makimoto, G. et al. Randomized study comparing mannitol with Furosemide for the prevention of cisplatin-induced renal toxicity in non-small cell lung cancer: The OLCSG1406 trial. <italic>Asia Pac. J. Clin. Oncol.</italic><bold>17</bold>, 101–108 (2021).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/ajco.13423"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32885583"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Makimoto, G. et al. Randomized study comparing mannitol with Furosemide for the prevention of cisplatin-induced renal toxicity in non-small cell lung cancer: The OLCSG1406 trial. Asia Pac. J. Clin. Oncol.17, 101–108 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17"><named-content content-type="citation-string">El Hamamsy, M., Kamal, N., Bazan, N. S. &amp; El Haddad, M. Evaluation of the effect of Acetazolamide versus mannitol on cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity, a pilot study. <italic>Int. J. Clin. Pharm.</italic><bold>40</bold>, 1539–1547 (2018).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s11096-018-0677-x"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="30167970"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="El Hamamsy, M., Kamal, N., Bazan, N. S. &amp; El Haddad, M. Evaluation of the effect of Acetazolamide versus mannitol on cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity, a pilot study. Int. J. Clin. Pharm.40, 1539–1547 (2018)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Murakami, E. et al. Mannitol versus Furosemide in patients with thoracic malignancies who received cisplatin-based chemotherapy using short hydration: A randomized phase II trial. <italic>Cancer Med.</italic><bold>13</bold>, e6839 (2024).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1002/cam4.6839"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC10923027"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38457231"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Murakami, E. et al. Mannitol versus Furosemide in patients with thoracic malignancies who received cisplatin-based chemotherapy using short hydration: A randomized phase II trial. Cancer Med.13, e6839 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Mach, C. M. et al. A retrospective evaluation of Furosemide and mannitol for prevention of cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity. <italic>J. Clin. Pharm. Ther.</italic><bold>42</bold>, 286–291 (2017).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/jcpt.12509"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="28276070"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Mach, C. M. et al. A retrospective evaluation of Furosemide and mannitol for prevention of cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity. J. Clin. Pharm. Ther.42, 286–291 (2017)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ostrow, S. et al. High-dose cisplatin therapy using mannitol versus furosemide diuresis: Comparative pharmacokinetics and toxicity. <italic>Cancer Treat. Rep.</italic><bold>65</bold>, 73–78 (1981).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="6784924"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Ostrow, S. et al. High-dose cisplatin therapy using mannitol versus furosemide diuresis: Comparative pharmacokinetics and toxicity. Cancer Treat. Rep.65, 73–78 (1981)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Miyoshi, T. et al. Cisplatin-Induced nephrotoxicity: A multicenter retrospective study. <italic>Oncology</italic><bold>99</bold>, 105–113 (2021).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1159/000510384"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32966986"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Miyoshi, T. et al. Cisplatin-Induced nephrotoxicity: A multicenter retrospective study. Oncology99, 105–113 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Motwani, S. S. et al. Development and validation of a risk prediction model for acute kidney injury after the first course of cisplatin. <italic>J. Clin. Oncol.</italic><bold>36</bold>, 682–688 (2018).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1200/JCO.2017.75.7161"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC5946720"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="29320311"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Motwani, S. S. et al. Development and validation of a risk prediction model for acute kidney injury after the first course of cisplatin. J. Clin. Oncol.36, 682–688 (2018)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Mizuno, T. et al. The risk factors of severe acute kidney injury induced by cisplatin. <italic>Oncology</italic><bold>85</bold>, 364–369 (2013).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1159/000356587"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="24335484"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Mizuno, T. et al. The risk factors of severe acute kidney injury induced by cisplatin. Oncology85, 364–369 (2013)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Kidera, Y. et al. Risk factors for cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity and potential of magnesium supplementation for renal protection. <italic>PLOS One</italic><bold>9</bold>, e101902 (2014).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pone.0101902"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC4096506"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="25020203"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Kidera, Y. et al. Risk factors for cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity and potential of magnesium supplementation for renal protection. PLOS One9, e101902 (2014)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Saito, Y. et al. Risk factor analysis for cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity with the short hydration method in diabetic patients. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>13</bold>, 17126 (2023).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41598-023-44477-w"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC10564853"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37816823"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Saito, Y. et al. Risk factor analysis for cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity with the short hydration method in diabetic patients. Sci. Rep.13, 17126 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Miller, R. P., Tadagavadi, R. K., Ramesh, G. &amp; Reeves, W. B. Mechanisms of cisplatin nephrotoxicity. <italic>Toxins</italic><bold>2</bold>, 2490–2518 (2010).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/toxins2112490"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC3153174"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="22069563"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Miller, R. P., Tadagavadi, R. K., Ramesh, G. &amp; Reeves, W. B. Mechanisms of cisplatin nephrotoxicity. Toxins2, 2490–2518 (2010)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Yoshida, T. et al. Protective effect of magnesium preloading on cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity: A retrospective study. <italic>Jpn. J. Clin. Oncol.</italic><bold>44</bold>, 346–354 (2014).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1093/jjco/hyu004"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="24503028"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Yoshida, T. et al. Protective effect of magnesium preloading on cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity: A retrospective study. Jpn. J. Clin. Oncol.44, 346–354 (2014)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ronco, C. et al. Cardiorenal syndrome. <italic>J. Am. Coll. Cardiol.</italic><bold>52</bold>, 1527–1539 (2008).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.jacc.2008.07.051"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="19007588"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Ronco, C. et al. Cardiorenal syndrome. J. Am. Coll. Cardiol.52, 1527–1539 (2008)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Santoso, J. T., Lucci, J. A., Coleman, R. L., Schafer, I. &amp; Hannigan, E. V. Saline, mannitol, and Furosemide hydration in acute cisplatin nephrotoxicity: A randomized trial. <italic>Cancer Chemother. Pharmacol.</italic><bold>52</bold>, 13–18 (2003).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s00280-003-0620-1"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="12719883"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Santoso, J. T., Lucci, J. A., Coleman, R. L., Schafer, I. &amp; Hannigan, E. V. Saline, mannitol, and Furosemide hydration in acute cisplatin nephrotoxicity: A randomized trial. Cancer Chemother. Pharmacol.52, 13–18 (2003)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Evans, R. G. et al. Haemodynamic influences on kidney oxygenation: clinical implications of integrative physiology. <italic>Clin. Exp. Pharmacol. Physiol.</italic><bold>40</bold>, 106–122 (2013).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/1440-1681.12031"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="23167537"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Evans, R. G. et al. Haemodynamic influences on kidney oxygenation: clinical implications of integrative physiology. Clin. Exp. Pharmacol. Physiol.40, 106–122 (2013)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Kelland, L. The resurgence of platinum-based cancer chemotherapy. <italic>Nat. Rev. Cancer</italic><bold>7</bold>, 573–584 (2007).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/nrc2167"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="17625587"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Kelland, L. The resurgence of platinum-based cancer chemotherapy. Nat. Rev. Cancer7, 573–584 (2007)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ciarimboli, G. et al. Organic cation transporter 2 mediates cisplatin-induced oto- and nephrotoxicity and is a target for protective interventions. <italic>Am. J. Pathol.</italic><bold>176</bold>, 1169–1180 (2010).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.2353/ajpath.2010.090610"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC2832140"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="20110413"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Ciarimboli, G. et al. Organic cation transporter 2 mediates cisplatin-induced oto- and nephrotoxicity and is a target for protective interventions. Am. J. Pathol.176, 1169–1180 (2010)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Better, O. S. et al. Mannitol therapy revisited (1940–1997). <italic>Kidney Int.</italic><bold>52</bold>, 886–894 (1997).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/ki.1997.409"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="9328926"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Better, O. S. et al. Mannitol therapy revisited (1940–1997). Kidney Int.52, 886–894 (1997)."/></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></sec></sec><sec id="_ad93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="associated-data" disp-level="1"><title>Associated Data</title><sec id="_adsm93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="supplementary-materials" disp-level="2"><title>Supplementary Materials</title><supplementary-material id="db_ds_supplementary-material1_reqid_" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41598_2025_25510_MOESM1_ESM.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document"><?cloudpmc-path caa7/12644863/0c872988e2e8/41598_2025_25510_MOESM1_ESM.docx?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 21523?><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="db_ds_supplementary-material2_reqid_" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41598_2025_25510_MOESM2_ESM.tiff" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><?cloudpmc-path caa7/12644863/5af37d3288b7/41598_2025_25510_MOESM2_ESM.tiff?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 2686980?><caption><p>Supplementary Material 2</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="_adda93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="data-availability-statement" disp-level="2"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The data that support the findings of this study are available from the study group. However, restrictions apply to the availability of these data, which were used under a license for the current study and are thus not publicly available. Data is, nevertheless, available from the corresponding authors upon reasonable request and with the permission of the study group.</p></sec></sec></body></article>