
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2757</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">cureus</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cureus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-8184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cureus Inc.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11501097</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11501097.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11501097</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11501097</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39449947</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.70114</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Internal Medicine</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Nephrology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Oral Liposomal Iron Versus Injectable Iron Sucrose for Anemia Treatment in Non-dialysis Chronic Kidney Disease Patients: A Non-inferiority Study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names initials="A">Alexander</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adler</surname><given-names initials="JR">John R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bengelloun Zahr</surname><given-names initials="S">Soufiane</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Allata</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yassine</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El Mansoury</surname><given-names initials="M">Mouna</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chouhani</surname><given-names initials="BA">Basmat Amal</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kabbali</surname><given-names initials="N">Nadia</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El Bardai</surname><given-names initials="G">Ghita</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sqalli Houssaini</surname><given-names initials="T">Tarik</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label>
Nephrology, Dialysis, and Transplantation, Hassan II University Hospital, Fez, MAR </aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label>
Laboratory of Epidemiology and Health Science Research, Faculty of Medicine, Sidi Mohammed Ben Abdellah University, Fez, MAR </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Soufiane Bengelloun Zahr <email>samy.bengelloun@outlook.fr</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>24</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>9</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue>9</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">469782</issue-id><elocation-id>e70114</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>24</day><month>09</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>24</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-10-25 17:25:53.963"><day>25</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2024, Bengelloun Zahr et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Bengelloun Zahr et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License CC-BY 4.0., which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000070114.pdf"><?pdf-name cureus-0016-00000070114.pdf?><?pdf-size 1100716?><?pdf-md5 13eb99620194e199a41c76f670e1f1d0?><?pdf-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?pdf-cloudpmc-urn urn:app:5cbe/11501097/13eb99620194/cureus-0016-00000070114.pdf?></self-uri><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cureus.com/articles/280098-oral-liposomal-iron-versus-injectable-iron-sucrose-for-anemia-treatment-in-non-dialysis-chronic-kidney-disease-patients-a-non-inferiority-study">This article is available from https://www.cureus.com/articles/280098-oral-liposomal-iron-versus-injectable-iron-sucrose-for-anemia-treatment-in-non-dialysis-chronic-kidney-disease-patients-a-non-inferiority-study</self-uri><abstract><p>Introduction</p><p>Anemia is a prevalent and persistent complication in chronic kidney disease (CKD), particularly in advanced stages, contributing to the deterioration of renal function and diminishing patients' quality of life. Iron supplementation constitutes a cornerstone of anemia management in this population. Among various iron formulations, liposomal iron has emerged as a promising option due to its enhanced efficacy in replenishing iron reserves and improved tolerability.</p><p>Objective</p><p>This study aims to assess the comparative effects of intravenous and liposomal oral iron on hemoglobin levels in non-dialysis CKD patients. Additionally, it seeks to evaluate the rate of hemoglobin correction, iron reserve status during treatment, and therapeutic tolerance to these interventions.</p><p>Materials and methods</p><p>A randomized controlled trial enrolled CKD patients (stages 3-5, not on dialysis) with iron deficiency anemia (hemoglobin ≤ 12 g/dL, ferritin ≤ 100 ng/mL, transferrin saturation ≤ 25%). Participants were allocated to receive either daily oral liposomal iron (Group OS) at a dosage of 30 mg or intravenous iron-hydroxide sucrose complex weekly (Group IV) for three months. Follow-up extended through the treatment phase and two months post-withdrawal.</p><p>Results</p><p>Thirty-one CKD patients were randomized into two groups: 14 received intravenous iron (IV group) and 17 received oral iron (OS group). After excluding four patients, the final cohort comprised 27 individuals (IV group: n=13, OS group: n=14). Both iron treatments resulted in progressive hemoglobin increases, with the IV group showing a mean increase of 14.65% (p=0.049) compared to 4.78% (p=0.003) in the OS group. Secondary analysis revealed significant increases in ferritin levels (p&lt;0.001) and transferrin saturation (TSAT) levels (p=0.031) in the IV group. Post-treatment follow-up demonstrated stable hemoglobin levels in the OS group and a consistent increase in ferritin levels in the IV group. Adverse reactions predominantly included hypotension in the IV group (4 (30.7%)) and constipation in the OS group (4 (28.4%)).</p><p>Discussion and conclusion</p><p>Anemia remains a significant challenge in CKD patients. Our study compares oral liposomal iron to injectable iron for anemia treatment, aiming to minimize hospitalizations for iron infusion, preserve venous capital, and mitigate potential harmful side effects. We found oral liposomal iron to be a safe and effective option for correcting anemia in non-dialysis CKD patients, albeit with lower efficacy in replenishing iron stores compared to IV iron. Comparative analysis with similar studies supports the non-inferiority of oral liposomal iron, although IV iron retains superiority in replenishing iron reserves.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>chronic kidney disease</kwd><kwd>ferritin</kwd><kwd>hemoglobin</kwd><kwd>intravenous iron sucrose</kwd><kwd>liposomal iron</kwd><kwd>transferrin saturation</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>The last two and a half decades have seen erythropoiesis-stimulating agents (ESAs) and iron therapy at the forefront of managing anemia in chronic kidney disease (CKD) patients. While ESAs have demonstrated significant efficacy in alleviating anemia in this context, recent large-scale randomized controlled trials in both non-dialysis and dialysis CKD patients have highlighted their limitations [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].</p><p>Attempts to normalize hemoglobin (Hb) levels with ESAs have shown no significant cardiovascular benefits and have been associated with increased risks of adverse events, such as stroke and venous thromboembolism [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Consequently, there has been a reduction in ESA prescriptions, an increase in blood transfusions, and a notable rise in the use of iron therapy due to its role in addressing hypo responsiveness to ESAs.</p><p>Anemia remains a common complication in CKD, significantly impacting cardiovascular health and quality of life. While a deficit in renal erythropoietin production is a primary cause, iron deficiency plays a pivotal role in the genesis of CKD-related anemia. Iron deficiency, whether absolute or functional, alongside an inflammatory block often seen in CKD patients, accounts for the main reasons behind hypo responsiveness to ESAs [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>The recent shift from ESA-centered treatment to iron therapy has prompted debates regarding the ideal route of iron administration, particularly in non-dialysis CKD patients. Despite the benefits of oral iron, including cost-effectiveness and ease of administration, its use remains limited due to poor gastrointestinal absorption and high rates of adverse events. Conversely, concerns about intravenous (IV) iron revolve around potential kidney damage, infections, atherosclerosis promotion, and other adverse reactions.</p><p>Given these considerations, our study aims to compare the efficacy of oral liposomal iron versus IV iron in treating anemia in non-dialysis CKD patients in terms of iron status during treatment, Hb levels, speed of Hb correction, and therapeutic tolerance.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><p>Study design</p><p>We conducted a randomized controlled trial in the Nephrology, Dialysis, and Transplantation Department of the University Hospital Center Hassan II of Fes. We screened 81 consecutive patients with CKD (stages 3-5) from July 2021 to July 2023. In accordance with the International Committee of Medical Journal Editors (ICMJE) guidelines, our trial is registered at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://ClinicalTrials.gov" ext-link-type="uri">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> under the ID <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT06556134">NCT06556134</ext-link>.</p><p>Inclusion criteria</p><p>Participants were required to be over 18 years of age, with an estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) of ≤60 mL/min/1.73 m² (using the Modification of Diet in Renal Disease equation, MDRD), Hb levels ≤12 g/dL, ferritin levels ≤100 ng/mL, transferrin saturation (TSAT) ≤25%, and parathyroid hormone (PTH) serum levels between 30 and 300 pg/mL.</p><p>Exclusion and withdrawal criteria</p><p>Patients were excluded if they had inflammatory or infectious diseases with C-reactive protein (CRP) levels ≥6 mg/L at the study's onset, had undergone surgical interventions within the last three months, or had hematological disorders, including recent bleeding or blood transfusions (within the past six months). Additional exclusion criteria included malignancies, ongoing immunosuppressive treatments, severe malnutrition (defined as a BMI &lt;20 kg/m², hypoalbuminemia &lt;32 g/L with normal CRP levels, or weight loss &gt;5% in one month or &gt;7.5% in three months), major cardiovascular disease (myocardial infarction, chronic heart failure, stroke), chronic alcohol abuse, known hepatitis B or C infection, pregnancy or lactation, and the need to start dialysis.</p><p>Withdrawal from the study was mandated in cases of severe anemia requiring urgent blood transfusion, non-adherence to the protocol, or withdrawal of consent.</p><p>Ethics committee approval</p><p>The trial received approval from Comite D’ethique Hospitalo-Universitaire Fes (approval number: 01/20) and strictly adhered to the principles outlined in the Declaration of Helsinki.</p><p>Informed consent</p><p>In our study, the process of obtaining informed consent ensured that participants fully understood the nature and objectives of the research. Prior to consenting, participants received a comprehensive explanation of the study's purpose, design, and hypothesis. This information was presented in a clear and understandable manner to facilitate informed decision-making. To further enhance comprehension, participants were provided with an information form that outlined all relevant details, and this document was made available in both French and Arabic.</p><p>The bilingual information form aimed to cater to the diverse linguistic preferences of the study participants, ensuring that each individual had access to the necessary information in their preferred language. Following the detailed explanation of the study, participants were provided with a consent form in both French and Arabic languages and were encouraged to sign the consent form in their preferred language, ensuring that they fully comprehended the information presented. The consent form explicitly outlined all their rights, including the crucial right to withdraw from the study at any time without facing any repercussions.</p><p>This approach adhered to ethical standards, prioritizing transparency and respect for participant autonomy throughout the informed consent process.</p><p>Screening and randomization</p><p>We screened 81 patients in accordance with our inclusion and exclusion criteria. The recruited patients underwent historical and clinical assessments and discontinued any oral iron supplementation that was not part of the study. Subsequently, the participants were randomized into the treatment phase at baseline (referred to as M0). The randomization process was generated by a statistician, and the allocation was concealed through sequentially numbered, sealed envelopes. These envelopes were opened by staff members who were not involved in any step of patient care.</p><p>Study protocol</p><p>The first group (Group IV) received IV iron-hydroxide sucrose complex (marketed as Fermed® 100 mg), administered at a dose of 100 mg, diluted in 250 mL of normal saline, and infused weekly for three months. In contrast, the second group (Group OS) received one oral capsule per day containing 30 mg of pyrophosphate liposomal iron and 70 mg of ascorbic acid (marketed as Lisofer® 30 mg) for the same three-month duration. Before receiving the iron treatment, subjects underwent clinical evaluations, which were repeated immediately after the iron infusion, as well as at 30- and 60-minute post-infusion. Laboratory tests were conducted monthly, starting at baseline (M0) and during all follow-up visits at months 1 (M1), 2 (M2), and 3 (M3), as well as two months post-treatment discontinuation (M4 and M5). These tests included Hb levels, ferritin serum levels, TSAT, CRP, and serum albumin levels. A detailed operating sheet was prepared for each patient to collect and monitor comprehensive data throughout the study period. This sheet recorded clinical and laboratory information, including baseline clinical details such as weight, recent infections or hospitalizations, eGFR, CKD stage, and specific renal diseases, if present. Baseline laboratory data such as Hb, ferritin, TSAT, PTH, CRP, albumin, calcium, and phosphate levels were also recorded. Information about the concurrent use of ESAs, angiotensin receptor blockers (ARBs), or angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors (ACE-Is) was documented to assess potential confounding factors. Throughout the study, the operating sheet facilitated ongoing patient monitoring, tracking clinical and laboratory changes, and documenting any observed side effects or adverse events. The doses of ACE-Is/ARBs and ESAs were managed by the clinician according to personal habits, independently of the study. During the study period, iron therapy was suspended if TSAT exceeded 50% or if ferritin levels were &gt;800 ng/mL.</p><p>Compliance and adverse effects evaluations</p><p>Patients in both groups were followed up monthly for compliance (Questionnaire A) and potential adverse effects and their severity (Questionnaire B). Questionnaire B specifically asked patients to quantify (none, somewhat/occasionally, a lot/often) the frequency of various symptoms, including gastrointestinal symptoms (nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain, bloating, constipation (&lt;1 bowel movement per two days), diarrhea (&gt;3 bowel movements per day)), immune system symptoms (hypersensitivity, angioedema, anaphylactic reactions), nervous system symptoms (dysgeusia, headaches, vertigo, paresthesia, hypoesthesia, syncope, drowsiness, confusion, decreased level of consciousness, anxiety, tremor), cardiac symptoms (bradycardia, tachycardia, palpitations, chest pain), vascular symptoms (hypotension, hypertension, flushing, thrombophlebitis, circulatory collapse), respiratory symptoms (dyspnea, bronchospasm), urinary symptoms (chromaturia), dermatological symptoms (pruritus, rash, urticaria, erythema), musculoskeletal and systemic symptoms (muscle spasms, myalgias, arthralgias, back pain), and general symptoms, as well as others related to the administration site (fever, chills, fatigue, peripheral edema, hyperhidrosis, cold sweat, malaise, pallor, flu symptoms, reactions at the injection/perfusion site).</p><p>Statistical analysis</p><p>Data collected were tabulated in a Microsoft Excel sheet (Microsoft Corporation, Redmond, Washington). The means and standard deviations of the measurements per group were used for statistical analysis using IBM SPSS Statistics for Windows, Version 26 (Released 2019; IBM Corp., Armonk, New York). The differences between the two groups were assessed using the Friedman test, a non-parametric statistical test, with the p-value set at &lt; 0.05.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>Baseline data</p><p>As depicted in Figure <xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, out of the initial pool of 81 patients assessed for eligibility, 31 individuals were randomized into two distinct treatment groups: 14 were assigned to the IV iron group (IV group), while 17 were allocated to the oral iron group (OS group). Four patients were excluded from the study for various reasons: one individual from the IV group due to non-adherence to treatment, and three individuals from the OS group (two deaths and one requiring urgent dialysis with a Hb level &lt;8 g/dL). Consequently, the subsequent statistical analysis was conducted on a final cohort of 27 patients, comprising 13 individuals in the IV group and 14 in the OS group. During the study period, one individual's death was attributed to what appeared to be a myocardial infarction, while the cause of death for the second participant remained undetermined.</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>A flowchart illustrating patient recruitment and disposition in the study</title><p>Hb: hemoglobin</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000070114-i01.jpg"><?image-name cureus-0016-00000070114-i01.jpg?><?image-size 57784?><?image-md5 e7aa08428ffbc6ccf507ae4ab66d956b?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 2225?><?image-original-width 3000?><?image-scaled-height 556?><?image-scaled-width 750?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/5cbe/11501097/e7aa08428ffb/cureus-0016-00000070114-i01.jpg?><?thumb-name cureus-0016-00000070114-i01.gif?><?thumb-size 2767?><?thumb-md5 e4b9b05633b763113d90e93e0566027e?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 79?><?thumb-scaled-width 107?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/5cbe/11501097/e4b9b05633b7/cureus-0016-00000070114-i01.gif?></graphic></fig><p>The primary analysis of each group's baseline data compares demographics, anthropometric measures, renal function, renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (RAAS) inhibitor use, and variances in renal disease between the OS and IV groups. The characteristics of these patients are summarized in Tables <xref rid="TAB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, <xref rid="TAB2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. Baseline laboratory data are also presented in Table <xref rid="TAB3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. No significant differences were detected between the two groups in the key laboratory parameters, including those related to anemia.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Demographic characteristics of the two groups under study</title><p>eGFR: estimated glomerular filtration rate, RAASi: renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system inhibitors, SD: standard deviation.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV Iron Group (N=13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oral Iron Group (N=14)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (46.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 4 (28.6%)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (53.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 10 (71.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years) ± SD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.79 ± 18.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.29 ± 14.34</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight (kg) ± SD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.64 ± 11.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.29 ± 12.99</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body mass index (kg/m²) ± SD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.08 ± 4.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.48 ± 6.07</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Creatinine (mg/L) ± SD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.21 ± 10.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.29 ± 19.64</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">eGFR (mL/min/1.73 m²) ± SD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.64 ± 8.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.82 ± 8.91</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RAASi use </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (69.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 12 (85.7%)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Variances in renal diseases in the two groups under study</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Renal diseases </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV Iron Group (N=13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oral Iron Group (N=14)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetic kidney disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (61.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (50%)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nephroangiosclerosis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (7.15%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tubulointerstitial nephritis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (7.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (7.15%)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urological disorders</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (7.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (7.15%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (23.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (7.15%)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indeterminate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (21.4%)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Laboratory data of the patients in the two groups at baseline</title><p>The values are expressed in means ± SD.</p><p>TSAT: transferrin saturation, PTH: parathyroid hormone, CRP: C-reactive protein, SD: standard deviation.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Parameters
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Oral Iron Group (N = 14)
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
IV Iron Group (N = 13)
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Hb (g/dL)
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
9.82 ± 1.21
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
10.03 ± 0.66
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Ferritin (ng/mL)
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
64.45 ± 37.41
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
60.71 ± 35.89
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
TSAT (%)
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
12.89 ± 9.3
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
11.33 ± 3.05
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Serum iron (mg/L)
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.54 ± 0.25
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.5 ± 0.12
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Vitamin B12 (pg/mL)
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
378 ± 145
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
409 ± 137
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Vitamin B9 (ng/mL)
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
6.7 ± 2.8
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
6.1 ± 3.2
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Albumin (g/L)
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
39.9 ± 2.11
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
39.71 ± 4.3
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
PTH (pg/mL)
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
256 ± 96
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
298 ± 106
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
CRP (mg/L)
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
3.17 ± 2.63
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
3.8 ± 2.2
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Follow-up data</p><p>Both iron treatments were associated with a progressive increase in Hb levels (M5 versus respective M0), although to varying degrees. By the end of the treatment period, the mean increases in Hb levels (M5 versus M0) were 14.65% for the IV group and 4.78% for the OS group.</p><p>As shown in Tables <xref rid="TAB4" ref-type="table">4</xref>, <xref rid="TAB5" ref-type="table">5</xref>, the secondary analysis examines follow-up data to evaluate the effects of both oral and IV iron treatments on various laboratory parameters, including Hb levels, serum iron, TSAT, ferritin, hsCRP, and albumin.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Clinical and laboratory data in the OS group throughout the study</title><p>The values are expressed in means ± SD.</p><p>Hb: hemoglobin, TSAT: transferrin saturation, CRP: C-reactive protein.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">  Parameters</td><td colspan="8" rowspan="1">Oral Iron Group (N=14)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chi-Square Value</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hb (g/dL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.82 ± 1.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.88 ± 1.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.94 ± 1.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.04 ± 1.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.32 ± 1,46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.29 ± 1.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.68</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin (ng/mL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.45 ± 37.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.72 ± 66.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.65 ± 33.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.45 ± 78.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.36 ± 61.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.90 ± 64.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.399</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.14</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum iron (mg/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54 ± 0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70 ± 0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60 ± 0.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56 ± 0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57 ± 0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61 ± 0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.57</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TSAT (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.89 ± 9.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.12 ± 9.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.56 ± 4.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.28 ± 4.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.52 ± 6.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.19 ± 5.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.057</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.72</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Albumin (g/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.9 ± 2.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.18 ± 2.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 ± 2.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.18 ± 2.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.45 ± 2,46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40  ± 1.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.436</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.83</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRP (mg/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.17 ± 2,63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.77 ± 12.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.35 ± 2.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.78 ± 2.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.35 ± 2.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.37 ± 1.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.839</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.07</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><title>Clinical and laboratory data in the IV group throughout the study</title><p>The values are expressed in means ± SD.</p><p>Hb: hemoglobin, TSAT: transferrin saturation, CRP: C-reactive protein.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">  Parameters</td><td colspan="8" rowspan="1">IV Iron Group (N=13)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chi-Square Value</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hb (g/dL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.03 ± 0.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.86 ± 0.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.57 ± 0.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.62 ± 0.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.65 ± 0.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.50 ± 0.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.049</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin (ng/mL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.71 ± 35.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">189.85 ± 116.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">233.28± 148.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">242.85 ± 134.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">282.85 ± 100.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">289.42 ± 103.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.98</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum iron (mg/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 ± 0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66 ± 0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74± 0.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83 ± 0.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67 ± 0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80 ± 0.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.099</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.26</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TSAT (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.33 ± 3.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.00 ± 2.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.33 ± 1.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.33 ± 7.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.66 ± 6.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.45 ± 6.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.031</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.28</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Albumin (g/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.71 ± 4.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.00 ± 4.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.85 ± 5.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.4 ± 3.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.71 ± 5.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.85 ± 4.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.696</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.02</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRP (mg/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.85 ± 2.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.44 ± 9.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.94 ± 1.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.64 ± 1.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.45 ± 1.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.48 ± 1.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.494</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.39</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>In the oral treatment group (Group OS), hemoglobin (Hb) levels showed a gradual and significant increase from M0 to M5, reaching 10.29 ± 1.61 g/dL (p=0.003), with minimal changes observed at M1, M2, and M3, and a more noticeable rise between M3 and M4. Ferritin levels displayed a consistent yet non-significant upward trend from M0 (64.45 ± 37.41 ng/mL) to M5 (92.90 ± 64.60 ng/mL) (p=0.399), while TSAT increased from M0 (12.89 ± 9.3%) to M5 (14.19 ± 5.12%), approaching but not reaching statistical significance (p=0.057). In the IV iron treatment group (Group IV), Hb levels consistently and significantly increased from M0 to M5, plateauing at 11.50 ± 0.96 g/dL (p=0.049). Ferritin levels rose significantly from M0 (60.71 ± 35.89 ng/mL) to M5 (289.42 ± 103.13 ng/mL) (p=0.0001), and TSAT levels increased significantly from M0 (11.33 ± 3.05%) to M5 (17.00 ± 6.92%) (p=0.031). These changes are illustrated in Figure <xref rid="FIG2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. Throughout the study, albumin and hsCRP levels remained stable.</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Effects of IV (Group IV, red lines) and oral liposomal iron (Group OS, blue lines) on hemoglobin (A), ferritin (B), and TSAT (C) throughout the study</title><p>Data are expressed as means.</p><p>M0, baseline levels; M1, M2, and M3, values after one, two, and three months of follow-up with both drugs; M4, one month after drug withdrawal; M5, two months after drug withdrawal.</p><p>TSAT: transferrin saturation.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000070114-i02.jpg"><?image-name cureus-0016-00000070114-i02.jpg?><?image-size 69092?><?image-md5 129928fb72111d67509f8a44d5a7124f?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 3872?><?image-original-width 3000?><?image-scaled-height 968?><?image-scaled-width 750?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/5cbe/11501097/129928fb7211/cureus-0016-00000070114-i02.jpg?><?thumb-name cureus-0016-00000070114-i02.gif?><?thumb-size 2933?><?thumb-md5 fadc089b61a6ad4af97f30d149706966?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 129?><?thumb-scaled-width 100?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/5cbe/11501097/fadc089b61a6/cureus-0016-00000070114-i02.gif?></graphic></fig><p>Data after drug withdrawal</p><p>In the post-treatment follow-up period at M4 and M5, distinct alterations in key biochemical markers were evident in both the OS and IV groups. At M4 and M5, the oral iron (Group OS) cohort displayed a stable trend in Hb levels, showing minimal deviation. Similarly, the IV iron (Group IV) treatment group maintained steady Hb levels from M4 to M5. Ferritin levels demonstrated a marginal change in the oral iron group, remaining relatively stable with little deviation between M4 and M5. In contrast, the IV iron group exhibited a consistent increase in ferritin levels from M4 to M5. Both treatment groups displayed fluctuations in TSAT levels. In the oral iron group, TSAT decreased from M4 to M5, while the IV iron group demonstrated stability in TSAT over the same period.</p><p>Adverse effects</p><p>In Group IV, which received IV iron, hypotension was the most prevalent adverse event, affecting four patients (30.7%). This was followed by infusion site reactions in three patients (23%) and headaches, also in three patients (23%). In contrast, Group OS, treated with oral iron, reported constipation as the most frequent adverse event in four patients (28.4%), followed by abdominal pain in three patients (21.4%) and headaches in two patients (14.2%). Notably, diarrhea and vertigo were absent in Group IV, whereas they were present in Group OS. A summary of adverse events experienced by patients in both treatment groups is provided in Table <xref rid="TAB6" ref-type="table">6</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB6" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6</label><caption><title>Adverse events in the OS and IV groups</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adverse Event, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oral Iron Group (N=14)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV Iron Group (N=13)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constipation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (28.4%)  </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (15.3%)  </td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diarrhea</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (7.1%)  </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)  </td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abdominal pain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (21.4%)  </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)  </td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infusion site reaction</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)  </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (23%)  </td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Headache</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (14.2%)  </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (23%)  </td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vertigo</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (7.1%)  </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)  </td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypotension</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (7.1%)  </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (30.7%)  </td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Anemia is frequently associated with CKD, significantly impacting cardiovascular health and increasing hospitalization rates among these patients. Addressing CKD-related anemia is a crucial aspect of patient care, with the National Kidney Foundation Kidney Disease Outcome Quality Initiative guidelines advocating for oral or IV iron supplementation as essential in managing iron-deficient anemic CKD patients [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Previous research has highlighted the similar efficacy of oral and IV iron supplements in correcting iron deficiency anemia (IDA) associated with CKD [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p><p>Despite numerous studies investigating the effectiveness of IV iron therapy in rectifying iron deficiencies and managing anemia in non-dialysis CKD populations, there remains a notable gap in comparative analyses between IV and oral iron therapies. This gap contributes to ongoing confusion, with studies drawing disparate conclusions due to varied parameters such as initial Hb levels, study duration, participants' iron status, sample sizes, and differences in IV iron formulations [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>-<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p>Clinical evidence consistently supports the superiority of IV iron over oral iron therapy in hemodialysis-dependent CKD patients. The limited absorption and slow incorporation of orally administered iron into the red cell mass in hemodialysis patients, especially without epoetin therapy, highlight the practical advantages of IV iron administration. Unlike oral iron, IV iron ensures complete absorption and utilization, avoiding issues related to inadequate absorption due to chelation by intraluminal cations or interference by certain medications. Additionally, by bypassing the gastrointestinal tract, IV iron reduces the risk of adverse gastrointestinal symptoms associated with oral iron supplementation, enhancing patient tolerance and compliance [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p><p>Moreover, IV iron therapy offers logistical advantages, particularly in patients unable to maintain adequate iron stores with oral supplementation. Current guidelines recommend IV iron for patients who fail to achieve sufficient iron status with oral supplementation. Despite the potential inconvenience of IV administration, recent studies have demonstrated the feasibility and safety of rapid IV iron administration, particularly in outpatient settings: administering 200 mg of iron sucrose intravenously over five minutes has been shown to be well-tolerated and convenient, minimizing the challenges of IV iron therapy, especially in outpatient settings [<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><p>Despite the efficacy and advantages of IV iron therapy, it may not be suitable for all patients. The IV route can be inconvenient or uncomfortable, particularly with prolonged infusion durations or concerns about potential allergic reactions [<xref rid="REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Alternatively, oral iron therapy, although less efficient and associated with gastrointestinal side effects, may be preferred due to its convenience and familiarity. Moreover, oral iron therapy typically results in lower overall costs compared to IV therapy, largely due to reduced hospitalizations and associated healthcare needs. Additionally, the risk of anaphylactic or hypersensitivity reactions, although rare, can deter patients from opting for IV iron therapy [<xref rid="REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].</p><p>Studies highlighting the limitations of non-liposomal oral iron formulations have raised concerns about their effectiveness in replenishing iron stores due to challenges in absorption, gastrointestinal side effects, non-compliance, and the prevalent inflammation seen in ND-CKD patients [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. However, the emergence of liposomal iron offers promise as a new frontier in oral iron formulations. Utilizing ferric pyrophosphate enclosed within a phospholipid and sucrose esters of the fatty acid membrane, this innovative technology bypasses direct gastrointestinal interaction, facilitating direct intestinal absorption. The specialized architecture of liposomal iron ensures uptake by specific M cells in the small intestine, enabling its transport to hepatocytes, where enzymatic breakdown releases the encapsulated iron for utilization [<xref rid="REF18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p><p>Our primary objective in conducting this prospective randomized trial was to assess the impact of both IV and liposomal oral iron on Hb levels in non-dialysis CKD patients. We also aimed to compare their efficacy in correcting Hb levels, assess patients' iron status during treatment, and evaluate their tolerance to the therapy. To ensure the reliability of our findings and avoid masking potential benefits on Hb levels, we specifically targeted patients with stable PTH levels corresponding to their CKD stage, maintaining a balanced calcium-phosphate ratio without any signs of inflammation.</p><p>Our results suggest that oral liposomal iron is non-inferior to IV iron in increasing Hb levels, albeit with a slower and less pronounced rise. Notably, IV iron demonstrated superior efficacy in replenishing iron stores, as evidenced by the substantial and quicker increases in ferritin and TSAT. This reinforces the idea that while oral liposomal iron is a viable alternative for correcting anemia, particularly in non-dialysis CKD patients, IV iron showcases swifter and more robust iron store replenishment.</p><p>While oral liposomal iron appears non-inferior to IV iron in correcting anemia, it is important to consider the broader clinical context and potential limitations of oral iron therapy. Traditional oral iron formulations are associated with poor absorption, gastrointestinal side effects, and variable efficacy, particularly in CKD patients who may have impaired iron absorption due to underlying inflammation or comorbidities. In contrast, liposomal oral iron formulations have been developed to improve bioavailability and reduce gastrointestinal side effects, offering a more tolerable and effective alternative to traditional oral iron preparations [<xref rid="REF19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].</p><p>Several formulations of IV iron are currently available for the treatment of IDA in patients with CKD. These formulations include ferric carboxymaltose (FCM), ferric gluconate (FG), ferumoxytol, iron sucrose (IS), ferric derisomaltose/iron isomaltoside, and low molecular weight iron dextran (LMW ID). Each formulation has its unique pharmacokinetic and safety profile, making them suitable for different clinical scenarios [<xref rid="REF20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>-<xref rid="REF22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p><p>The choice of IS as the IV iron formulation for this study was influenced by multiple factors, including its proven efficacy and favorable safety profile. Comparative trials involving other IV iron formulations, such as ferumoxytol and FCM, have shown them to be similarly effective in increasing Hb levels, with comparable safety profiles [<xref rid="REF23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Additionally, iron sucrose is noted for its high tolerability and low incidence of adverse events [<xref rid="REF24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="REF25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. These characteristics, combined with its widespread clinical use and availability, made IS the preferred agent for our trial. Its prevalent use in treating iron deficiency anemia in CKD patients aligns well with the demographic focus of our study on non-dialysis CKD patients.</p><p>Our study results were assessed alongside findings from four additional studies to gain more comprehensive insights into managing iron deficiency anemia in CKD patients. These studies, conducted in Italy, India, and the United States, examined various treatment strategies, including oral liposomal iron, IV iron, and oral non-liposomal iron, considering geographical and clinical differences across different populations [<xref rid="REF26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>-<xref rid="REF29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].</p><p>The trends identified in the follow-up data from these studies reveal notable similarities with our findings. Pisani’s research emphasizes that oral liposomal iron is a safe and effective option for correcting anemia in non-dialysis CKD patients but acknowledges that IV iron is superior in rapidly replenishing body iron stores and accelerating iron repletion [<xref rid="REF26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. This aligns with our study, which also demonstrates that IV iron is more effective for rapid iron repletion compared to oral alternatives.</p><p>Similarly, both our study and Qunibi's research confirm that IV iron leads to a more pronounced and rapid increase in Hb levels compared to oral iron formulations [<xref rid="REF27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. The Agrawal study further supports these findings by highlighting the particularly significant impact of IV iron in specific patient populations, such as those with CKD on dialysis, where it induces a faster and more substantial increase in Hb levels [<xref rid="REF28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].</p><p>In contrast, Charytan's research indicates that CKD patients receiving IV iron experienced increases in both Hb and ferritin, while those on oral iron saw increases in Hb without corresponding increases in iron stores [<xref rid="REF29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].</p><p>Our study presents several limitations that warrant careful consideration. The small sample size restricts the generalizability of our findings to the broader CKD population. Additionally, the highly selective nature of the patient groups may not fully reflect the diversity encountered in clinical practice. While this selection minimized confounding factors related to renal anemia, such as inflammation, it limited our ability to evaluate the efficacy of liposomal iron in inflammatory states, which is a significant consideration, as inflammation commonly impairs iron absorption and utilization in CKD patients. Furthermore, while a subgroup analysis by CKD stage would be insightful, given the small numbers within each stage group, such analysis would lack statistical robustness. This limitation is pertinent as oral bioavailability of treatments typically decreases with advancing CKD stages due to multifactorial influences. Therefore, these analyses would be more appropriately conducted within larger, more diverse cohorts.</p><p>Secondly, the study did not investigate the potential effects of oxidative stress between the two types of iron or their impact on eGFR. Previous studies have reported conflicting results regarding the influence of iron on renal function, with some small-scale investigations suggesting that IV iron therapy may adversely affect renal tubular function and increase proteinuria [<xref rid="REF30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].</p><p>Thirdly, due to the short follow-up period, it is uncertain whether the beneficial effects of liposomal iron observed in this study will persist long-term and significantly impact CKD outcomes. Longer-duration trials involving more patients would be necessary to address this question.</p><p>Finally, it is worth noting that this study did not compare liposomal iron to other oral iron formulations. Such a comparison could provide valuable insights into the relative efficacy and safety of different iron supplementation strategies.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The management of anemia in CKD requires careful consideration of several factors, including the method of iron administration and the choice of treatment regimen. Our study findings suggest that oral liposomal iron presents a feasible alternative for treating anemia in non-dialysis CKD patients. Although it may not achieve the rapid and substantial iron repletion observed with IV iron, its lower incidence of adverse events, greater convenience, and reduced cost make it an attractive option for initial anemia management in uncomplicated CKD cases. Additionally, using oral iron instead of IV iron in CKD patients helps preserve venous capital, as oral administration eliminates the need for venous access for IV infusions, thereby reducing the risk of vascular damage and protecting vein integrity over time.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group content-type="conflict"><title>Disclosures</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Human subjects:</bold> Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Comite D’ethique Hospitalo-Universitaire Fes issued approval 01/20. This study was approved by the Ethics Committee of the Faculty of Medicine, Pharmacy, and Dentistry at Sidi Mohamed Ben Abdellah University. A total of 31 patients with chronic kidney disease (CKD) and anemia were enrolled between 2021 and 2023 at the Nephrology, Dialysis, and Transplantation Department of Hassan II University Hospital in Fez, Morocco. Informed consent was obtained from all participants in accordance with institutional guidelines. The study was conducted in compliance with the approved protocols and adhered to the principles outlined in the Declaration of Helsinki.</p><p><bold>Animal subjects:</bold> All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue.</p><p><bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold> In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following:</p><p><bold>Payment/services info:</bold> All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Financial relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Other relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</bold>  Soufiane Bengelloun Zahr, Ghita El Bardai, Yassine Allata, Basmat Amal Chouhani , Tarik Sqalli Houssaini, Nadia Kabbali, Mouna El Mansoury</p><p><bold>Drafting of the manuscript:</bold>  Soufiane Bengelloun Zahr</p><p><bold>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</bold>  Soufiane Bengelloun Zahr, Ghita El Bardai, Yassine Allata, Basmat Amal Chouhani , Tarik Sqalli Houssaini, Nadia Kabbali, Mouna El Mansoury</p><p><bold>Concept and design:</bold>  Ghita El Bardai, Yassine Allata, Basmat Amal Chouhani , Tarik Sqalli Houssaini, Nadia Kabbali</p><p><bold>Supervision:</bold>  Ghita El Bardai, Yassine Allata, Basmat Amal Chouhani , Tarik Sqalli Houssaini, Nadia Kabbali, Mouna El Mansoury</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Normalization of hemoglobin level in patients with chronic kidney disease and anemia</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Drüeke</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Locatelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Clyne</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>2071</fpage><lpage>2084</lpage><volume>355</volume><year>2006</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17108342</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMoa062276</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>An overview on safety issues related to erythropoiesis-stimulating agents for the treatment of anaemia in patients with chronic kidney disease</article-title><source>Expert Opin Drug Saf</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Del Vecchio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Locatelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1021</fpage><lpage>1030</lpage><volume>15</volume><year>2016</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27149639</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/14740338.2016.1182494</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Erythropoiesis-stimulating agent hyporesponsiveness and adverse outcomes: guilty as charged?</article-title><source>Kidney Med</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wish</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>526</fpage><lpage>528</lpage><volume>2</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33090128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.xkme.2020.08.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7568056</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Chapter 2: Use of iron to treat anemia in CKD</article-title><source>Kidney Int Suppl</source><fpage>292</fpage><lpage>298</lpage><volume>2</volume><year>2012</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/kisup.2012.34</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4089602</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25018949</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Ferumoxytol for treating iron deficiency anemia in CKD</article-title><source>J Am Soc Nephrol</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Spinowitz</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kausz</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Baptista</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>1599</fpage><lpage>1605</lpage><volume>19</volume><year>2008</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18525001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1681/ASN.2007101156</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2488268</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>A randomized, controlled trial comparing IV iron sucrose to oral iron in anemic patients with nondialysis-dependent CKD</article-title><source>Kidney Int</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Van Wyck</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Roppolo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mazey</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McMurray</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>2846</fpage><lpage>2856</lpage><volume>68</volume><year>2005</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16316362</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1523-1755.2005.00758.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>A comparative look at the safety profiles of intravenous iron products used in the hemodialysis population</article-title><source>Ann Pharmacother</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Coppol</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shelly</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kaakeh</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shepler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>247</lpage><volume>45</volume><year>2011</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21304025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1345/aph.1P466</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The importance of iron in long-term survival of maintenance hemodialysis patients treated with epoetin-alfa and intravenous iron: analysis of 9.5 years of prospectively collected data</article-title><source>BMC Nephrol</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pollak</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lorch</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Satwah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>6</fpage><volume>10</volume><year>2009</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19245700</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2369-10-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2671502</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The safety of intravenous iron sucrose use in the elderly patient</article-title><source>Consult Pharm</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Charytan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>230</fpage><lpage>238</lpage><volume>22</volume><year>2007</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17658969</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4140/tcp.n.2007.230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Treatment of iron deficiency anemia in CKD and end-stage kidney disease</article-title><source>Kidney Int Rep</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gutiérrez</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>2261</fpage><lpage>2269</lpage><volume>6</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34514189</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ekir.2021.05.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8418942</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Anemia and iron deficiency among chronic kidney disease Stages 3-5ND patients in the Chronic Kidney Disease Outcomes and Practice Patterns Study: often unmeasured, variably treated</article-title><source>Clin Kidney J</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>613</fpage><lpage>624</lpage><volume>13</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32905241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ckj/sfz091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7467578</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Efficacy and safety of intravenous iron sucrose in treating adults with iron deficiency anemia</article-title><source>Rev Bras Hematol Hemoter</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cançado</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>de Figueiredo</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Olivato</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chiattone</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>439</fpage><lpage>443</lpage><volume>33</volume><year>2011</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23049360</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5581/1516-8484.20110119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3459362</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Safety and efficacy of intravenous ferric derisomaltose compared to iron sucrose for iron deficiency anemia in patients with chronic kidney disease with and without heart failure</article-title><source>Am J Cardiol</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ambrosy</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>von Haehling</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kalra</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Court</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bhandari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McDonagh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cleland</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>138</fpage><lpage>145</lpage><volume>152</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34162484</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.amjcard.2021.04.042</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Safety concerns about intravenous iron therapy in patients with chronic kidney disease</article-title><source>Clin Kidney J</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Del Vecchio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Longhi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Locatelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>260</fpage><lpage>267</lpage><volume>9</volume><year>2016</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26985378</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ckj/sfv142</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4792617</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Novel oral iron therapies for iron deficiency anemia in chronic kidney disease</article-title><source>Adv Chronic Kidney Dis</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pergola</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fishbane</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ganz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>272</fpage><lpage>291</lpage><volume>26</volume><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31477258</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/j.ackd.2019.05.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Comparative safety of intravenous ferumoxytol versus ferric carboxymaltose in iron deficiency anemia: a randomized trial</article-title><source>Am J Hematol</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Adkinson</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Macdougall</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>683</fpage><lpage>690</lpage><volume>93</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29417614</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ajh.25060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5947731</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Strategies for iron supplementation: oral versus intravenous</article-title><source>Kidney Int Suppl</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Macdougall</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><volume>69</volume><year>1999</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1523-1755.1999.055suppl.69061.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10084288</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Recent and emerging therapies for iron deficiency in anemia of CKD: a review</article-title><source>Am J Kidney Dis</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bazeley</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wish</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>868</fpage><lpage>876</lpage><volume>79</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34758368</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/j.ajkd.2021.09.017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Efficacy and safety of oral supplementation with liposomal iron in non-dialysis chronic kidney disease patients with iron deficiency</article-title><source>Nutrients</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cesarano</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Borrelli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Campilongo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><volume>16</volume><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/nu16091255</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11085822</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38732502</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Intravenous iron supplementation therapy</article-title><source>Mol Aspects Med</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schaefer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Meindl</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tilg</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zoller</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>100862</fpage><volume>75</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32444112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.mam.2020.100862</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Differences between intravenous iron products: focus on treatment of iron deficiency in chronic heart failure patients</article-title><source>ESC Heart Fail</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Martin-Malo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Borchard</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Flühmann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Silverberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jankowska</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>253</lpage><volume>6</volume><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30694615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ehf2.12400</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6437426</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Analysis of adverse events and intravenous iron infusion formulations in adults with and without prior infusion reactions</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Arastu</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Elstrott</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>5</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.4488</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8968468</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35353168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of iron preparations</article-title><source>Pharmaceutics</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Geisser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Burckhardt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><volume>3</volume><year>2011</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24310424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/pharmaceutics3010012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3857035</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Intravenous iron infusion in patients with heart failure: a systematic review and study-level meta-analysis</article-title><source>ESC Heart Fail</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Salah</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Savarese</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rosano</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ambrosy</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mentz</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fudim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1473</fpage><lpage>1480</lpage><volume>10</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36734033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ehf2.14310</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10053151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Iron sucrose: a wealth of experience in treating iron deficiency</article-title><source>Adv Ther</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Macdougall</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Comin-Colet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Breymann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Spahn</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Koutroubakis</surname><given-names>IE</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1960</fpage><lpage>2002</lpage><volume>37</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32297281</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12325-020-01323-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7467495</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Effect of oral liposomal iron versus intravenous iron for treatment of iron deficiency anaemia in CKD patients: a randomized trial</article-title><source>Nephrol Dial Transplant</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pisani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Riccio</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sabbatini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Andreucci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Del Rio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Visciano</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>645</fpage><lpage>652</lpage><volume>30</volume><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25395392</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ndt/gfu357</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>A randomized controlled trial comparing intravenous ferric carboxymaltose with oral iron for treatment of iron deficiency anaemia of non-dialysis-dependent chronic kidney disease patients</article-title><source>Nephrol Dial Transplant</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Qunibi</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Benjamin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mangione</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Roger</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1599</fpage><lpage>1607</lpage><volume>26</volume><year>2011</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20929915</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ndt/gfq613</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3084440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Efficacy of oral versus injectable iron in patients with chronic kidney disease: a two-year cross-sectional study conducted at a rural teaching hospital</article-title><source>Cureus</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sonawane</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>14</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7759/cureus.27529</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9427239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36060352</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Comparison of intravenous iron sucrose to oral iron in the treatment of anemic patients with chronic kidney disease not on dialysis</article-title><source>Nephron Clin Pract</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Charytan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Qunibi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bailie</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><volume>100</volume><year>2005</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1159/000085049</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15824508</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The impact of intravenous iron on renal injury and function markers in patients with chronic kidney disease and iron deficiency without anemia</article-title><source>Kidney Int Rep</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kassianides</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hazara</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Macdougall</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kalra</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bhandari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>322</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><volume>7</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35155871</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ekir.2021.11.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8820978</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>