
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" article-type="review-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2757</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">cureus</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cureus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-8184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cureus Inc.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC13134476</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC13134476.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">13134476</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">13134476</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">42078226</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.106291</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Obstetrics/Gynecology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Hematology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Pharmacology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Intravenous and Oral Iron Strategies for Iron-Deficiency Anemia in Pregnancy: A Systematic Review of Randomized Controlled Trials From a Hematology Perspective</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names initials="A">Alexander</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adler</surname><given-names initials="JR">John R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guerra Toro</surname><given-names initials="HI">Hector I</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaramillo</surname><given-names initials="AP">Arturo P</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pazmino</surname><given-names initials="G">Genesis</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caceres</surname><given-names initials="VM">Valeria M</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label>
General Medicine, La Pontificia Universidad Católica del Ecuador, Quito, ECU </aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label>
General Medicine, Universidad Estatal de Guayaquil, Guayaquil, ECU </aff><aff id="aff-3">
<label>3</label>
General Medicine, University of the Americas, Quito, ECU </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Arturo P. Jaramillo <email>drapjz@gmail.com</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>1</day><month>4</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>4</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>18</volume><issue>4</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">510775</issue-id><elocation-id>e106291</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>1</day><month>4</month><year>2026</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>04</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>02</day><month>05</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-05-04 15:25:16.243"><day>04</day><month>05</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2026, Guerra Toro et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2026</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Guerra Toro et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License CC-BY 4.0., which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="cureus-0018-00000106291.pdf"><?pdf-name cureus-0018-00000106291.pdf?><?pdf-size 762376?><?pdf-md5 d2e14e6ea0da826a8f3bb5bf35ff4873?><?pdf-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?pdf-cloudpmc-urn urn:app:e98a/13134476/d2e14e6ea0da/cureus-0018-00000106291.pdf?></self-uri><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://cureus.com/articles/477101-intravenous-and-oral-iron-strategies-for-iron-deficiency-anemia-in-pregnancy-a-systematic-review-of-randomized-controlled-trials-from-a-hematology-perspective">This article is available from https://cureus.com/articles/477101-intravenous-and-oral-iron-strategies-for-iron-deficiency-anemia-in-pregnancy-a-systematic-review-of-randomized-controlled-trials-from-a-hematology-perspective</self-uri><abstract><p>Iron-deficiency anemia is the most common hematologic disorder in pregnancy. Slow iron repletion, poor gastrointestinal tolerance, and late presentation during gestation often limit the effectiveness of oral ferrous salts, which remain the traditional first-line treatment. Intravenous iron offers faster iron delivery, but its role in routine antenatal care remains uncertain, particularly regarding its long-term safety and cost-effectiveness compared to traditional oral iron treatments. This qualitative systematic review included 10 randomized controlled trials published within the last decade that enrolled pregnant women with iron-deficiency anemia or persistent iron deficiency (defined, where applicable, as ferritin &lt;30 μg/L after approximately four weeks of oral iron therapy) and compared intravenous iron with oral iron or one intravenous formulation with another. Across the included trials, intravenous iron generally produced more rapid ferritin replenishment and, in many studies, a faster rise in hemoglobin than oral therapy. Oral ferrous preparations were associated with more gastrointestinal adverse effects; for example, in one study, gastrointestinal treatment-related events were reported in more women receiving oral ferrous sulfate versus those receiving ferric carboxymaltose. In another trial, nausea/vomiting occurred in greater number of oral-iron recipients versus intravenous ones, while constipation and epigastric discomfort were reported only in the oral group. By contrast, serious intravenous treatment-related events were uncommon in the larger trials.​ ​Smaller and medium-sized trials generally favored parenteral iron for hematologic recovery, but the largest pragmatic studies from India, Malawi, and Nigeria showed that biochemical superiority did not consistently translate into lower rates of late-pregnancy anemia or improved major maternal and neonatal outcomes. One head-to-head intravenous trial also suggested practical and hematologic advantages of ferric carboxymaltose over iron sucrose. From a hematology perspective, intravenous iron appears most useful when rapid restoration of iron stores is needed, when adherence to oral therapy is doubtful, or when little time remains before delivery. Future trials should standardize ferritin-based diagnostic criteria, clearly distinguish hematologic from obstetric endpoints, and better define which patients are most likely to derive clinically meaningful benefit from parenteral iron.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>ferrous sulfate supplements</kwd><kwd>hematology and oncology</kwd><kwd>intravenous iron sucrose (ivis)</kwd><kwd>iron deficiency anemia (ida)</kwd><kwd>iron-deficiency anemia in pregnancy</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction and background</title><p>Iron-deficiency anemia (IDA) is the most common hematologic disorder encountered in pregnancy and remains a frequent reason for specialty consultation in women of reproductive age. Globally, approximately one-third of pregnant women are affected by anemia, and iron deficiency contributes substantially to that burden, particularly in settings where nutritional inadequacy, short birth spacing, parasitic disease, and inconsistent antenatal follow-up coexist [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. From a hematology perspective, pregnancy-related iron deficiency is clinically important not only because hemoglobin falls but also because maternal erythropoiesis must expand while iron is simultaneously diverted toward placental growth and fetal development. When that demand is not met, the consequences can include reduced oxygen-carrying capacity, fatigue, poor functional tolerance, impaired cognition, and greater peripartum vulnerability, while the fetus may face lower birth weight and reduced neonatal iron stores [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p><p>The physiology of pregnancy helps explain why standard oral therapy is often less effective than expected in routine practice. Maternal red cell mass rises progressively, total iron requirements accelerate during the second and third trimesters, and many women present only after stores are already depleted. Even with pregnancy-associated suppression of hepcidin, the amount of elemental iron that can be absorbed from oral preparations may be insufficient to correct moderate deficiency quickly, particularly late in gestation. In addition, ferrous salts commonly cause nausea, epigastric discomfort, constipation, and poor tolerability, which undermines adherence outside controlled settings [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. As a result, oral iron may be less effective in women who present later in gestation, remain iron deficient despite prior supplementation, or have insufficient time before delivery for gradual repletion to achieve meaningful hematologic correction.</p><p>These limitations have renewed interest in intravenous (IV) iron formulations that bypass the gastrointestinal tract and deliver larger amounts of bioavailable iron over a shorter period. Iron sucrose has long been used because of its reassuring safety profile, whereas ferric carboxymaltose and ferric derisomaltose offer the practical advantage of high single-dose administration. For hematologists, this is relevant because treatment success in pregnancy is not defined by hemoglobin alone. Restoration of storage iron is also essential. Compared with oral therapy, IV iron produced larger short-term hematologic gains in representative trials; for example, hemoglobin rose by 22 versus 12 g/L at four weeks in Bhavi and Jaju [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], while in Chawla et al. [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], ferritin increased by 332.4 versus 62.9 ng/mL at three weeks and hemoglobin by 2.7 versus 1.6 g/dL at six weeks, supporting a practical advantage when the interval to delivery is limited. This may be especially useful in women with symptomatic anemia, previous oral treatment failure, ongoing inflammation, poor adherence, or late gestational presentation [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>-<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The key question, however, is whether this biologic advantage is consistent enough across randomized trials to support broader clinical use.</p><p>The recent trial literature offers both encouragement and caution. Smaller randomized studies have repeatedly shown faster hemoglobin recovery and markedly greater ferritin repletion with IV iron sucrose or ferric carboxymaltose than with oral ferrous salts [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>-<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Bhavi and Jaju reported larger gains in hemoglobin and iron stores with IV iron sucrose than with oral ferrous fumarate after four weeks [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The international FERric carboxymaltose-Assessment of SAfety and efficacy in Pregnancy (FER-ASAP) trial found that ferric carboxymaltose achieved anemia correction more often and more rapidly than oral ferrous sulfate, while causing fewer gastrointestinal adverse effects and better patient-reported vitality [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Such findings align with daily hematology practice, where the speed of biochemical correction often matters as much as the eventual hemoglobin plateau.</p><p>Yet, larger pragmatic trials have shown that hematologic superiority does not automatically translate into major clinical benefits. In India, Neogi and colleagues randomized more than 2,000 women with moderate-to-severe anemia and found no reduction in the primary maternal composite outcome with IV iron sucrose compared with standard oral therapy [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Large African trials of ferric carboxymaltose reported a similar pattern: better correction of iron deficiency and IDA, but no clear or uniform benefit for late-gestation anemia prevalence, preterm birth, or birthweight, while the large Indian phase three trial did not show improvement in the primary maternal composite outcome [<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Improving iron levels can be very effective, but overall pregnancy outcomes may still not change if the anemia has multiple causes, normal pregnancy-related blood dilution continues, or the results are measured late in pregnancy after other factors have already affected the outcome.</p><p>Another challenge is the clinical, methodological, and endpoint heterogeneity of the available evidence: the included trials used different hemoglobin and ferritin eligibility thresholds, enrolled women at different gestational stages, compared different IV and oral regimens, administered different cumulative doses, and assessed outcomes at different follow-up intervals. The trials varied in baseline hemoglobin thresholds, ferritin cutoffs, gestational age at enrollment, cumulative iron dose, formulation type, and follow-up duration. Most compared IV therapy with oral ferrous sulfate or ferrous fumarate, but some compared two IV preparations directly [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>-<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Accordingly, the included trials must be interpreted across distinct endpoint domains, including hematologic outcomes such as ferritin recovery and anemia correction, obstetric outcomes such as gestational age and birthweight, and patient-centered outcomes such as tolerability, convenience, and symptom improvement. Hematologists may focus on ferritin recovery, anemia correction, and avoidance of severe anemia or transfusion. Obstetric clinicians may prioritize gestational age, birthweight, and postpartum morbidity. Patients may value tolerability, convenience, and speed of symptom improvement. A qualitative systematic review is useful in this context because it allows those priorities to be interpreted side by side rather than collapsed into a single pooled effect estimate.</p><p>The therapeutic landscape has also changed over the last decade. Earlier antenatal practice relied heavily on iron sucrose, which often requires multiple visits to replete the total iron deficit. Newer formulations, particularly ferric carboxymaltose and ferric derisomaltose, can deliver larger replacement doses in a single encounter, which may be highly relevant in busy clinics and low-resource settings [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Even so, convenience alone should not determine treatment selection. A hematology-guided approach still must weigh the severity of anemia, certainty that iron deficiency is truly present, infusion logistics, risk of adverse reactions, and the amount of time remaining before delivery.</p><p>Accordingly, the present systematic review synthesizes randomized evidence from the last 10 years on IV and oral iron strategies for pregnancy-related iron deficiency, with explicit emphasis on hematologic endpoints and clinical interpretation. The review addresses three key clinical questions: whether IV iron produces a faster or more reliable hemoglobin response than oral therapy, whether iron-store recovery consistently favors parenteral treatment, and whether those benefits are accompanied by acceptable tolerability and meaningful maternal or neonatal advantage.</p></sec><sec sec-type="review"><title>Review</title><p>Study design</p><p>This manuscript was developed as a qualitative systematic review of randomized trials evaluating therapeutic iron strategies in pregnancy and was reported in accordance with the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) 2020 framework [<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Quantitative pooling was not undertaken because the included studies showed substantial clinical, methodological, and endpoint heterogeneity, including differences in hemoglobin and ferritin eligibility thresholds, gestational age at enrollment, IV formulation, cumulative iron dose, oral comparator regimen, follow-up interval, and the outcomes prioritized for analysis. This review was not prospectively registered in International Prospective Register of Systematic Reviews (PROSPERO). It was conducted as a focused qualitative systematic review organized around the 10 eligible full-text randomized trials retained for synthesis, and no meta-analysis was planned because of the narrative design and the substantial heterogeneity across studies.</p><p>Information sources and search approach</p><p>PubMed, Embase, and the Cochrane Library were searched for eligible studies. The search was limited to studies published within the last 10 years to reflect the contemporary therapeutic era of antenatal iron replacement. All database searches were last run on February 2, 2026. Search strategies were adapted to the syntax of each database and combined controlled vocabulary terms with free-text keywords using Boolean operators. In PubMed, MeSH terms such as “Anemia, Iron-Deficiency” and “Pregnancy” were combined with free-text terms including iron deficiency anemia, pregnancy, intravenous iron, oral iron, iron sucrose, ferric carboxymaltose, and ferric derisomaltose, using AND and OR, with exclusion of animal-only records using NOT. PubMed also applied a randomized-trial filter. Embase searches used corresponding Emtree terms and title/abstract/keyword fields, whereas CENTRAL searches used MeSH descriptors and keyword combinations within the trials register.</p><p>Eligibility criteria</p><p>Studies were eligible if they were randomized controlled trials published within the last 10 years, a time window selected to capture the contemporary era of antenatal iron therapy, including newer IV formulations such as ferric carboxymaltose and ferric derisomaltose and modern high-dose replacement strategies. Eligible trials enrolled pregnant participants with IDA or persistent iron deficiency, defined according to each study’s prespecified hematologic criteria, most commonly low ferritin; where explicitly operationalized, persistent iron deficiency referred to ferritin &lt;30 μg/L after prior oral iron therapy. Because transferrin saturation (TSAT) was not reported uniformly across the included trials, it was not used as a mandatory review-level eligibility threshold, although it was extracted descriptively when available. Differences in iron formulation, cumulative replacement dose, number of infusions, and oral elemental iron regimen were recorded during data extraction because they were clinically meaningful and contributed to between-study heterogeneity. Non-randomized studies, postpartum-only trials, non-English reports, and studies without extractable clinical or hematologic outcomes were excluded.</p><p>Study selection and data extraction</p><p>Study selection proceeded in two stages: title and abstract screening, followed by full-text eligibility assessment. Three reviewers screened records independently at each stage using the prespecified eligibility criteria. Any disagreements regarding eligibility were resolved through consensus discussion. Data extraction was performed independently by the three reviewers using a standardized extraction form. Extracted variables included country, sample size, gestational age, hematologic entry criteria, iron formulation, comparator regimen, cumulative dose where available, duration of follow-up, hemoglobin response, ferritin or iron-store response, adverse effects, and reported maternal or neonatal outcomes. Any disagreements in extracted data were resolved through consensus review of the full text and supplementary material.</p><p>Risk of bias assessment</p><p>Risk of bias was assessed using the original Cochrane domain-based Risk of Bias framework [<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The domains evaluated included random sequence generation, allocation concealment, blinding, incomplete outcome data, selective reporting, and other potential sources of bias. Two reviewers performed the assessment independently, and each domain was judged as low risk, high risk, or unclear risk of bias. Any disagreements were resolved through consensus discussion. Because many included trials were open-label, several studies were judged to have at least some concern for performance bias, even when laboratory outcomes were relatively objective.</p><p>Results</p><p>Literature Search and Study Selection</p><p>A total of 1,358 records were identified from PubMed, Embase, and Cochrane. Following the elimination of 58 duplicates, 1300 entries were subjected to title and abstract screening, resulting in the exclusion of 845 records. A total of 455 full-text papers were evaluated based on predetermined criteria: publication within the last decade, English language, randomized controlled design, and availability of extractable outcome data. 445 complete texts were excluded: 289 non-randomized controlled trials, 100 without extractable quantitative results, 50 in non-English languages, and six case reports or reviews. In conclusion, 10 papers fulfilled all criteria and were included in the qualitative synthesis (Figure <xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) [<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>PRISMA flow diagram used for literature search and study selection</title><p>PRISMA: Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic reviews and Meta-Analyses.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="cureus-0018-00000106291-i01.jpg"><?image-name cureus-0018-00000106291-i01.jpg?><?image-size 102872?><?image-md5 1ea0f270671883527638d0637c61199f?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 2403?><?image-original-width 3000?><?image-scaled-height 601?><?image-scaled-width 750?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/e98a/13134476/1ea0f2706718/cureus-0018-00000106291-i01.jpg?><?thumb-name cureus-0018-00000106291-i01.gif?><?thumb-size 3876?><?thumb-md5 69014abcd4b2af3d03283bdb04230d7e?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 80?><?thumb-scaled-width 100?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/e98a/13134476/69014abcd4b2/cureus-0018-00000106291-i01.gif?></graphic></fig><p>This systematic review was executed and documented in compliance with the PRISMA 2020 standards. Ten randomized trials met the eligibility criteria and were included in the final qualitative synthesis. As directed by the project materials, the study-selection workflow is displayed using the Figure <xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.</p><p>Study Characteristics</p><p>The 10 included trials were published between 2017 and 2024 and together randomized 5,311 pregnant participants. Most studies compared IV iron with oral ferrous sulfate or ferrous fumarate, whereas one trial compared ferric carboxymaltose with IV iron sucrose. Trial settings ranged from single-center hospital studies to large multicenter pragmatic trials in India, Malawi, and Nigeria. Follow-up periods ranged from four weeks to delivery and early postpartum follow-up. The dominant outcomes were hemoglobin change, ferritin or iron-store recovery, anemia correction, tolerability, and selected maternal or neonatal endpoints (Table <xref rid="TAB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Study characteristics of the included randomized trials</title><p>RCT: randomized clinical trials; FMC: Ferric Carboxymaltose; Hb: hemoglobin; IV: intravenous.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Setting / sample</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comparator</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Follow-up</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Key hematology findings</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bhavi et al., 2017 [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">India; n=112; prospective RCT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV iron sucrose 200 mg/day to calculated dose</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oral ferrous fumarate 200 mg/day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 weeks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Greater Hb rise and markedly larger ferritin increase with IV iron; fewer gastrointestinal adverse effects.</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ruangvutilert et al., 2017 [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thailand; n=80; RCT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weekly IV iron sucrose 200 mg up to 500 mg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daily oral iron (ferrous fumarate)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Until delivery</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The late-pregnancy IV strategy was designed for faster correction with lower pill burden; hematologic efficacy favored parenteral treatment.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breymann et al., 2017 [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multinational; n=252; open-label RCT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferric carboxymaltose 1000-1500 mg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oral ferrous sulfate 200 mg/day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 weeks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Higher and faster anemia correction with FCM, less gastrointestinal toxicity, and better vitality/social functioning.</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jose et al., 2019 [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">India; n=100; open-label RCT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferric carboxymaltose</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV iron sucrose complex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 weeks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FCM achieved faster repletion and required fewer visits than iron sucrose, with favorable hematologic recovery.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neogi et al., 2019 [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">India; n=2018; multicenter phase 3 RCT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calculated-dose IV iron sucrose</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard oral elemental iron 100 mg twice daily</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Through delivery and postpartum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biologically effective but did not reduce the primary maternal composite outcome; serious adverse events were not treatment-related.</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chawla et al., 2022 [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">India; n=362; randomized trial</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single-dose ferric carboxymaltose 1000 mg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oral ferrous sulfate 120 mg/day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 weeks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Larger Hb and ferritin rise with FCM, fewer gastrointestinal complaints, and no clear neonatal difference.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hansen et al., 2023 [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Denmark; n=201; single-center RCT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferric derisomaltose 1000 mg single dose</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oral ferrous fumarate 100 mg/day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 weeks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">More women remained non-anemic; IV therapy improved Hb, fatigue, and quality of life while maintaining comparable safety.</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chauhan et al., 2023 [<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">India; n=268; open-label RCT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV iron sucrose</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oral ferrous sulfate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short-term follow-up</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quicker Hb and ferritin response with IV iron and better tolerability in a late-presenting population.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pasricha et al., 2023 [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Malawi; n=862; open-label RCT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferric carboxymaltose up to 1000 mg once</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard oral elemental iron for 90 days</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 weeks plus postpartum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No difference in 36-week anemia or birthweight, but earlier hematologic improvement and good safety profile.</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Afolabi et al., 2024 [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nigeria; n=1056; multicenter open-label RCT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single-dose ferric carboxymaltose 20 mg/kg (max 1000 mg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oral ferrous sulfate until 6 weeks postpartum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 weeks plus postpartum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No significant difference in anemia at 36 weeks or preterm birth, but lower iron deficiency and iron-deficiency anemia with IV treatment.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Risk of Bias</p><p>Most studies were randomized and clinically relevant, but open-label treatment was common. As a result, the structured summary was characterized by some concerns rather than low risk of bias. Objective laboratory outcomes reduced detection bias in several trials, whereas concealment procedures were not always described in detail (Table <xref rid="TAB2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) [<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Qualitative risk of bias assessment of the included trials</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Randomization / concealment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blinding / deviations</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outcome data / reporting</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall judgment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Concise rationale</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bhavi et al., 2017 [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some concerns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some concerns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some concerns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Small open-label trial; objective hematologic outcomes reduce detection bias, but allocation detail was limited.</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ruangvutilert et al., 2017 [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some concerns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some concerns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A randomized design was reported, but masking was not evident, and the accessible report provided limited methodological detail.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breymann et al., 2017 [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some concerns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some concerns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Large randomized international trial; open-label design introduces potential performance bias despite objective outcomes.</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jose et al., 2019 [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some concerns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Computer-generated block randomization was described, but the trial was open-label.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neogi et al., 2019 [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some concerns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Large multicenter phase 3 trial with robust reporting; open-label treatment remained the main concern.</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chawla et al., 2022 [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some concerns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some concerns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some concerns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Randomized but analyzed per protocol, with losses to follow-up and open-label treatment.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hansen et al., 2023 [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some concerns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Web-based randomization and structured follow-up were strengths; open-label delivery remained unavoidable.</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chauhan et al., 2023 [<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some concerns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some concerns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Open-label trial with limited detail on concealment, but clinically relevant outcomes were clearly reported.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pasricha et al., 2023 [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some concerns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some concerns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Randomized with masked laboratory/birthweight assessment; participants and nurses were not masked.</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Afolabi et al., 2024 [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some concerns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some concerns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Large web-randomized pragmatic trial with comprehensive outcome reporting; primary unmasking created some concern for deviations.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Qualitative Evidence Synthesis</p><p>Hemoglobin response: Across the review, the most reproducible hematologic finding was a faster early hemoglobin response with IV iron. Bhavi and Jaju [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] reported a greater four-week hemoglobin increment with IV iron sucrose than with oral ferrous fumarate (22 ± 11.5 g/L vs 12 ± 9 g/L), and a hemoglobin rise greater than 20 g/L occurred in 55% versus 11% of participants, respectively. Breymann and colleagues [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] reported that ferric carboxymaltose achieved anemia correction more often than oral ferrous sulfate (84% vs 70%) and in a shorter median time (3.4 vs 4.3 weeks); by week six, the mean hemoglobin increase was also greater with ferric carboxymaltose (1.75 ± 1.18 g/dL vs 1.32 ± 1.54 g/dL). Chawla et al., Hansen et al., and Chauhan et al. [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>-<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] likewise reported quicker hemoglobin improvement with parenteral therapy. In contrast, the larger pragmatic studies showed a more nuanced picture. Neogi et al. [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] demonstrated that IV iron sucrose was biologically active but did not improve the prespecified maternal composite outcome, and the Malawian and Nigerian ferric carboxymaltose trials did not show a decisive reduction in late-pregnancy anemia prevalence despite favorable intermediate responses [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Collectively, these findings suggest that IV iron has a clear hematologic advantage for early correction, but that the magnitude of the benefit depends on baseline severity, gestational timing, and the endpoint chosen.</p><p>Iron stores and ferritin recovery: Serum ferritin recovery and trial-defined correction of iron deficiency favored IV therapy more consistently than hemoglobin did. This pattern was seen in the small iron sucrose trials, in the ferric carboxymaltose studies, and in the ferric derisomaltose trial. From a hematology standpoint, this is highly relevant because ferritin recovery reflected materially greater restoration of storage iron in representative trials; for example, Bhavi and Jaju [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] reported a four-week ferritin increase of 112.17 ± 98.15 ng/mL versus 22.71 ± 11.32 ng/mL with IV versus oral therapy, and Jose et al. [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] found a three-week median ferritin of 343 versus 298 μg/L with ferric carboxymaltose versus iron sucrose. Bhavi and Jaju [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] reported markedly greater ferritin improvement with IV iron sucrose. Jose et al. [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] showed that ferric carboxymaltose replenished stores more quickly than iron sucrose while requiring fewer visits. The Intravenous versus oral iron for iron deficiency anaemia in pregnant Nigerian women (IVON) trial [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] demonstrated a substantially lower prevalence of iron deficiency and iron-deficiency anemia at 36 weeks among women treated with ferric carboxymaltose, even though overall anemia prevalence remained similar between groups. These data suggest that parenteral iron is particularly effective when the clinical objective is complete repletion of iron deficit rather than partial symptomatic improvement.</p><p>Tolerability and safety: A second consistent signal was the poorer tolerability of oral ferrous preparations. In the FER-ASAP trial [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], treatment-related adverse events occurred in 14 women (11%) receiving ferric carboxymaltose versus 19 women (15%) receiving oral ferrous sulfate, with gastrointestinal disorders reported in three versus 16 women, respectively. In Chawla et al. [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], nausea/vomiting occurred in five versus 31 women, constipation in zero versus 27, and epigastric discomfort in zero versus 23 in the IV versus oral groups. Chauhan et al. [<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] likewise reported fewer adverse effects with IV iron sucrose, with eight mild hypersensitivity-type events in the IV group compared with 51 adverse-effect reports in the oral group. Serious infusion-related toxicity remained uncommon. In Neogi et al. [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], maternal serious adverse events occurred in 16 women receiving IV iron sucrose and 13 receiving oral therapy, while serious fetal/neonatal adverse events occurred in 39/961 (4%) versus 45/982 (5%), and none was considered treatment-related. Similarly, the Malawian ferric carboxymaltose trial found no infusion-related serious adverse events and no significant difference in overall adverse events (43% vs 39%) [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], and the Nigerian IVON trial [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] likewise reported no significant difference in adverse events between groups. Thus, the classic concern that IV iron is inherently more hazardous than oral treatment was not strongly supported in these contemporary pregnancy trials, although infusion monitoring and formulation-specific precautions remain appropriate.</p><p>Maternal and neonatal outcomes</p><p>When maternal and neonatal outcomes beyond laboratory correction were examined, the evidence was less consistent, particularly for the primary maternal composite outcome, anemia prevalence at 36 weeks, birthweight, and preterm birth. The Indian phase three trial did not show benefit of IV iron on the primary maternal composite outcome [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The Malawian trial found no difference in birthweight and no significant reduction in anemia prevalence at 36 weeks, despite early post-treatment gains and reassuring safety [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Similarly, the Nigerian IVON study [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] found no significant difference in maternal anemia at 36 weeks or preterm birth, but it did show better correction of iron deficiency and iron-deficiency anemia. Most smaller trials were not powered for obstetric endpoints and therefore mainly inform hematologic rather than perinatal decision-making. This distinction is important: failure to change birthweight or preterm birth does not negate the hematologic value of restoring iron stores, but it does argue against assuming that every laboratory advantage will translate into a measurable obstetric benefit.</p><p>Comparative IV formulations</p><p>The single head-to-head randomized trial comparing ferric carboxymaltose with IV iron sucrose adds a practical dimension to the literature. Jose et al. [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] reported more rapid repletion and fewer treatment visits with ferric carboxymaltose. Hematologically, this suggests that formulation choice is not trivial. The ability to replace a substantial iron deficit in one or two sessions may improve treatment completion, reduce missed appointments, and accelerate store recovery in women presenting late in pregnancy. For clinicians managing antenatal anemia services, convenience therefore intersects with effectiveness.</p><p>Discussion</p><p>Across the included randomized trials, IV iron generally produced faster ferritin recovery and, in many studies, a more rapid hemoglobin response than oral therapy, with fewer gastrointestinal adverse effects; however, the largest pragmatic trials did not show clear improvement in the primary maternal composite outcome, anemia prevalence at 36 weeks, birthweight, or preterm birth, despite better correction of iron deficiency and IDA [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Although oral iron continues to be the usual first-line treatment in many settings, the randomized controlled trials included in this review suggest that IV iron often leads to a quicker rise in hemoglobin and better replenishment of iron stores than oral therapy [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. This pattern becomes especially important in pregnancy because untreated or poorly treated anemia can affect both maternal well-being and fetal outcomes, and the time available to correct anemia may be limited depending on gestational age [<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>-<xref rid="REF18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p><p>The earlier trials in this review already pointed in this direction. Bhavi and Jaju found that IV iron sucrose was more effective than oral ferrous fumarate in treating anemia in pregnancy, showing that IV therapy can be a practical and successful option in women who need stronger correction than oral treatment may provide [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. In the same way, Ruangvutilert and colleagues compared weekly low-dose IV iron sucrose with daily oral iron in women with IDA during late pregnancy and also reported favorable outcomes with IV treatment [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. This is especially meaningful because women who present in late pregnancy have less time before delivery, so a faster treatment option may be more clinically useful [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. These early studies suggest that IV iron should not only be viewed as a backup treatment, but in some cases as a preferred option depending on the patient’s condition and timing in pregnancy [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p><p>The studies involving ferric carboxymaltose expanded the contemporary evidence base on IV iron, particularly with respect to ferritin recovery, hemoglobin response, and treatment practicality. In the FER-ASAP trial, Breymann and colleagues showed that ferric carboxymaltose was effective compared with oral iron and had the added advantage of allowing larger doses to be administered in fewer visits [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. That practical benefit matters in prenatal care because repeated hospital or clinic visits may be difficult for pregnant women due to transportation, work, childcare, or other barriers. Jose and colleagues compared ferric carboxymaltose with iron sucrose complex and found that both IV treatments were effective in improving IDA during pregnancy [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Their findings are useful because they show that the benefits of IV therapy are not limited to just one formulation. Chawla and colleagues later compared ferric carboxymaltose with oral iron and again reported positive results for the IV group, adding more support to the idea that modern IV formulations may be particularly helpful when rapid iron replacement is needed [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p><p>Among the 10 studies, some of the strongest evidence came from the larger and more recent multicenter trials. Neogi and colleagues conducted a phase three randomized controlled trial in India and showed that IV iron sucrose was both safe and effective in pregnant women with moderate-to-severe anemia [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. This study is especially important because it focused on women with more serious anemia, which is often the group most likely to benefit from faster and more reliable treatment. In these patients, waiting for oral iron to work may not be ideal, especially if the patient is symptomatic or approaching delivery [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Pasricha and colleagues also contributed major evidence through their trial in Malawian women with second-trimester anemia, where ferric carboxymaltose was compared with standard oral care [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Their study showed that IV iron can be effective even in lower-resource settings with a high burden of maternal anemia, which expands the relevance of this treatment beyond high-income countries [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Similarly, Afolabi and colleagues in the IVON trial showed that IV iron could be successfully used in pregnant women in Nigeria, again supporting its usefulness in settings where anemia is common and where an effective intervention may have important public health value [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p><p>The studies from 2023 also added valuable detail to the overall picture. Hansen and colleagues compared ferric derisomaltose with oral iron in pregnant women with persistent iron deficiency and found that IV treatment remained beneficial with newer iron formulations as well [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Chauhan and colleagues compared iron sucrose with ferrous sulfate and also found results that favored IV treatment [<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Together, these trials show that the advantage of IV iron has remained consistent across different years, settings, and formulations. They also suggest that the question is no longer simply whether IV iron works in pregnancy, but rather which patients will benefit the most, which preparation is most practical, and at what stage of pregnancy IV therapy should be considered [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>-<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p><p>Even though the overall pattern supports IV iron, the results were not exactly the same across all trials, and this should be acknowledged. The included studies varied in several important ways, including gestational age at enrollment, baseline severity of anemia, oral comparator used, IV formulation, and dosing schedule [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Some studies included women later in pregnancy, where time to delivery was short, while others enrolled women earlier, allowing oral therapy more time to show a benefit [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Some trials focused on moderate-to-severe anemia, while others included broader patient groups [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. These differences likely explain why the size of the treatment effect was not identical in every study. Still, despite this heterogeneity, the direction of the evidence was largely the same, with IV iron generally producing faster and stronger hematologic improvement than oral iron [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p><p>Safety is also an important consideration. Based on the trials included in this review, IV iron was generally well tolerated and did not show major safety concerns that outweighed its clinical benefits when used appropriately [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>-<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. At the same time, IV treatment does require more medical resources, including infusion facilities, observation, and trained staff, which may limit its accessibility in some settings. Oral iron, despite its slower effect and frequent gastrointestinal side effects, remains easier to prescribe, less resource-intensive, and more widely available [<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>-<xref rid="REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. For that reason, it would not be accurate to say that IV iron should replace oral iron in every pregnant patient. Instead, the evidence suggests that IV iron may be especially useful for women with moderate-to-severe anemia, poor response to oral therapy, intolerance to oral iron, or limited time before delivery [<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>-<xref rid="REF18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p><p>The broader secondary literature supports this interpretation. Reviews, meta-analyses, and guideline papers generally conclude that IV iron is associated with a faster increase in hemoglobin and better correction of iron deficiency than oral therapy, although they also emphasize that treatment decisions should be individualized based on severity, timing, and available resources [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>-<xref rid="REF27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. This is consistent with a hematology-focused perspective, where treatment choice should depend not only on whether anemia is present, but also on how severe it is, how quickly it needs to be corrected, and whether oral therapy is realistic for that patient [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Current guidelines also continue to support oral iron as a reasonable first step in many uncomplicated cases, while recognizing IV iron as an important option when oral therapy is not sufficient or not tolerated [<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>-<xref rid="REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p><p>Overall, the 10 randomized controlled trials included in this review support a hematologic advantage of IV iron in pregnancy, particularly for faster ferritin repletion and, in many studies, more rapid hemoglobin improvement, especially in women who require prompt correction or do not tolerate oral therapy well [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Although more research is still needed on formulation-specific comparisons, cost-effectiveness, and long-term maternal and neonatal outcomes, the current evidence already supports a meaningful role for IV iron in the management of IDA during pregnancy [<xref rid="REF20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>-<xref rid="REF27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>].</p><p>Limitations</p><p>Several limitations should be acknowledged. First, this review was not prospectively registered in PROSPERO, which reduces prospective methodological transparency even though the eligibility criteria and qualitative synthesis objectives were defined during manuscript preparation. Second, the review was restricted to 10 randomized trials and did not include meta-analyses, so the findings should be interpreted as a structured qualitative synthesis rather than a pooled quantitative estimate. Third, the included studies showed substantial clinical and methodological heterogeneity, including differences in baseline hemoglobin thresholds, ferritin cutoffs, gestational age at enrollment, IV formulation, cumulative iron dose, comparator regimen, follow-up duration, and prioritized endpoints. Fourth, many of the included trials were open label, and several were single-center studies, which increases the possibility of performance bias and limits generalizability despite the relative objectivity of laboratory outcomes. Fifth, outcome definitions were not fully standardized across studies, particularly for anemia correction, iron deficiency, maternal composite outcomes, and neonatal endpoints, which limited direct between-study comparison. Finally, the study populations differed in baseline anemia severity, iron status, malaria exposure, and concomitant antenatal interventions, factors that may have influenced both hematologic and obstetric outcomes. Despite these limitations, the overall direction of the hematologic evidence was broadly similar across trials, especially with respect to faster ferritin recovery and better tolerability of IV therapy relative to oral iron.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>IV iron provides a reliable hematologic advantage in pregnancy, with consistently faster ferritin repletion and usually more rapid hemoglobin improvement than oral ferrous salts, while oral therapy is frequently limited by gastrointestinal intolerance and slower repletion. </p><p>However, the larger contemporary pragmatic trials indicate that biochemical superiority does not consistently translate into improved major obstetric outcomes, supporting a targeted approach in which IV iron is prioritized for late gestation, poor oral tolerance, suspected nonadherence, or when rapid restoration of iron stores is clinically necessary.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group content-type="conflict"><title>Disclosures</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold> In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following:</p><p><bold>Payment/services info:</bold> All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Financial relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Other relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Concept and design:</bold>  Arturo P. Jaramillo, Hector I. Guerra Toro, Genesis Pazmino</p><p><bold>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</bold>  Arturo P. Jaramillo, Hector I. Guerra Toro, Genesis Pazmino, Valeria M. Caceres</p><p><bold>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</bold>  Arturo P. Jaramillo, Hector I. Guerra Toro, Genesis Pazmino</p><p><bold>Supervision:</bold>  Arturo P. Jaramillo, Hector I. Guerra Toro</p><p><bold>Drafting of the manuscript:</bold>  Hector I. Guerra Toro, Genesis Pazmino, Valeria M. Caceres</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Intravenous iron sucrose v/s oral ferrous fumarate for treatment of anemia in pregnancy. A randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>BMC Pregnancy Childbirth</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bhavi</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jaju</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>137</fpage><volume>17</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28482869</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12884-017-1313-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5422878</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Low-dose weekly intravenous iron sucrose versus daily oral iron for iron deficiency anemia in late pregnancy: a randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>J Med Assoc Thai</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ruangvutilert</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chanprapaph</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chuenwattana</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Titapant</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Komoltri</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>496</fpage><lpage>503</lpage><volume>100</volume><year>2017</year><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.thaiscience.info/journals/Article/JMAT/10986263.pdf">https://www.thaiscience.info/journals/Article/JMAT/10986263.pdf</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Ferric carboxymaltose vs. oral iron in the treatment of pregnant women with iron deficiency anemia: an international, open-label, randomized controlled trial (FER-ASAP)</article-title><source>J Perinat Med</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Breymann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Milman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mezzacasa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dudenhausen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>453</lpage><volume>45</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27278921</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1515/jpm-2016-0050</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Comparison of ferric Carboxymaltose and iron sucrose complex for treatment of iron deficiency anemia in pregnancy- randomised controlled trial</article-title><source>BMC Pregnancy Childbirth</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jose</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mahey</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bhatla</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Saxena</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kalaivani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kriplani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>54</fpage><volume>19</volume><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30717690</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12884-019-2200-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6360702</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Safety and effectiveness of intravenous iron sucrose versus standard oral iron therapy in pregnant women with moderate-to-severe anaemia in India: a multicentre, open-label, phase 3, randomised, controlled trial</article-title><source>Lancet Glob Health</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Neogi</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Devasenapathy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><volume>7</volume><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2214-109X(19)30427-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31708151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>A randomised controlled trial to compare injection ferric carboxymaltose and oral iron in treating iron deficiency anemia during pregnancy</article-title><source>J Obstet Gynaecol India</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chawla</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jhamb</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Anupama</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>492</fpage><lpage>496</lpage><volume>72</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36506904</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s13224-022-01653-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9732156</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Intravenous ferric derisomaltose versus oral iron for persistent iron deficient pregnant women: a randomised controlled trial</article-title><source>Arch Gynecol Obstet</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pinborg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Krebs</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thomsen</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Moos</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Holm</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1165</fpage><lpage>1173</lpage><volume>308</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36107229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00404-022-06768-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10435604</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Randomized controlled trial comparing ferrous sulfate and iron sucrose in iron deficiency anemia in pregnancy</article-title><source>Cureus</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chauhan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dogra</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kant</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Soni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>15</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7759/cureus.34858</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10010153</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36923182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Ferric carboxymaltose versus standard-of-care oral iron to treat second-trimester anaemia in Malawian pregnant women: a randomised controlled trial</article-title><source>Lancet</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pasricha</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mwangi</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Moya</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>1595</fpage><lpage>1609</lpage><volume>401</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37088092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(23)00278-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10193370</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Intravenous versus oral iron for anaemia among pregnant women in Nigeria (IVON): an open-label, randomised controlled trial</article-title><source>Lancet Glob Health</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Afolabi</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Babah</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Adeyemo</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><volume>12</volume><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2214-109X(24)00239-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11420468</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39304237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Bias risk assessment: (3) Revised Cochrane bias risk assessment tool for individual randomized, cross-over trials (RoB2.0) (Article in Chinese)</article-title><source>Zhonghua Liu Xing Bing Xue Za Zhi</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1436</fpage><lpage>1440</lpage><volume>38</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29060995</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3760/cma.j.issn.0254-6450.2017.10.028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The PRISMA 2020 statement: an updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews</article-title><source>BMJ</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bossuyt</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>372</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13643-021-01626-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8008539</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33781348</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>UK guidelines on the management of iron deficiency in pregnancy</article-title><source>Br J Haematol</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pavord</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Daru</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Prasannan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stanworth</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Girling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>819</fpage><lpage>830</lpage><volume>188</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31578718</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/bjh.16221</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Anemia in pregnancy: ACOG practice bulletin, number 233</article-title><source>Obstet Gynecol</source><fpage>0</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><volume>138</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/AOG.0000000000004477</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34293770</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Guideline: daily iron and folic acid supplementation in pregnant women</article-title><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
<month>3</month>
<year>2026</year>
</date-in-citation><year>2012</year><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789241501996">https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789241501996</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23586119</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Identifying and treating iron deficiency anemia in pregnancy</article-title><source>Hematology Am Soc Hematol Educ Program</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lewkowitz</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tuuli</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>228</lpage><volume>2023</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38066889</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1182/hematology.2023000474</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10727057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Iron deficiency anaemia in pregnancy: a contemporary review</article-title><source>Obstet Med</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Frise</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Frise</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><volume>14</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34394714</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/1753495X20932426</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8358243</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Iron deficiency anaemia in pregnancy: a narrative review from a clinical perspective</article-title><source>Diagnostics (Basel)</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Obianeli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Afifi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stanworth</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Churchill</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>2306</fpage><volume>14</volume><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39451629</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/diagnostics14202306</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11506382</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Screening and treatment of iron deficiency anemia in pregnancy: a review and appraisal of current international guidelines</article-title><source>Int J Gynaecol Obstet</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>O'Toole</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sheane</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Reynaud</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McAuliffe</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>214</fpage><lpage>227</lpage><volume>166</volume><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38069617</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ijgo.15270</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Treatment of iron deficiency anemia in pregnancy with intravenous versus oral iron: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Am J Perinatol</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Govindappagari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Burwick</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>366</fpage><lpage>376</lpage><volume>36</volume><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30121943</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1055/s-0038-1668555</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Intravenous compared with oral iron for the treatment of iron-deficiency anemia in pregnancy: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>J Perinatol</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lewkowitz</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>519</fpage><lpage>532</lpage><volume>39</volume><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30692612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41372-019-0320-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Intravenous or oral iron for treating iron deficiency anaemia during pregnancy: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Med J Aust</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Qassim</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Grivell</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kidson-Gerber</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shand</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Grzeskowiak</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>373</lpage><volume>211</volume><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31441077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5694/mja2.50308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Iron preparations for women of reproductive age with iron deficiency anaemia in pregnancy (FRIDA): a systematic review and network meta-analysis</article-title><source>Lancet Haematol</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rogozińska</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Daru</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolaides</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><volume>8</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2352-3026(21)00137-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7612251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34171281</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Effect and safety of intravenous iron compared to oral iron for treatment of iron deficiency anaemia in pregnancy</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Axon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Daru</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rogozińska</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>12</volume><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD016136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11626698</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39651609</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Clinical effectiveness of ferric carboxymaltose (iv) versus iron sucrose (iv) in treatment of iron deficiency anaemia in pregnancy: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Indian J Med Res</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Srimathi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Revathy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bagepally</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>62</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><volume>159</volume><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38439125</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4103/ijmr.ijmr_246_23</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10954109</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>A meta-analysis of ferric carboxymaltose versus other intravenous iron preparations for the management of iron deficiency anemia during pregnancy</article-title><source>Rev Bras Ginecol Obstet</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gupte</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mukhopadhyay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Puri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gopinath</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Swami</surname><given-names>OC</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>46</volume><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.61622/rbgo/2024AO21</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11075392</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38765534</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Single-dose intravenous iron vs oral iron for treatment of maternal iron deficiency anemia: a randomized clinical trial</article-title><source>Am J Obstet Gynecol</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Derman</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bellad</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Somannavar</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>120</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><volume>233</volume><year>2025</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ajog.2025.01.037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39909327</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>