<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">365</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">springeropen</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>European Journal of Clinical Pharmacology</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title>Eur J Clin Pharmacol</abbrev-journal-title></journal-title-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11458663</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11458663</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11458663</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39134879</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00228-024-03738-x</article-id><title-group><article-title>Characteristics of isoniazid-induced psychosis: a systematic review of case reports and case series</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="author"><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>B</surname><given-names initials="K">Keerthanaa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="_eqcntrb93pmc__">#</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Appaji</surname><given-names initials="R">Rashmi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="_eqcntrb93pmc__">#</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names initials="L">Levin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Baral</surname><given-names initials="T">Tejaswini</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>N</surname><given-names initials="S">Skanda</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaithra</surname></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>M</surname><given-names initials="SS">Sonal Sekhar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Saravu</surname><given-names initials="K">Kavitha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Undela</surname><given-names initials="K">Krishna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names initials="M">Mahadev</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="_fncrsp93pmc__">✉</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Pharmacy Practice, Manipal College of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Manipal Academy of Higher Education, Manipal, 576104 Udupi, Karnataka India </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Psychiatry, Father Muller Medical College Hospital, Father Muller Road, Kankanady, 575002 Mangalore, Karnataka India </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Infectious Diseases, Kasturba Medical College, Manipal, Manipal Academy of Higher Education, Manipal, 576104 Udupi, Karnataka India </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Pharmacy Practice, National Institute of Pharmaceutical Education and Research (NIPER), Guwahati, Changsari, Kamrup (R), Assam 781101 India </aff><author-notes><fn id="_fncrsp93pmc__"><label>✉</label><p>Corresponding author.</p></fn><fn id="_eqcntrb93pmc__"><label>#</label><p>Contributed equally.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date><day>13</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>80</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1725</fpage><page-range>1725–1740</page-range><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>9</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><license><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ext-link-type="uri">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="228_2024_Article_3738.pdf" content-type="pmc-pdf"><?cloudpmc-path 9dd3/11458663/b2b2f5a47137/228_2024_Article_3738.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 1847698?></self-uri><abstract id="Abs1"><title>Abstract</title><sec id="sec1" disp-level="2"><title>Purpose</title><p id="Par1">Isoniazid, a first-line antitubercular drug, is associated with nervous system adverse drug reactions such as seizures, peripheral neuropathy, and psychosis. This systematic review of case reports and case series aimed to characterize the demographic, social, and clinical factors associated with isoniazid-induced psychosis in patients with active tuberculosis (TB) and those who received isoniazid for latent TB infection (LTBI).</p></sec><sec id="sec2" disp-level="2"><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">We comprehensively searched the Embase, PubMed, and Scopus databases to identify relevant studies published between the date of inception of the database and June 2024.</p></sec><sec id="sec3" disp-level="2"><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">A total of 28 studies, including 21 case reports and 7 case series involved 37 patients who developed isoniazid-induced psychosis. A higher frequency of isoniazid-induced psychosis was observed during the first 2 months of treatment, with a relatively early onset observed among patients aged 18 years or less. Delusions and/or hallucinations are the common symptoms of isoniazid-induced psychosis. Psychomotor disturbances, disorganized speech or formal thought disorder, disorganized or abnormal behaviour, and neuropsychiatric symptoms (sleep disturbances, hostility or aggression, confusion, affective symptoms, anxiety symptoms, and cognitive difficulties) were the other symptoms observed in the included studies. More than 80% of cases rechallenged with isoniazid resulted in the recurrence of psychotic symptoms.</p></sec><sec id="sec4" disp-level="2"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">Patients with TB and LTBI should be assessed for psychotic and neuropsychiatric symptoms during isoniazid therapy, mainly in the first 2 months. Further research is required to understand the impact of underlying risk factors, such as genetic predisposition and isoniazid pharmacokinetics, as well as the clinical utility and dosage recommendations of pyridoxine for managing isoniazid-induced psychosis.</p></sec><sec id="sec5" disp-level="2"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1007/s00228-024-03738-x.</p></sec><sec id="kwd-group1" xml:lang="en" sec-type="kwd-group" disp-level="2"><p><bold>Keywords:</bold> Adverse drug reaction, Isoniazid, Psychosis, Pyridoxine, Tuberculosis</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>status</meta-name><meta-value>released</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>display-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-in-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-journal-matter</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-scanned</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-retracted</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes notes-type="article-notes"><sec id="historyarticle-meta1" sec-type="history" disp-level="2"><p>Received 2024 Apr 13; Accepted 2024 Aug 6; Issue date 2024.</p></sec></notes></front><body><sec id="Sec1" disp-level="1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par5">Isoniazid has been one of the first-line antitubercular drugs used to treat both active tuberculosis (TB) and latent TB infection (LTBI) for several years [<xref rid="CR1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Isoniazid is associated with numerous types of adverse drug reactions (ADRs) affecting the central and peripheral nervous system, such as insomnia, headache, muscle twitching, optic neuropathy, peripheral neurotoxicity, psychosis, and restlessness [<xref rid="CR2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Isoniazid may cause psychiatric ADRs that include symptoms such as delusions, hallucination, abnormal behaviour, disorganized thoughts, and euphoria [<xref rid="CR3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="CR4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Several case studies have found an association between the development of psychosis and isoniazid use in the treatment and prophylaxis of TB [<xref rid="CR5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Several mechanisms have been hypothesized for isoniazid-induced psychosis. One mechanism involves the marginal inhibition of monoamine oxidase (MAO) by isoniazid, which results in elevated levels of monoamines [<xref rid="CR7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="CR8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Another mechanism is the lack of vitamin B6/pyridoxine, a cofactor necessary to produce numerous neurotransmitters, including gamma-aminobutyric acid (GABA) [<xref rid="CR9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. When isoniazid is metabolized, it produces hydrazine and its metabolites (reactive nitrogen species), which bind with pyridoxal phosphate, an active form of pyridoxine. This binding inhibits the enzymes dependent on pyridoxal phosphate, including transaminases and those involved in amino acid metabolism, leading to a functional pyridoxine deficiency [<xref rid="CR10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. In addition, isoniazid is linked to increased oxidative stress caused by increased production of reactive oxygen species (ROS), which lowers the density of N-methyl-D-aspartate (NMDA) receptors in the hippocampus. ROS are hypothesized to be produced more often, and subsequently, glutathione levels are depleted [<xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p><p id="Par6">The incidence of isoniazid-induced psychosis has not yet been established. The risk factors for the occurrence of psychosis induced by isoniazid include older age, malnourishment, alcohol consumption, diabetes mellites, uraemia, present, past, and family history of psychiatric illness, hepatocellular dysfunction, and neurological disorder [<xref rid="CR12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>–<xref rid="CR14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Additionally, the isoniazid dose (&gt; 5 mg/kg) and <italic>N</italic> acetyltransferases (<italic>NAT2</italic>) slow acetylators status might contribute to the risk of developing psychosis secondary to isoniazid intake [<xref rid="CR13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. To our knowledge, no epidemiological studies focused on psychosis due to isoniazid for TB treatment and/or LTBI, and most of the available literature includes case reports and case series.</p><p id="Par7">Despite its clinical importance, there is a limited understanding regarding the demographic, social, and clinical determinants of isoniazid-induced psychosis in patients with TB and LTBI. Our systematic review focused on the in-depth clinical profiling of patients who developed isoniazid-induced psychosis. In this systematic review, we assessed the occurrence of isoniazid-induced psychosis based on patient demographics, social factors, and clinical determinants. We investigated whether there were specific periods during which psychosis was more likely to occur in TB and LTBI patients. This review also provides an overview of the pharmacological management of isoniazid-induced psychosis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" disp-level="1"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3" disp-level="2"><title>Research question</title><p id="Par8">We conducted our systematic review to address the main research question: What demographic, social, and clinical variables are associated with isoniazid-induced psychosis in patients with active TB or those who received isoniazid for LTBI?</p></sec><sec id="Sec4" disp-level="2"><title>PICO framework</title><p id="Par9">The population-intervention-comparator-outcomes-study design (PICO) framework was used to identify eligible cases [<xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The criteria used were as follows:</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par10">Population: Active TB/LTBI patients, regardless of age or demographics.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par11">Intervention: Individuals received isoniazid for active TB treatment/LTBI.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par12">Comparator: Comparator was not applicable.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par13">Outcome: The development of psychosis following the initiation of isoniazid therapy as prophylactic or antitubercular treatment.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="Sec5" disp-level="2"><title>Eligibility criteria</title>
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par15">Inclusion criteria: Case studies of isoniazid-induced psychosis was included based on the diagnostic criteria for substance/medication-induced psychosis defined by the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, Fifth Edition (DSM-5) classification [<xref rid="CR16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], published in the format of full text, correspondence, and letters to the editor focused entirely on the case report.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par16">Exclusion criteria: Review articles, conference abstract, articles not published in the English language, cases with drug-induced psychosis other than isoniazid, patients with a current or previous history of psychiatric illness, and patients with no symptoms of either hallucination or delusion.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="Sec6" disp-level="2"><title>Information source and search strategy</title><p id="Par17">The current study was performed according to the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses 2020 (PRISMA) guidelines [<xref rid="CR17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] and the PRISMA checklist in Supplemental Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">1</xref>. A systematic search approach was used to identify relevant studies. This included searching electronic databases such as PubMed, Embase, and Scopus and manually reviewing the reference lists of pertinent papers. The search was performed from the date of inception of each database until June 2024. The search keywords used in this systematic review are listed in Supplemental Table <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">2</xref>. Figure <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> illustrates the PRISMA flowchart generated using Microsoft Word.</p><fig id="Fig1" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>PRISMA 2020 flow diagram for study selection. Abbreviations: INH, isoniazid; PRISMA, Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses; TB, tuberculosis</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO1" xlink:href="228_2024_3738_Fig1_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/9dd3/11458663/a9ff22ef2a72/228_2024_3738_Fig1_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1438?><?original-width 1770?><?scaled-height 575?><?scaled-width 708?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="228_2024_3738_Fig1_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/9dd3/11458663/cc614eaf4f17/228_2024_3738_Fig1_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par18">Two independent reviewers, K.B. and S.N., performed article screening and review. Following an initial search and elimination of duplicates, two independent reviewers (K.B. and S.N.) conducted an extensive eligibility evaluation on the titles and abstracts of the remaining articles. The selected articles were subjected to a systematic full-text screening process, and only those that matched the predetermined inclusion criteria were included in the systematic review. When there were disagreements between the two reviewers regarding the acceptability of an article for inclusion, the other reviewers (L.T. and R.A.) were consulted for arbitration. All excluded reports and the reasons for their exclusion were well-documented, ensuring a rigorous and open selection process.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7" disp-level="2"><title>Selection process and data extraction</title><p id="Par19">Three authors (K.B., L.T., and S.N.) independently extracted the data from each study using a Microsoft Excel spreadsheet. If there was a disagreement among the authors regarding the extracted data, a co-author (R.A. or M.R.) was consulted to arrive at a final decision.</p><p id="Par20">The data extraction involved demographic, social, and clinical variables from the included studies. The variables were as follows: age, sex, body mass index (BMI), type of TB, treatment regimen, comorbidities/previous medical history, alcohol and smoking history, family history of psychosis/psychiatric illness, onset of psychosis since antitubercular treatment initiation, reported psychotic signs and symptoms, rechallenge with isoniazid and its response, pyridoxine dose administered during or after antitubercular treatment, psychotropics given after psychotic episode, withhold/discontinuation of isoniazid, and resolution of psychotic symptoms following therapeutic action. All extracted data were entered into Microsoft Excel for further analysis. We grouped the included studies as follows: cases prescribed only pyridoxine, cases prescribed only psychotropics, cases prescribed pyridoxine and psychotropics, and cases not prescribed or not mentioned regarding pyridoxine and psychotropic administration. GraphPad Prism Version 10.1.2 (GraphPad Software, USA) was used to plot the assessment of the medication, family and social history profile of patients who developed psychosis after the administration of isoniazid (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>), the relationship between isoniazid dose and age group with the onset of psychosis (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>), the symptoms experienced by patients who developed isoniazid-induced psychosis (Supplemental Fig. <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="supplementary-material">1</xref>), and the risk of bias of studies (Supplemental Fig. <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="supplementary-material">2</xref>).</p><fig id="Fig2" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Medication, family and social history profile of patients who developed psychosis after the administration of isoniazid. *Cases that were not isoniazid induced psychosis has been excluded from the case series. Pyridoxine administered before the occurrence of the psychosis. Abbreviations: Fam_hist_Psy_illness, family history of psychiatric illness; NR, not reported; PAS, para-aminosalicylic acid</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO2" xlink:href="228_2024_3738_Fig2_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/9dd3/11458663/62e584e30aee/228_2024_3738_Fig2_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1801?><?original-width 968?><?scaled-height 1200?><?scaled-width 645?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="228_2024_3738_Fig2_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/9dd3/11458663/c29cfc1c8d22/228_2024_3738_Fig2_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><fig id="Fig3" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Onset of psychosis symptoms with a dose of isoniazid. Footnote: Out of the 37 observed cases, only 21 were included in this study, while the remaining 16 were excluded due to incomplete documentation of dose or onset of psychosis. Abbreviation: mg, milligram</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO3" xlink:href="228_2024_3738_Fig3_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/9dd3/11458663/d90dd825bab5/228_2024_3738_Fig3_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1328?><?original-width 968?><?scaled-height 885?><?scaled-width 645?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="228_2024_3738_Fig3_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/9dd3/11458663/50e70203ad67/228_2024_3738_Fig3_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec><sec id="Sec8" disp-level="2"><title>Quality assessment</title><p id="Par21">The methodological assessment of study quality was performed using a standardized tool adapted from Murad et al. [<xref rid="CR18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. This scale assesses selection, ascertainment, causation, and reporting domains. Although there were eight questions, question seven was omitted because it was irrelevant to our review. Therefore, the maximum possible score is seven. Each of the seven items in the questionnaire received a binary (yes/no) response. If the criteria were satisfied, a score of one was given; otherwise, a score of zero was given. If the study obtained a score of five to seven, three to four, and under three, we considered the chance of bias to be low, moderate, or high risk of bias, respectively (Supplemental Fig. <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="supplementary-material">2</xref>). Four independent reviewers (K.B., L.T., T.B., and S.N.) evaluated the quality of the studies. In case of any discrepancies concerning the overall rating of a paper, R.A. acted as an arbitrator.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9" disp-level="1"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec10" disp-level="2"><title>Study selection</title><p id="Par22">A comprehensive search of the electronic databases yielded 722 records. After removing 121 duplicates, 601 records were used for title and abstract screening. We sought 59 studies for retrieval, of which five could not be retrieved because of the unavailability of the full text. Finally, 54 studies were deemed relevant and subjected to a full-text review. After thoroughly evaluating full-text articles consisting of case reports, case series, and cases in the form of letters to the editor or short communications, 17 studies met our inclusion criteria. In addition, 11 more studies were identified by manually searching the articles from pertinent literature references. A total of 28 publications were included in our review [<xref rid="CR5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="CR12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="CR14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>–<xref rid="CR42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], which consisted of 37 cases from 13 case reports [<xref rid="CR5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="CR12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="CR14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="CR20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="CR27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="CR30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="CR31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="CR34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="CR36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="CR39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], seven case series (16 cases) [<xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="CR32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="CR35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="CR37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="CR38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="CR40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], seven letters to editors [<xref rid="CR22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="CR23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="CR26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="CR28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="CR29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="CR41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="CR42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], and one short communication [<xref rid="CR33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. The data extracted from the selected studies are presented in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.
</p><table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of included case reports and case studies</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sl.no</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">First author; year; country (race/ethnicity/immigrant) [reference]</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age; sex</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Study design</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TB/LTBI</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Type of TB</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Comorbidities/previous medical history</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Onset of psychosis diagnosis since ATT initiation</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rechallenge was done</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Appearance of psychotic and neuropsychiatric symptoms after the rechallenge of isoniazid</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pyridoxine dose administered during ATT</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pyridoxine dose was administered after psychosis</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Psychotropics given after psychotic episode</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="14" rowspan="1">Cases prescribed only pyridoxine</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Duncan H et al.; 1962; UK-Case 1 (Nigerian) [<xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>35;</p><p>F</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case series</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">EPTB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fourth week</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">500 mg BD</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Duncan H et al.; 1962; UK-Case 3 [<xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>61;</p><p>F</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case series</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PTB (bilateral apical TB)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Diabetes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40 mg/day</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80 mg/day</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Iannaccone R et al.; 2002; USA [<xref rid="CR27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>14;</p><p>F</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case report</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LTBI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Generalized tonic–clonic seizures</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 day</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 mg/day</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kargiotis O et al.; 2015; Greece [<xref rid="CR29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75; M</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Letter to Editor</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PTB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Arterial hypertension</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 mg/day</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="14" rowspan="1">Cases prescribed only psychotropics</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ball R et al.; 1989; UK-Case 1 (Hong Kong immigrant) [<xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53; M</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case series</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PTB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Insulin-dependent diabetes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chlorpromazine</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Baytunca MB et al.; 2015; Turkey [<xref rid="CR22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>11;</p><p>F</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Letter to Editor</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LTBI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Risperidone</p><p>Fluoxetine</p><p>Aripiprazole</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Demartini B et al.; 2013; Sri Lanka [<xref rid="CR23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56; M</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Letter to Editor</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">EPTB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hepatic encephalopathy</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Delorazepam</p><p>Haloperidol</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prasad R et al.; 2008; India [<xref rid="CR14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28; M</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case report</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PTB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 days</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Diazepam</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rajpal S et al.; 2000; India [<xref rid="CR36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18; M</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case report</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PTB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 months</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Drug name not mentioned</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Singh H et al.; 2017; India-Case 2 [<xref rid="CR37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>51;</p><p>F</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case series</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Miliary TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>AKI,</p><p>ATT-hepatitis</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 week</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lorazepam, Risperidone</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Umut G et al.; 2016; Turkey [<xref rid="CR39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28; M</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case report</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LTBI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ankylosing spondylitis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 days</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Quetiapine</p><p>Haloperidol</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="14" rowspan="1">Cases prescribed pyridoxine and psychotropics</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Alao O et al.; 1998; USA [<xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>31;</p><p>F</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case report</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LTBI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 mg/day</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Olanzapine</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Alfawaz S et al.; 2020; Saudi Arabia [<xref rid="CR20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>12;</p><p>F</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case report</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.98</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PTB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not prescribed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 mg/day</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Risperidone</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ball R et al.; 1989; UK-Case 2 (Filipino immigrant) [<xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>43;</p><p>F</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case series</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">EPTB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 months</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes-dose unknown</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes-dose unknown</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Thioridazine</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chaturvedi SK; 1988; India [<xref rid="CR42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18; M</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Letter to Editor</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PTB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 days</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes-dose unknown</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Haloperidol</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Duke T et al.; 1999; Papua New Guinea [<xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6;</p><p>M</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case report</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">EPTB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5 mg daily-first visit</p><p>10 mg after rechallenging</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chlorpromazine</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gnam W et al.; 1993; China [<xref rid="CR26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>64;</p><p>F</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Letter to Editor</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PTB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Optic atrophy</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 months</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 mg/day</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 mg/day</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Loxapine</p><p>Perphenazine</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gomes J et al.; 2019; Portugal (African descent) [<xref rid="CR12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>21;</p><p>F</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case report</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">EPTB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 days</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">200 mg/day</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Olanzapine</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ibrahim ZY et al.; 1994; USA [<xref rid="CR28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64; M</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Letter to Editor</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LTBI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Seizure disorder</p><p>Anaemia</p><p>Glaucoma</p><p>Bell’s palsy</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 days</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 mg/day</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Haloperidol</p><p>Lorazepam</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Khanna S et al.; 2022; India [<xref rid="CR30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31; M</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case report</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PTB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 mg/day</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Olanzapine</p><p>Lorazepam</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mukherjee S et al.; 2023; India [<xref rid="CR33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>47;</p><p>F</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Short communication</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PTB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 days</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 mg/day</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Olanzapine</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Madan A et al.; 1989; India [<xref rid="CR31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20; M</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case report</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PTB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Anaemia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100 mg</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Diazepam</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Menon VB et al.; 2017; India-Case 2 [<xref rid="CR32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55; M</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case series</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.08</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PTB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 mg/day</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40 mg/day</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Lorazepam</p><p>Haloperidol</p><p>Risperidone</p><p>Quetiapine</p><p>Clonazepam</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nagano H et al.; 2019; Japan [<xref rid="CR34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>80;</p><p>F</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case report</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LTBI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Rheumatoid Arthritis</p><p>Organizing pneumonia</p><p>Vasospastic angina</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 months</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30 mg</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Quetiapine</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Oninla S et al.; 2016; Nigeria-Case 1 [<xref rid="CR35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14; M</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case series</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PTB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Undernutrition</p><p>Anaemia</p><p>Congestive cardiac failure</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 days</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100 mg/day</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Haloperidol</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Singh H et al.; 2017; India-Case 1 [<xref rid="CR37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>18;</p><p>F</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case series</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PTB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 week</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes-dose unknown</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Risperidone, Lorazepam</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Witkowski AE et al.; 2007; Philippines [<xref rid="CR41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>61;</p><p>F</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Letter to Editor</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LTBI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Abdominal pain</p><p>Received appendectomy and small bowel resection</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">200 mg</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Risperidone</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="14" rowspan="1">Cases not prescribed or not mentioned regarding pyridoxine and psychotropics administration</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bourgeois JA et al.; 1996; USA (Filipino) [<xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24; M</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case report</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LTBI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 months</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Duncan H et al.;1962; UK-Case 2 (Jamaican) [<xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40; M</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case series</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">EPTB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not clearly defined</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Jackson SL; 1954; Canada-Case 2 [<xref rid="CR38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39; M</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case series</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PTB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Jackson SL; 1955; Canada—Case 3 [<xref rid="CR38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37; M</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case series</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PTB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not clearly defined</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Jackson SL; 1955; Canada-Case 4 [<xref rid="CR38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17; M</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case series</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sharawat IK et al.; 2021; India [<xref rid="CR5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3;</p><p>F</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case report</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LTBI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Wiedorn WS et al.; 1954; USA-Case 1 (African descent) [<xref rid="CR40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>27;</p><p>F</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case series</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PTB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 months</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Wiedorn WS et al.; 1954; USA-Case 2</p><p>(African descent) [<xref rid="CR40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46; M</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case series</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PTB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Peripheral neuropathy</p><p>Malnutrition</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Wiedorn WS et al.; 1954; USA-Case 3</p><p>(African descent) [<xref rid="CR40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>31;</p><p>F</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case series</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PTB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 months</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Wiedorn WS et al.; 1954; USA-Case 4</p><p>(African descent) [<xref rid="CR40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>26;</p><p>F</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case series</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Disseminated TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not clearly defined</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="_fn_p109"><p>Abbreviations: <italic>ADR</italic>, adverse drug reaction; <italic>AKI</italic>, acute kidney injury; <italic>ATT</italic>, antitubercular treatment; <italic>BD</italic>, bis in die; <italic>BMI</italic>, body mass index; <italic>CKD</italic>, chronic kidney disease; <italic>ESRD</italic>, end-stage renal disease; <italic>EPTB</italic>, extrapulmonary tuberculosis; <italic>F</italic>, female; <italic>HIV</italic>, human immunodeficiency viruses; <italic>INH</italic>, isoniazid; <italic>LTBI</italic>, latent tuberculosis infection; <italic>M</italic>, male; <italic>Mg</italic>, milligram; <italic>NR</italic>, not reported; <italic>PTB</italic>, pulmonary tuberculosis; <italic>TB</italic>, tuberculosis</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="Sec11" disp-level="2"><title>Characteristics of included studies</title><p id="Par23">Our comprehensive search identified 37 cases in 14 countries. Out of the 37 cases, 10 reported the race/ethnicity/immigrant status of the patients [<xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="CR12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="CR40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The countries from which case studies were reported include India (<italic>n</italic> = 10) [<xref rid="CR5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="CR14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="CR30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>–<xref rid="CR33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="CR36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="CR37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="CR42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], the USA (<italic>n</italic> = 8; 4 African descent, 1 Filipino, and 3 unknown) [<xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="CR27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="CR28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="CR40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], the UK (<italic>n</italic> = 5; 1 Hong Konger, 1 Filipino, 1 Jamaican, 1 African descent, and 1 unknown) [<xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], Canada (<italic>n</italic> = 3) [<xref rid="CR38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], Turkey (<italic>n</italic> = 2) [<xref rid="CR22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="CR39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], China (<italic>n</italic> = 1) [<xref rid="CR26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], Nigeria (<italic>n</italic> = 1) [<xref rid="CR35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], Greece (<italic>n</italic> = 1) [<xref rid="CR29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], Japan (<italic>n</italic> = 1) [<xref rid="CR34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], Papua New Guinea (<italic>n</italic> = 1) [<xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], the Philippines (<italic>n</italic> = 1) [<xref rid="CR41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>], Portugal (<italic>n</italic> = 1; 1 African descent) [<xref rid="CR12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], Saudi Arabia (<italic>n</italic> = 1) [<xref rid="CR20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], and Sri Lanka (<italic>n</italic> = 1) [<xref rid="CR23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].</p><p id="Par24">The median age of the patients were 31 (IQR 34) years (age range from 3 to 80 years). The frequencies of male and female patients with isoniazid-induced psychosis across the cases were 19 (51.3%) and 18 (48.6%), respectively. Of the 37 cases, 19 were reported to have pulmonary TB (PTB) [<xref rid="CR14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="CR20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="CR26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="CR29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>–<xref rid="CR33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="CR35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>–<xref rid="CR38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="CR40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="CR42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], six were extra-pulmonary TB (EPTB) [<xref rid="CR12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="CR23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>–<xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], one had disseminated TB [<xref rid="CR40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], and one had miliary TB [<xref rid="CR37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Among the reported cases of EPTB, there were cases of pleural effusion TB (<italic>n</italic> = 2) [<xref rid="CR12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="CR23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], TB meningitis (<italic>n</italic> = 2) [<xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], spinal TB (<italic>n</italic> = 1) [<xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], pericarditis TB (<italic>n</italic> = 1) [<xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Furthermore, nine additional cases were where isoniazid was administered for LTBI [<xref rid="CR5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="CR22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="CR27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="CR28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="CR34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="CR39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="CR41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. However, one case did not report the type of TB [<xref rid="CR38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Patients diagnosed with TB also had comorbidities, such as anaemia (<italic>n</italic> = 3) [<xref rid="CR28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="CR31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="CR35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] and diabetes mellitus (<italic>n</italic> = 2) [<xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. There was one case with a documented history of smoking [<xref rid="CR32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], one with alcohol consumption [<xref rid="CR28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], and one with both smoking and alcohol consumption [<xref rid="CR23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], respectively (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). There were three cases in where the patient had a family history of psychosis [<xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="CR22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="CR30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). All 37 patients received isoniazid treatment. The combination of antitubercular drugs administered to patients in conjunction with isoniazid is shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>.</p><p id="Par25">Psychosis was diagnosed at a median of 15 days (IQR 46) after the initiation of isoniazid (<italic>n</italic> = 37). The dose of isoniazid reported in these studies was between 150 and 600 mg daily. Among the 37 patients included in the study, the most frequently reported dose of isoniazid was a 300 mg daily (<italic>n</italic> = 17). Assessment of isoniazid daily dose and age groups with the onset time of psychosis (<italic>n</italic> = 21) revealed that all patients ≤ 18 years developed isoniazid-induced psychosis within 15 days of isoniazid initiation, as shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>.</p><p id="Par26">Approximately 75.8% (<italic>n</italic> = 25) of patients developed psychosis within the first 60 days of isoniazid therapy. From our findings, we found that the use of pyridoxine during antitubercular treatment has been documented in 11 cases (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>), whereas 13 cases have reported pyridoxine supplementation following the onset of psychosis. The total daily dose of pyridoxine ranged from 5 to 1000 mg. Delusions (<italic>n</italic> = 27), hallucinations (<italic>n</italic> = 26), psychomotor disturbances (<italic>n</italic> = 25), disorganized speech (or) formal thought disorder (<italic>n</italic> = 19), disorganized (or) abnormal behaviour (<italic>n</italic> = 15), sleep disturbances (<italic>n</italic> = 13), hostility (or) aggression (<italic>n</italic> = 10), confusion (<italic>n</italic> = 11), affective symptoms (<italic>n</italic> = 10), anxiety symptoms (<italic>n</italic> = 9), and cognitive difficulties (<italic>n</italic> = 7) were observed in patients with isoniazid-induced psychosis (Supplemental Fig. <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="supplementary-material">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par27">From the selected 37 cases, we observed that after the onset of isoniazid-induced psychosis, the isoniazid was dechallenged in 32 cases [<xref rid="CR5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="CR12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="CR14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>–<xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="CR23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>–<xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="CR28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>–<xref rid="CR42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Of these 32 cases, in 19 cases, patients who received psychotropics and had complete resolution of psychotic and neuropsychiatric symptoms [<xref rid="CR12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="CR14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>–<xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="CR23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="CR28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="CR30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>–<xref rid="CR37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="CR39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="CR41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="CR42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], whereas in 13 patients who did not receive psychotropic intervention [<xref rid="CR5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="CR29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="CR38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="CR40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], nine had complete resolution of the psychotic and neuropsy<bold>c</bold>hiatric symptoms [<xref rid="CR5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="CR29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="CR38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="CR40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], two had a partial resolution [<xref rid="CR40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], and two had no improvement in their psychotic/neuropsychiatric symptoms [<xref rid="CR38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. In one of the cases with partial resolution of symptoms, cognitive disturbance in the form of disorientation persisted, although psychotic symptoms such as auditory and visual hallucinations resolved after 3 months. In this case, the patient had a medical history of peripheral neuropathy and malnutrition. There were no reports of social history (alcohol consumption and smoking habits) or a family history of psychiatric illness. In another case, the patient experienced disturbance even after 8 weeks of discontinuing isoniazid, and there were no reports of any comorbid conditions, social history, or family history of mental illness. Neither patients were rechallenged with isoniazid or prescribed pyridoxine (both prophylactically and therapeutically) and psychotropics [<xref rid="CR40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. In our review, out of 37 cases, isoniazid was not dechallenged in five cases [<xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="CR22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="CR26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="CR27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="CR37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], of which four received psychotropics [<xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="CR22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="CR26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="CR37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], while one did not receive psychotropic intervention [<xref rid="CR27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] and had complete resolution of the symptoms. Patients were treated with haloperidol (<italic>n</italic> = 6), lorazepam (<italic>n</italic> = 5), risperidone (<italic>n</italic> = 6), olanzapine (<italic>n</italic> = 4), quetiapine (<italic>n</italic> = 3), and clonazepam (<italic>n</italic> = 1), either as monotherapy or in combination therapy for managing psychiatric symptoms (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Out of 37 cases, eight were rechallenged with isoniazid, of which seven (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) experienced recurrence of psychotic/neuropsychiatric symptoms (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). We found that only five cases were evaluated, which included an assessment of the causality and severity of ADR [<xref rid="CR30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="CR32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="CR33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="CR37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The ADR causality assessment tools employed were the World Health Organization (WHO) Uppsala Monitoring Centre (UMC) scale in four cases [<xref rid="CR32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="CR33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="CR37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], and the Naranjo scale in four cases [<xref rid="CR30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="CR32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="CR37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The Hartwig and Siegel severity scale was used in two cases [<xref rid="CR32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="CR33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. The grades of the aforementioned scales are listed in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>.
</p><table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Reported adverse drug reaction causality, and severity assessment grades for isoniazid-induced psychosis from included cases</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">S.N</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Studies</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WHO-UMC scale</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Naranjo scale</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hartwig ADR severity scale</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Khanna S et al. [<xref rid="CR30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Possible</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Menon VB et al. [<xref rid="CR32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case 2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Definite</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Definite</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderate</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Mukherjee S et al. [<xref rid="CR33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Probable</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderate</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Singh H et al. [<xref rid="CR37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case 1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Possible</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Possible</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case 2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Possible</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Possible</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="_fn_p116"><p><italic>ADR</italic> adverse drug reaction, <italic>NR</italic> not reported, <italic>WHO-UMC</italic> World Health Organization-Uppsala Monitoring Centre</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="Sec12" disp-level="2"><title>Quality of assessment</title><p id="Par28">According to the risk of bias score and classification rules, 25 cases received a score between five and seven (low risk of bias) [<xref rid="CR5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="CR12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="CR14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>–<xref rid="CR32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="CR34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>–<xref rid="CR36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="CR39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="CR41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="CR42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], six cases received a score between three and four (moderate risk of bias) [<xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="CR33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="CR37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="CR38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], and six cases received a score of less than three (high risk of bias) [<xref rid="CR38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="CR40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. A detailed quality assessment of each case is presented in Supplemental Fig. <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="supplementary-material">2</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13" disp-level="1"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par29">Psychosis is a rare but serious adverse event associated with isoniazid therapy [<xref rid="CR10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Our systematic review included 37 patients with psychosis after the isoniazid intake. We found that most cases of isoniazid-induced psychosis were reported in India (<italic>n</italic> = 10). India is among the top 30 countries with a high TB burden as per the Global Tuberculosis Report 2022 [<xref rid="CR43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. We identified several variables such as a family history of mental illness, alcohol and smoking history, comorbidities, and the lack of pyridoxine supplementation among patients with isoniazid-induced psychosis. We excluded the studies reporting current or previous history of psychiatric illness. However, the evidence for these associations between ATT-induced psychosis remains insufficient despite some studies being in line with previous research [<xref rid="CR7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="CR44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>–<xref rid="CR47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. A recent systematic review and meta-analysis of 53 studies reported a high pooled prevalence (48%) of malnutrition (51 studies used a low BMI to define malnutrition) among PTB patients [<xref rid="CR48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Nutritional deficiencies and complications that occur during malnutrition, such as sleep deprivation and metabolic derangements, are known medical causes of psychosis; nutritional rehabilitation and weight restoration may be key interventional strategies for the resolution of psychosis [<xref rid="CR49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Lower BMI (&lt; 18.5 kg/m<sup>2</sup>) was reported for the two cases that have BMI data in our systematic review [<xref rid="CR20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="CR32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. There is a high prevalence of TB in patients with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) co-infection [<xref rid="CR50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. A meta-analysis reported a pooled prevalence of 23% of the first episodes of psychosis in people living with HIV (PLWHIV) on the African continent [<xref rid="CR51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Additionally, the occurrence of psychosis has been reported in the treatment with antiretroviral agents [<xref rid="CR52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="CR53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Co-administration of isoniazid preventive therapy and antiretroviral therapy (ART) was reported to be associated with a higher frequency of psychosis [<xref rid="CR54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Further studies assessing the possibility of a synergistic effect of isoniazid and antiretroviral agents in causing psychosis among TB patients co-infected with HIV are required. Hence, factors such as lower BMI/malnutrition, HIV co-infection, and co-administration of antiretroviral agents with isoniazid should be considered as potential confounding variables and/or risk factors in future studies.</p><p id="Par30">The recommended daily dose of isoniazid in adults is 5 mg/kg [<xref rid="CR55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Our systematic review identified a daily dose of 300 mg of isoniazid as the most frequently prescribed dose among cases who developed isoniazid-induced psychosis [<xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="CR12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="CR22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="CR27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>–<xref rid="CR33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="CR38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="CR39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="CR42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. <italic>NAT2</italic> genotype is an important covariate influencing the plasma concentrations of isoniazid. <italic>NAT2</italic> slow acetylators achieve higher concentrations of isoniazid than intermediate and fast acetylators [<xref rid="CR56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Only one case in our systematic review reported <italic>NAT2</italic> phenotype status as a <italic>NAT2</italic> fast acetylator [<xref rid="CR34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. <italic>NAT2</italic> single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) and haplotypes were not assessed (or) reported in any of the 37 cases. <italic>NAT2</italic> slow acetylators have been implicated as a risk factor for the development of isoniazid-induced ADRs, such as drug-induced liver injury (DILI), particularly during the first month of isoniazid therapy initiation [<xref rid="CR57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, <xref rid="CR58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Future studies should identify and evaluate whether patients with <italic>NAT2</italic> genotype/SNPs have an increased risk of developing psychosis due to higher plasma concentrations of isoniazid. Most patients developed isoniazid-induced psychosis within 2 months of isoniazid initiation; although in some cases, it appears even after eight months of therapy. Closer monitoring of isoniazid-induced psychotic symptoms in paediatric patients may be required during the first 2 weeks of treatment. Numerous studies have consistently shown a significant association between the utilization of antibiotics such as cephalosporins and fluoroquinolones and the occurrence of psychosis within a remarkably short period of 2 weeks following the initiation of treatment [<xref rid="CR44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="CR59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>–<xref rid="CR64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Considering the highly heterogeneous and pleomorphic presentation of isoniazid psychosis, we operationalized the definition based on broad criteria of psychotic disorders as per the International Classification of Diseases (ICD)-10 [<xref rid="CR65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>] and DSM-5 [<xref rid="CR16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. From our review findings, psychotic symptoms (psychomotor disturbance, disorganized speech (or) formal thought disorder, and disorganized (or) abnormal behaviour) and neuropsychiatric symptoms (sleep disturbances, hostility (or) aggression, confusion, affective symptoms, anxiety symptoms, and cognitive difficulties) were the frequently observed symptoms along with delusion and hallucination in the included cases. These findings are consistent with earlier literature [<xref rid="CR9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="CR66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>], which identified comparable symptom patterns in patients with drug-induced psychosis, including drugs such as aminoglycosides, other antitubercular agents, beta-lactam agents, and psychotropic drugs (central nervous system (CNS) stimulants, and CNS depressants) [<xref rid="CR9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="CR66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. However, they might serve as significant early-stage indicators and call for further research.</p><p id="Par31">A high frequency of patients had a psychomotor disturbance in our study. Pyridoxine deficiency has been reported to enhance noradrenergic signaling and facilitate behavioural deficits in mice [<xref rid="CR67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Pyridoxine (100 mg/day) improved neuroleptic-induced parkinsonism and psychotic symptoms in a patient with schizophrenia [<xref rid="CR68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. A double-blind placebo-controlled cross-over study in patients with schizophrenia reported pyridoxine as an effective agent for tardive dyskinesia at doses from 300 mg/day [<xref rid="CR69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study reported that the high-dose pyridoxine-treated patients (1200 mg/day administered as 600 mg BID) had improvement in neuroleptic-induced akathisia symptoms within a few days [<xref rid="CR70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. The quality of evidence about the effectiveness of pyridoxine for the treatment of neuroleptic-induced tardive dyskinesia among people with schizophrenia and other related psychotic disorders is low [<xref rid="CR71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Another study reported that though pyridoxine may be beneficial for ameliorating antipsychotic-induced akathisia, there was no significant difference observed among those who received a low dose (600 mg/day administered as 300 mg BID) or high dose (1200 mg/day administered as 600 mg BID) pyridoxine [<xref rid="CR72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Pyridoxine 100 mg was the most prescribed dose; however, several patients have been prescribed pyridoxine doses lesser than 100 mg/day post-isoniazid-induced psychosis.</p><p id="Par32">According to Chan et al., even though pyridoxine supplementation is recommended in patients who are at risk of neuropathy due to underlying medical conditions such as diabetes, uraemia, alcoholism, and HIV infection, it is not an effective treatment for isoniazid-induced psychosis [<xref rid="CR73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. On the other hand, Yadav et al. suggest that pyridoxine supplementation should be considered after the occurrence of isoniazid-induced psychosis to ensure the reintroduction of isoniazid does not exacerbate psychosis [<xref rid="CR74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. Only a single study had administered a high dose of pyridoxine of 1000 mg/day (administered as 500 mg intramuscularly BID for 4 days), which, however, did not improve psychosis during the period of administration [<xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The role of pyridoxine supplementation for isoniazid-induced psychosis warrants robust scientific validation for conclusive recommendations. A comparative benefit assessment of different doses of pyridoxine supplementation for the treatment of isoniazid-induced psychosis is also required. Our systematic review shows that approximately 60% (<italic>n</italic> = 23) of patients have received psychotropic drugs. Notably, in our review, a substantial proportion of the cases did not involve the administration of psychotropic drugs to treat isoniazid-induced psychosis. Among the psychotropics used, lorazepam, which belongs to the class of benzodiazepines [<xref rid="CR75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>], is the most frequently administered. The other antipsychotics, which belong to the classes butyrophenones and atypical antipsychotics [<xref rid="CR76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>], such as haloperidol, risperidone, quetiapine, and olanzapine, were employed in varying frequencies to treat the psychotic symptoms. In our review, isoniazid-induced psychosis was assessed using numerous ADR assessment tools across the studies, with the WHO UMC scale and the Naranjo scale being the most frequently used. Using different causality assessment tools underscores the importance of standard approaches to establishing the likelihood of isoniazid-induced psychosis [<xref rid="CR77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>].</p><p id="Par33">Our systematic review has a few inherent limitations that should be considered. Our review is primarily limited to case reports and case series, which may not provide the strongest degree of evidence in contrast to other study designs. Additionally, by only including articles in English, it is possible that pertinent studies published in different languages were left out. Due to the smaller number of reports and several missing data in these reports, our analysis could affect the precision and generalizability of the findings. Participants with a current or previous history of psychiatric illness studies were excluded from the study. We also excluded grey literature in our review. Some relevant case reports could not be retrieved because the full text was unavailable in the databases. Some case reports have scanty descriptions of the symptoms. However, we included these articles as they mentioned the evaluation of the patient by a mental health professional that led to the diagnosis of isoniazid-induced psychosis. Ascertaining the psychosis diagnosis becomes even more challenging, especially in studies involving the paediatric population. The classificatory systems in psychiatry do get revised over time. The importance of certain symptoms would change with the changing diagnostic guidelines. Including case reports from earlier decades, such as the 1950s, and applying the current classificatory guidelines to relook at the clinical manifestations would have some limitations. We restricted our attention to the relationship between isoniazid and psychosis, which potentially led to an incomplete understanding of the broader mental health implications, such as anxiety and depression. These limitations raise attention to the need for further research to address these gaps and offer a more thorough understanding of the effects of isoniazid on mental health. Future research should focus on well-designed epidemiological studies to determine the incidence/prevalence of isoniazid-induced psychosis and neuropsychiatric symptoms. Our review provides evidence for closer monitoring of psychotic symptoms during the first 2 months of isoniazid treatment as shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, with a rechallenge of isoniazid resulting in the recurrence of the psychotic and/or neuropsychiatric symptoms in the majority of the patients. However, we could not conclusively conclude on the risk factors that may lead to isoniazid induced psychosis as well as on the clinical utility and dosage recommendations of pyridoxine as a therapeutic agent for the management of isoniazid-induced psychosis symptoms. Further research may focus on retrieval of a greater number of isoniazid-induced psychosis and neuropsychiatric symptoms cases using pharmacovigilance databases such as VigiBase (WHO global database of individual case safety reports), EudraVigilance (European pharmacovigilance database), and the Food and Drug (FDA) adverse event reporting system (FAERS), which may also include unpublished cases for in-depth analysis of the risk factors, severity assessment, and signal detection [<xref rid="CR78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec14" disp-level="1"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par34">Our systematic review identified a higher frequency of isoniazid-induced psychosis during the first 2 months of TB treatment, with a relatively early onset observed among patients of 18 years or less, warranting the need for closer monitoring during this period. Individual patient demographic, social, and clinical characteristics may influence the manifestation of this adverse effect. There is a need for well-controlled studies, to evaluate the influence of genetic variants and isoniazid pharmacokinetics with the development of isoniazid-induced psychosis symptoms and for optimizing pyridoxine therapy.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15" disp-level="1"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p><supplementary-material id="MOESM1" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="228_2024_3738_MOESM1_ESM.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document"><?cloudpmc-path 9dd3/11458663/128ebec9fa77/228_2024_3738_MOESM1_ESM.docx?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 30307?><label>Supplemental Table 1</label><caption><p>(DOCX 29 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="MOESM2" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="228_2024_3738_MOESM2_ESM.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document"><?cloudpmc-path 9dd3/11458663/4ac9595df331/228_2024_3738_MOESM2_ESM.docx?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 14672?><label>Supplemental Table 2</label><caption><p>(DOCX 14 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="MOESM5" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="228_2024_3738_Fig4_ESM.png" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png"><?cloudpmc-path 9dd3/11458663/00210953b7bc/228_2024_3738_Fig4_ESM.png?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 156878?><label>Supplemental Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Isoniazid induced psychosis symptoms profile. Footnote: * Cases that were not isoniazid induced psychosis has been excluded from the case series. Abbreviation: Form_tht_dis: Formal thought disorder (PNG 153 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="MOESM3" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="228_2024_3738_MOESM3_ESM.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><?cloudpmc-path 9dd3/11458663/97ca827d5d7c/228_2024_3738_MOESM3_ESM.tif?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 709144?><caption><p>High resolution image (TIF 692 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="MOESM6" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="228_2024_3738_Fig5_ESM.png" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png"><?cloudpmc-path 9dd3/11458663/93a0e52ea24d/228_2024_3738_Fig5_ESM.png?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 137689?><label>Supplemental Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Quality assessment of included studies. Footnote: <sup>1</sup>Tool for evaluating the methodological quality of case reports and case series developed by Murad et al. <sup>2</sup>* Cases that were not isoniazid induced psychosis has been excluded from the case series. <sup>3</sup> Q1: Does the patient(s) represent(s) the whole experience of the investigator (centre) or is the selection method unclear to the extent that other patients with similar presentation may not have been reported? Q2: Was the exposure adequately ascertained? Q3: Was the outcome adequately ascertained? Q4: Were other alternative causes that may explain the observation ruled out? Q5: Was there a challenge/rechallenge phenomenon? Q6: Was there a dose-response effect? Q7: Is the case(s) described with sufficient details to allow other investigators to replicate the research or to allow practitioners make inferences related to their own practice? Abbreviation: Q: Question (PNG 134 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="MOESM4" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="228_2024_3738_MOESM4_ESM.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><?cloudpmc-path 9dd3/11458663/923131e6276e/228_2024_3738_MOESM4_ESM.tif?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 540718?><caption><p>High resolution image (TIF 528 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="ack1" sec-type="ack" disp-level="1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>K.B. is thankful to Dr. TMA Pai Ph.D. scholarship from Manipal Academy of Higher Education, Manipal. L.T. and T.B. thank the Indian Council of Medical Research (ICMR) for providing Senior Research Fellowships (No. 45/25/2020/PHA/BMS and No. TB-Fellowship/9/2022-ECD-I, respectively). C. is thankful to the Junior Research Fellowship from ICMR (F.No.5/8/5/45/multicentric study/2019/ECD-1). M.R. is thankful to the ICMR grant (F.No.5/8/5/45/multicentric study/2019/ECD-1).</p></sec><sec id="notes1" disp-level="1"><title>Author contribution</title><p>Concept and design: M.R.</p><p>Literature search: K.B, R.A, L.T, S.N.</p><p>Data extraction: K.B, L.T, S.N.</p><p>Quality assessment: K.B, R.A, L.T, T.B.</p><p>Drafting of the manuscript: K.B, R.A, M.R.</p><p>Reviewing and editing: K.B, R.A, L.T, T.B, S.N, C.S, S.S.M, K.S, K.U, M.R.</p></sec><sec id="notes2" disp-level="1"><title>Funding</title><p>Open access funding provided by Manipal Academy of Higher Education, Manipal</p></sec><sec id="notes3" disp-level="1"><title>Data availability</title><p>No datasets were generated or analyzed during the current study.</p></sec><sec id="notes4" disp-level="1"><title>Declarations</title><sec id="FPar1" disp-level="2"><title>Ethics approval</title><p id="Par35">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2" disp-level="2"><title>Consent to participate</title><p id="Par36">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3" disp-level="2"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par37">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></sec><sec id="fn-group1" sec-type="fn-group" disp-level="1"><title>Footnotes</title><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><p>Keerthanaa B and Rashmi Appaji contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="Bib1" sec-type="ref-list" disp-level="1"><title>References</title><sec id="Bib1_sec2" disp-level="2"><ref-list><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Murray JF, Schraufnagel DE, Hopewell PC (2015) Treatment of tuberculosis. A historical perspective. Ann Am Thorac Soc 12(12):1749–1759. 10.1513/AnnalsATS.201509-632PS
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1513/AnnalsATS.201509-632PS"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="26653188"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Murray JF, Schraufnagel DE, Hopewell PC (2015) Treatment of tuberculosis. A historical perspective. Ann Am Thorac Soc 12(12):1749–1759. 10.1513/AnnalsATS.201509-632PS"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bangert MK, Hasbun R (2019) Neurological and psychiatric adverse effects of antimicrobials. CNS Drugs 33(8):727–753. 10.1007/s40263-019-00649-9
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s40263-019-00649-9"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="31321707"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Bangert MK, Hasbun R (2019) Neurological and psychiatric adverse effects of antimicrobials. CNS Drugs 33(8):727–753. 10.1007/s40263-019-00649-9"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Esposito S, Canevini MP, Principi N (2017) Complications associated with antibiotic administration: neurological adverse events and interference with antiepileptic drugs. Int J Antimicrob Agents 50(1):1–8. 10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2017.01.027
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2017.01.027"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="28414069"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Esposito S, Canevini MP, Principi N (2017) Complications associated with antibiotic administration: neurological adverse events and interference with antiepileptic drugs. Int J Antimicrob Agents 50(1):1–8. 10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2017.01.027"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Kass JS, Shandera WX (2010) Nervous system effects of antituberculosis therapy. CNS Drugs 24(8):655–667. 10.2165/11534340-000000000-00000
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.2165/11534340-000000000-00000"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="20658798"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Kass JS, Shandera WX (2010) Nervous system effects of antituberculosis therapy. CNS Drugs 24(8):655–667. 10.2165/11534340-000000000-00000"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sharawat IK, Dawman L (2021) Toddler with intermittent abnormal behavior: is it isoniazid-induced psychosis? Pediatr Emerg Care 37(1):e60–e61. 10.1097/PEC.0000000000001555
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1097/PEC.0000000000001555"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="30045351"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Sharawat IK, Dawman L (2021) Toddler with intermittent abnormal behavior: is it isoniazid-induced psychosis? Pediatr Emerg Care 37(1):e60–e61. 10.1097/PEC.0000000000001555"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bourgeois JA, Zelenko M, Waraich BS (1996) Psychotic disorder associated with isoniazid. Mil Med 161(11):707. 10.1093/MILMED/161.11.707
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="8961730"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Bourgeois JA, Zelenko M, Waraich BS (1996) Psychotic disorder associated with isoniazid. Mil Med 161(11):707. 10.1093/MILMED/161.11.707"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Doherty AM, Kelly J, McDonald C et al (2013) A review of the interplay between tuberculosis and mental health. Gen Hosp Psychiatry 35(4):398–406. 10.1016/j.genhosppsych.2013.03.018
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.genhosppsych.2013.03.018"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="23660587"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Doherty AM, Kelly J, McDonald C et al (2013) A review of the interplay between tuberculosis and mental health. Gen Hosp Psychiatry 35(4):398–406. 10.1016/j.genhosppsych.2013.03.018"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Holdiness MR (1987) Neurological manifestations and toxicities of the antituberculosis drugs. A review. Med Toxicol 2(1):33–51. 10.1007/BF03259859
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/BF03259859"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="3547005"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Holdiness MR (1987) Neurological manifestations and toxicities of the antituberculosis drugs. A review. Med Toxicol 2(1):33–51. 10.1007/BF03259859"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sternbach H, State R (1997) Antibiotics: neuropsychiatric effects and psychotropic interactions. Harv Rev Psychiatry 5(4):214–226. 10.3109/10673229709000304
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3109/10673229709000304"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="9427014"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Sternbach H, State R (1997) Antibiotics: neuropsychiatric effects and psychotropic interactions. Harv Rev Psychiatry 5(4):214–226. 10.3109/10673229709000304"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zareifopoulos N, Panayiotakopoulos G (2017) Neuropsychiatric effects of antimicrobial agents. Clin Drug Investig 37(5):423–437. 10.1007/s40261-017-0498-z
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s40261-017-0498-z"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="28197902"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Zareifopoulos N, Panayiotakopoulos G (2017) Neuropsychiatric effects of antimicrobial agents. Clin Drug Investig 37(5):423–437. 10.1007/s40261-017-0498-z"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Samouco AICB, Alves SP (2023) Isoniazid-induced mania and the history of antidepressant drugs: Case report and literature review. Bipolar Disord 25(1):84–87. 10.1111/bdi.13272
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/bdi.13272"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36380697"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Samouco AICB, Alves SP (2023) Isoniazid-induced mania and the history of antidepressant drugs: Case report and literature review. Bipolar Disord 25(1):84–87. 10.1111/bdi.13272"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Gomes J, Durães D, Sousa A et al (2019) Isoniazid-induced acute psychosis in a patient with pleural tuberculosis. Case Rep Psychiatry 2019:4272941. 10.1155/2019/4272941
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1155/2019/4272941"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC6393917"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="30906613"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Gomes J, Durães D, Sousa A et al (2019) Isoniazid-induced acute psychosis in a patient with pleural tuberculosis. Case Rep Psychiatry 2019:4272941. 10.1155/2019/4272941"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Arya S, Sukhija G, Singh H (2015) Acute psychosis after recent isoniazid initiation. J Clin Diagn Res 9(6):VD01–VD02. 10.7860/JCDR/2015/12450.6130
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7860/JCDR/2015/12450.6130"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC4525588"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="26266198"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Arya S, Sukhija G, Singh H (2015) Acute psychosis after recent isoniazid initiation. J Clin Diagn Res 9(6):VD01–VD02. 10.7860/JCDR/2015/12450.6130"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Prasad R, Garg R, Verma SK (2008) Isoniazid- and ethambutol-induced psychosis. Ann Thorac Med 3(4):149–151. 10.4103/1817-1737.43083
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.4103/1817-1737.43083"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC2700450"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="19561898"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Prasad R, Garg R, Verma SK (2008) Isoniazid- and ethambutol-induced psychosis. Ann Thorac Med 3(4):149–151. 10.4103/1817-1737.43083"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Cumpston MS, McKenzie JE, Thomas J et al (2020) The use of “PICO for synthesis” and methods for synthesis without meta-analysis: protocol for a survey of current practice in systematic reviews of health interventions. F1000Res 9:678
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.12688/f1000research.24469.1"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7919603"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33728041"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Cumpston MS, McKenzie JE, Thomas J et al (2020) The use of “PICO for synthesis” and methods for synthesis without meta-analysis: protocol for a survey of current practice in systematic reviews of health interventions. F1000Res 9:678"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">American Psychiatric Association, DSM-5 Task Force (2013) Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders: DSM-5. 5th ed. American Psychiatric Publishing, Inc., Arlington. 10.1176/appi.books.9780890425596</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Page MJ, McKenzie JE, Bossuyt PM et al (2021) The PRISMA 2020 statement: an updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews. The BMJ 10(1):89. 10.1186/s13643-021-01626-4</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1186/s13643-021-01626-4"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC8008539"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33781348"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Page MJ, McKenzie JE, Bossuyt PM et al (2021) The PRISMA 2020 statement: an updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews. The BMJ 10(1):89. 10.1186/s13643-021-01626-4"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Murad MH, Sultan S, Haffar S et al (2018) Methodological quality and synthesis of case series and case reports. BMJ Evid Based Med 23:60–63. 10.1136/bmjebm-2017-110853
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1136/bmjebm-2017-110853"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC6234235"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="29420178"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Murad MH, Sultan S, Haffar S et al (2018) Methodological quality and synthesis of case series and case reports. BMJ Evid Based Med 23:60–63. 10.1136/bmjebm-2017-110853"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Alao AO, Yolles JC (1998) Isoniazid-induced psychosis. Ann Pharmacother 32:889–891. 10.1345/aph.17377
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1345/aph.17377"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="9762376"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Alao AO, Yolles JC (1998) Isoniazid-induced psychosis. Ann Pharmacother 32:889–891. 10.1345/aph.17377"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Alfawaz S, Alattas N, Alhammadi M et al (2020) Acute psychosis secondary to isoniazid in pediatric pulmonary tuberculosis: a case report and literature review. Int J Pediatr Adolesc Med 7(4):196–198. 10.1016/j.ijpam.2020.03.012
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.ijpam.2020.03.012"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7729223"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33319019"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Alfawaz S, Alattas N, Alhammadi M et al (2020) Acute psychosis secondary to isoniazid in pediatric pulmonary tuberculosis: a case report and literature review. Int J Pediatr Adolesc Med 7(4):196–198. 10.1016/j.ijpam.2020.03.012"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ball R, Rosser R (1989) Psychosis, and anti-tuberculosis therapy. Lancet 2(8654):105. 10.1016/s0140-6736(89)90344-9
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/s0140-6736(89)90344-9"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="2567848"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Ball R, Rosser R (1989) Psychosis, and anti-tuberculosis therapy. Lancet 2(8654):105. 10.1016/s0140-6736(89)90344-9"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Baytunca MB, Erermis S, Bildik T et al (2015) Isoniazid-induced psychosis with obsessive-compulsive symptoms (schizo-obsessive disorder) in a female child. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol 25(10):819–820. 10.1089/cap.2014.0065
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1089/cap.2014.0065"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="25265091"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Baytunca MB, Erermis S, Bildik T et al (2015) Isoniazid-induced psychosis with obsessive-compulsive symptoms (schizo-obsessive disorder) in a female child. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol 25(10):819–820. 10.1089/cap.2014.0065"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Demartini B, Camisasca M, Zuin M et al (2013) A case of isoniazid-induced delirium. J Neuropsychiatry Clin Neurosci 25(2):e68–e69. 10.1176/appi.neuropsych.12020022
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1176/appi.neuropsych.12020022"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="23686075"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Demartini B, Camisasca M, Zuin M et al (2013) A case of isoniazid-induced delirium. J Neuropsychiatry Clin Neurosci 25(2):e68–e69. 10.1176/appi.neuropsych.12020022"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Duke T, Mai M (1999) Meningitis, or madness: a delicate balance. J Paediatr Child Health 35(3):319–320. 10.1046/j.1440-1754.1999.00344.x
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1046/j.1440-1754.1999.00344.x"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="10404461"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Duke T, Mai M (1999) Meningitis, or madness: a delicate balance. J Paediatr Child Health 35(3):319–320. 10.1046/j.1440-1754.1999.00344.x"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Duncan H, Kerr D (1962) Toxic psychosis due to isoniazid. Br J Dis Chest 56(3):131–138. 10.1016/s0007-0971(62)80045-x
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/s0007-0971(62)80045-x"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="13888438"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Duncan H, Kerr D (1962) Toxic psychosis due to isoniazid. Br J Dis Chest 56(3):131–138. 10.1016/s0007-0971(62)80045-x"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Gnam W, Flint A, Goldbloom D (1993) Isoniazid-induced hallucinosis: response to pyridoxine. Psychosomatics 34(6):537–539. 10.1016/S0033-3182(93)71836-8
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/S0033-3182(93)71836-8"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="8284347"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Gnam W, Flint A, Goldbloom D (1993) Isoniazid-induced hallucinosis: response to pyridoxine. Psychosomatics 34(6):537–539. 10.1016/S0033-3182(93)71836-8"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Iannaccone R, Sue YJ, Avner JR (2002) Suicidal psychosis secondary to isoniazid. Pediatr Emerg Care 18(1):25–27. 10.1097/00006565-200202000-00008
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1097/00006565-200202000-00008"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="11862134"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Iannaccone R, Sue YJ, Avner JR (2002) Suicidal psychosis secondary to isoniazid. Pediatr Emerg Care 18(1):25–27. 10.1097/00006565-200202000-00008"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ibrahim ZY, Menke JJ (1994) Comment: isoniazid-induced psychosis. Ann Pharmacother 28(11):1311. 10.1177/106002809402801131
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1177/106002809402801131"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="7849363"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Ibrahim ZY, Menke JJ (1994) Comment: isoniazid-induced psychosis. Ann Pharmacother 28(11):1311. 10.1177/106002809402801131"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Kargiotis O, Marangos M, Polychronopoulos P (2015) An unusual case of isoniazid toxicity. Neurol Sci 36:1037–1039. 10.1007/s10072-015-2105-5
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s10072-015-2105-5"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="25670661"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Kargiotis O, Marangos M, Polychronopoulos P (2015) An unusual case of isoniazid toxicity. Neurol Sci 36:1037–1039. 10.1007/s10072-015-2105-5"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Khanna S, Pant S, Khanna H (2023) Isoniazid-induced psychosis in a patient with pulmonary tuberculosis: a case report. Case Rep Neurol 15(1):76–80. 10.1159/000530779
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1159/000530779"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC10294240"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37384039"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Khanna S, Pant S, Khanna H (2023) Isoniazid-induced psychosis in a patient with pulmonary tuberculosis: a case report. Case Rep Neurol 15(1):76–80. 10.1159/000530779"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Madan A, Jain NK, Sharma TN et al (1989) Attempted suicide following treatment with isoniazid. Tubercle 70(2):147–149. 10.1016/0041-3879(89)90041-x
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/0041-3879(89)90041-x"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="2617689"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Madan A, Jain NK, Sharma TN et al (1989) Attempted suicide following treatment with isoniazid. Tubercle 70(2):147–149. 10.1016/0041-3879(89)90041-x"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Menon VB, Shaji R, Pereira P (2017) Isoniazid associated psychosis: a case series of 3 patients. Indian J Phar Pract 10(2):142–146. 10.5530/IJOPP.10.2.29</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Menon VB, Shaji R, Pereira P (2017) Isoniazid associated psychosis: a case series of 3 patients. Indian J Phar Pract 10(2):142–146. 10.5530/IJOPP.10.2.29"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Mukherjee S, Roy S (2023) Acute psychosis secondary to isoniazid in a patient with pulmonary tuberculosis. Bengal Physician J 10(2):73–74</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Mukherjee S, Roy S (2023) Acute psychosis secondary to isoniazid in a patient with pulmonary tuberculosis. Bengal Physician J 10(2):73–74"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Nagano H, Miura T, Ueda T (2019) Mania induced by isoniazid preventive therapy during steroid treatment for rheumatoid arthritis and organising pneumonia. BMJ Case Rep 12(11):e231919. 10.1136/bcr-2019-231919
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1136/bcr-2019-231919"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC6827813"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="31678927"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Nagano H, Miura T, Ueda T (2019) Mania induced by isoniazid preventive therapy during steroid treatment for rheumatoid arthritis and organising pneumonia. BMJ Case Rep 12(11):e231919. 10.1136/bcr-2019-231919"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Oninla SO, Oyedeji GA, Oninla OA et al (2016) Isoniazid-induced psychosis in 2 children treated for tuberculosis: case reports and literature review. Int J Med Pharm Case Rep 6(4):1–6. 10.9734/IJMPCR/2016/23675</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Oninla SO, Oyedeji GA, Oninla OA et al (2016) Isoniazid-induced psychosis in 2 children treated for tuberculosis: case reports and literature review. Int J Med Pharm Case Rep 6(4):1–6. 10.9734/IJMPCR/2016/23675"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Rajpal S, Kumar R, Dhingra V et al (2000) Isoniazid-induced psychosis – a case report. Indian J Allergy Appl Immunol 14(1):25–27</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Rajpal S, Kumar R, Dhingra V et al (2000) Isoniazid-induced psychosis – a case report. Indian J Allergy Appl Immunol 14(1):25–27"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Singh H, Devi HJG, Chabaria M et al (2018) Isoniazid associated psychosis: case series from a tertiary care centre. Open J Psychiatry Allied Sci 9(2):161–163. 10.5958/2394-2061.2018.00019.8</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Singh H, Devi HJG, Chabaria M et al (2018) Isoniazid associated psychosis: case series from a tertiary care centre. Open J Psychiatry Allied Sci 9(2):161–163. 10.5958/2394-2061.2018.00019.8"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Jackson SL (1957) Psychosis due to isoniazid. Br Med J 2(5047):743–746. 10.1136/bmj.2.5047.743
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1136/bmj.2.5047.743"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC1962233"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="13460372"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Jackson SL (1957) Psychosis due to isoniazid. Br Med J 2(5047):743–746. 10.1136/bmj.2.5047.743"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Umut G, Dernek B, Kucukparlak I et al (2016) Acute psychotic attack under isoniazid treatment: a case report. Dusunen Adam J Psychiatry Neurol Sci 29(4):379–381. 10.5350/DAJPN2016290411</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Umut G, Dernek B, Kucukparlak I et al (2016) Acute psychotic attack under isoniazid treatment: a case report. Dusunen Adam J Psychiatry Neurol Sci 29(4):379–381. 10.5350/DAJPN2016290411"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wiedorn WS, Ervin F (1954) Schizophrenic like psychotic reactions with administration of isoniazid. AMA Arch Neurol 72(3):321–324. 10.1001/archneurpsyc.1954.02330030055005</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1001/archneurpsyc.1954.02330030055005"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="13196751"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Wiedorn WS, Ervin F (1954) Schizophrenic like psychotic reactions with administration of isoniazid. AMA Arch Neurol 72(3):321–324. 10.1001/archneurpsyc.1954.02330030055005"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Witkowski AE, Manabat CG, Bourgeois JA (2007) Isoniazid-associated psychosis. Gen Hosp Psychiatry 29(1):85–86. 10.1016/j.genhosppsych.2006.10.010
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.genhosppsych.2006.10.010"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="17189755"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Witkowski AE, Manabat CG, Bourgeois JA (2007) Isoniazid-associated psychosis. Gen Hosp Psychiatry 29(1):85–86. 10.1016/j.genhosppsych.2006.10.010"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Chaturvedi SK, Upadhyaya M (1988) Secondary mania in a patient receiving isonicotinic acid hydrazide and pyridoxine: case report. Can J Psychiatry 33(7):675–676. 10.1177/070674378803300729
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1177/070674378803300729"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="3197022"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Chaturvedi SK, Upadhyaya M (1988) Secondary mania in a patient receiving isonicotinic acid hydrazide and pyridoxine: case report. Can J Psychiatry 33(7):675–676. 10.1177/070674378803300729"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Global Tuberculosis report 2022 (2022) <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240061729" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240061729</ext-link>. Accessed 3 June 2023</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Adams M, Tavakoli H (2006) Gatifloxacin-induced hallucinations in a 19-year-old man. Psychosomatics 47(4):360. 10.1176/appi.psy.47.4.360
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1176/appi.psy.47.4.360"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="16844899"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Adams M, Tavakoli H (2006) Gatifloxacin-induced hallucinations in a 19-year-old man. Psychosomatics 47(4):360. 10.1176/appi.psy.47.4.360"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR45"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Davison K, Roth M (1996) Substance-induced psychosis. Br J Psychiatry 168(5):651. 10.1192/bjp.168.5.651b
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1192/bjp.168.5.651b"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="8829765"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Davison K, Roth M (1996) Substance-induced psychosis. Br J Psychiatry 168(5):651. 10.1192/bjp.168.5.651b"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Martin SJ, Bowden FJ (2007) Ethambutol toxicity manifesting as acute onset psychosis. Int J STD AIDS 18(4):287–288. 10.1258/095646207780658863
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1258/095646207780658863"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="17509184"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Martin SJ, Bowden FJ (2007) Ethambutol toxicity manifesting as acute onset psychosis. Int J STD AIDS 18(4):287–288. 10.1258/095646207780658863"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR47"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Pachi A, Bratis D, Moussas G et al (2013) Psychiatric morbidity, and other factors affecting treatment adherence in pulmonary tuberculosis patients. Tuberc Res Treat 2013:489865. 10.1155/2013/489865
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1155/2013/489865"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC3649695"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="23691305"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Pachi A, Bratis D, Moussas G et al (2013) Psychiatric morbidity, and other factors affecting treatment adherence in pulmonary tuberculosis patients. Tuberc Res Treat 2013:489865. 10.1155/2013/489865"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR48"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Li A, Yuan SY, Li QG et al (2023) Prevalence and risk factors of malnutrition in patients with pulmonary tuberculosis: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Front Med (Lausanne) 10:1173619. 10.3389/fmed.2023.1173619
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3389/fmed.2023.1173619"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC10448260"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37636566"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Li A, Yuan SY, Li QG et al (2023) Prevalence and risk factors of malnutrition in patients with pulmonary tuberculosis: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Front Med (Lausanne) 10:1173619. 10.3389/fmed.2023.1173619"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR49"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Brodrick BB, Jacobs MA, McAdams CJ (2020) Psychosis in anorexia nervosa: a case report and review of the literature. Psychosomatics 61(2):181–187. 10.1016/j.psym.2019.06.003
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.psym.2019.06.003"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC6933101"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="31371095"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Brodrick BB, Jacobs MA, McAdams CJ (2020) Psychosis in anorexia nervosa: a case report and review of the literature. Psychosomatics 61(2):181–187. 10.1016/j.psym.2019.06.003"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR50"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Gao J, Zheng P, Fu H (2013) Prevalence of TB/HIV co-infection in countries except China: a systematic review and meta-analysis. PLoS ONE 8(5):e64915. 10.1371/journal.pone.0064915
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pone.0064915"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC3669088"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="23741419"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Gao J, Zheng P, Fu H (2013) Prevalence of TB/HIV co-infection in countries except China: a systematic review and meta-analysis. PLoS ONE 8(5):e64915. 10.1371/journal.pone.0064915"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR51"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Chhagan U, Ntlantsana V, Tomita A et al (2021) The dual burden of HIV infection and first-episode psychosis in Africa: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Nerv Ment Dis 209(8):600–608. 10.1097/NMD.0000000000001366
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1097/NMD.0000000000001366"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34397760"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Chhagan U, Ntlantsana V, Tomita A et al (2021) The dual burden of HIV infection and first-episode psychosis in Africa: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Nerv Ment Dis 209(8):600–608. 10.1097/NMD.0000000000001366"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR52"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wise ME, Mistry K, Reid S (2002) Drug points: neuropsychiatric complications of nevirapine treatment. BMJ 324(7342):879. 10.1136/bmj.324.7342.879
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1136/bmj.324.7342.879"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC101401"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="11950737"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Wise ME, Mistry K, Reid S (2002) Drug points: neuropsychiatric complications of nevirapine treatment. BMJ 324(7342):879. 10.1136/bmj.324.7342.879"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR53"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Foster R, Olajide D, Everall IP (2003) Antiretroviral therapy-induced psychosis: case report and brief review of the literature. HIV Med 4(2):139–144. 10.1046/j.1468-1293.2003.00142.x
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1046/j.1468-1293.2003.00142.x"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="12702135"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Foster R, Olajide D, Everall IP (2003) Antiretroviral therapy-induced psychosis: case report and brief review of the literature. HIV Med 4(2):139–144. 10.1046/j.1468-1293.2003.00142.x"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR54"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Masuka JT, Chipangura P, Nyambayo PP et al (2018) A comparison of adverse drug reaction profiles in patients on antiretroviral and antitubercular treatment in Zimbabwe. Clin Drug Investig 38(1):9–17. 10.1007/s40261-017-0579-z
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s40261-017-0579-z"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="28965312"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Masuka JT, Chipangura P, Nyambayo PP et al (2018) A comparison of adverse drug reaction profiles in patients on antiretroviral and antitubercular treatment in Zimbabwe. Clin Drug Investig 38(1):9–17. 10.1007/s40261-017-0579-z"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR55"><named-content content-type="citation-string">O’Connor C, Patel P, Brady MF (2024) Isoniazid. StatPearls Publishing, Treasure Island (FL)</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32491549"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="O’Connor C, Patel P, Brady MF (2024) Isoniazid. StatPearls Publishing, Treasure Island (FL)"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR56"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Thomas L, Raju AP, Chaithra et al (2022) Influence of N-acetyltransferase 2 (NAT2) genotype/single nucleotide polymorphisms on clearance of isoniazid in tuberculosis patients: a systematic review of population pharmacokinetic models. Eur J Clin Pharmacol 78(10):1535–1553. 10.1007/s00228-022-03362-7
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s00228-022-03362-7"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9482569"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="35852584"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Thomas L, Raju AP, Chaithra et al (2022) Influence of N-acetyltransferase 2 (NAT2) genotype/single nucleotide polymorphisms on clearance of isoniazid in tuberculosis patients: a systematic review of population pharmacokinetic models. Eur J Clin Pharmacol 78(10):1535–1553. 10.1007/s00228-022-03362-7"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR57"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zhang M, Wang S, Wilffert B et al (2018) The association between the NAT2 genetic polymorphisms and risk of DILI during anti-TB treatment: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Br J Clin Pharmacol 84(12):2747–2760. 10.1111/bcp.13722
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/bcp.13722"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC6256008"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="30047605"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Zhang M, Wang S, Wilffert B et al (2018) The association between the NAT2 genetic polymorphisms and risk of DILI during anti-TB treatment: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Br J Clin Pharmacol 84(12):2747–2760. 10.1111/bcp.13722"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR58"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Thomas L, Raju AP, Chaithra S et al (2024) Influence of N-acetyltransferase 2 polymorphisms and clinical variables on liver function profile of tuberculosis patients. Expert Rev Clin Pharmacol 17(3):263–274. 10.1080/17512433.2024.2311314
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1080/17512433.2024.2311314"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38287694"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Thomas L, Raju AP, Chaithra S et al (2024) Influence of N-acetyltransferase 2 polymorphisms and clinical variables on liver function profile of tuberculosis patients. Expert Rev Clin Pharmacol 17(3):263–274. 10.1080/17512433.2024.2311314"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR59"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ben-Chetrit E, Rothstein N, Munter G (2013) Ciprofloxacin-induced psychosis. Antimicrob Agents Chemother 57(8):4079. 10.1128/AAC.00672-13
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1128/AAC.00672-13"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC3719694"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="23669392"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Ben-Chetrit E, Rothstein N, Munter G (2013) Ciprofloxacin-induced psychosis. Antimicrob Agents Chemother 57(8):4079. 10.1128/AAC.00672-13"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR60"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bernardo M, Gatell JM, Parellada E (1991) Acute exacerbation of chronic schizophrenia in a patient treated with antituberculosis drugs. Am J Psychiatry 148(10):1402. 10.1176/ajp.148.10.1402
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1176/ajp.148.10.1402"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="1897624"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Bernardo M, Gatell JM, Parellada E (1991) Acute exacerbation of chronic schizophrenia in a patient treated with antituberculosis drugs. Am J Psychiatry 148(10):1402. 10.1176/ajp.148.10.1402"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR61"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bhalerao S, Talsky A, Hansen K et al (2006) Ciprofloxacin-induced manic episode. Psychosomatics 47(6):539–540. 10.1176/appi.psy.47.6.539
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1176/appi.psy.47.6.539"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="17116962"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Bhalerao S, Talsky A, Hansen K et al (2006) Ciprofloxacin-induced manic episode. Psychosomatics 47(6):539–540. 10.1176/appi.psy.47.6.539"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR62"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Hakko E, Mete B, Ozaras R et al (2005) Levofloxacin-induced delirium. Clin Neurol Neurosurg 107(2):158–159. 10.1016/j.clineuro.2004.05.006
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.clineuro.2004.05.006"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="15708235"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Hakko E, Mete B, Ozaras R et al (2005) Levofloxacin-induced delirium. Clin Neurol Neurosurg 107(2):158–159. 10.1016/j.clineuro.2004.05.006"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR63"><named-content content-type="citation-string">McDonald CA, Addis S (2003) Cephalosporin-induced psychosis. Aust N Z J Psychiatry 37(5):627–628. 10.1046/j.1440-1614.2003.01243.x
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1046/j.1440-1614.2003.01243.x"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="14511096"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="McDonald CA, Addis S (2003) Cephalosporin-induced psychosis. Aust N Z J Psychiatry 37(5):627–628. 10.1046/j.1440-1614.2003.01243.x"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR64"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Reeves RR (1992) Ciprofloxacin-induced psychosis. Ann Pharmacother 26(7–8):930–931. 10.1177/106002809202600716
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1177/106002809202600716"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="1504404"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Reeves RR (1992) Ciprofloxacin-induced psychosis. Ann Pharmacother 26(7–8):930–931. 10.1177/106002809202600716"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">World Health Organization (1992) The ICD-10 classification of mental and behavioural disorders: clinical descriptions and diagnostic guidelines. World Health Organization, Geneva. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9241544228" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9241544228</ext-link>. Accessed 02 Jun 2024</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR66"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Poole R, Brabbins C (1996) Drug induced psychosis. Br J Psychiatry 168(2):135–138. 10.1192/bjp.168.2.135
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1192/bjp.168.2.135"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="8837900"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Poole R, Brabbins C (1996) Drug induced psychosis. Br J Psychiatry 168(2):135–138. 10.1192/bjp.168.2.135"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR67"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Toriumi K, Miyashita M, Suzuki K et al (2021) Vitamin B6 deficiency hyperactivates the noradrenergic system, leading to social deficits and cognitive impairment. Transl Psychiatry 11(1):262. 10.1038/s41398-021-01381-z
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41398-021-01381-z"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC8093222"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33941768"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Toriumi K, Miyashita M, Suzuki K et al (2021) Vitamin B6 deficiency hyperactivates the noradrenergic system, leading to social deficits and cognitive impairment. Transl Psychiatry 11(1):262. 10.1038/s41398-021-01381-z"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR68"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sandyk R, Pardeshi R (1990) Pyridoxine improves drug-induced parkinsonism and psychosis in a schizophrenic patient. Int J Neurosci 52(3–4):225–232. 10.3109/00207459009000524
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3109/00207459009000524"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="2269609"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Sandyk R, Pardeshi R (1990) Pyridoxine improves drug-induced parkinsonism and psychosis in a schizophrenic patient. Int J Neurosci 52(3–4):225–232. 10.3109/00207459009000524"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR69"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lerner V, Miodownik C, Kaptsan A et al (2001) Vitamin B(6) in the treatment of tardive dyskinesia: a double-blind, placebo-controlled, crossover study. Am J Psychiatry 158(9):1511–1514. 10.1176/appi.ajp.158.9.1511
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1176/appi.ajp.158.9.1511"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="11532741"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Lerner V, Miodownik C, Kaptsan A et al (2001) Vitamin B(6) in the treatment of tardive dyskinesia: a double-blind, placebo-controlled, crossover study. Am J Psychiatry 158(9):1511–1514. 10.1176/appi.ajp.158.9.1511"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR70"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lerner V, Bergman J, Statsenko N et al (2004) Vitamin B6 treatment in acute neuroleptic-induced akathisia: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study. J Clin Psychiatry 65(11):1550–1554. 10.4088/jcp.v65n1118
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.4088/jcp.v65n1118"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="15554771"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Lerner V, Bergman J, Statsenko N et al (2004) Vitamin B6 treatment in acute neuroleptic-induced akathisia: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study. J Clin Psychiatry 65(11):1550–1554. 10.4088/jcp.v65n1118"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR71"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Adelufosi AO, Abayomi O (2015) Ojo TM (2015) Pyridoxal 5 phosphate for neuroleptic-induced tardive dyskinesia. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 4:CD010501. 10.1002/14651858.CD010501.pub2</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1002/14651858.CD010501.pub2"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11064773"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="25866243"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Adelufosi AO, Abayomi O (2015) Ojo TM (2015) Pyridoxal 5 phosphate for neuroleptic-induced tardive dyskinesia. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 4:CD010501. 10.1002/14651858.CD010501.pub2"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR72"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Shams-Alizadeh N, Bakhshayesh H, Rezaei F et al (2018) Effect of vitamin B6 versus propranolol on antipsychotic-induced akathisia: a pilot comparative double-blind study. Iran J Pharm Res 17(Suppl):130–135
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC5958332"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="29796037"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Shams-Alizadeh N, Bakhshayesh H, Rezaei F et al (2018) Effect of vitamin B6 versus propranolol on antipsychotic-induced akathisia: a pilot comparative double-blind study. Iran J Pharm Res 17(Suppl):130–135"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR73"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Chan TYK (1999) Pyridoxine ineffective in isoniazid-induced psychosis. Ann Pharmacother 33(10):1123–1124. 10.1345/aph.19022
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1345/aph.19022"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="10534228"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Chan TYK (1999) Pyridoxine ineffective in isoniazid-induced psychosis. Ann Pharmacother 33(10):1123–1124. 10.1345/aph.19022"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR74"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Yadav R, Kumar M, Kumar N et al (2022) Pyridoxine in isoniazid-induced psychosis. Sudan J Paediatr 22(2):190–192. 10.24911/SJP.106-1584524803
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.24911/SJP.106-1584524803"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9983769"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36875946"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Yadav R, Kumar M, Kumar N et al (2022) Pyridoxine in isoniazid-induced psychosis. Sudan J Paediatr 22(2):190–192. 10.24911/SJP.106-1584524803"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR75"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Choke A, Perumal M, Howlett M (2007) Lorazepam prescription and monitoring in acute adult psychiatric wards. Psychiatri Bull 31(8):300–303. 10.1192/PB.BP.106.012328</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Choke A, Perumal M, Howlett M (2007) Lorazepam prescription and monitoring in acute adult psychiatric wards. Psychiatri Bull 31(8):300–303. 10.1192/PB.BP.106.012328"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR76"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Mackin P, Thomas SH (2011) Atypical antipsychotic drugs. BMJ 342:d1126. 10.1136/bmj.d1126
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1136/bmj.d1126"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="21378070"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Mackin P, Thomas SH (2011) Atypical antipsychotic drugs. BMJ 342:d1126. 10.1136/bmj.d1126"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR77"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Atmaja DS, Yulistiani S et al (2022) Detection tools for prediction and identification of adverse drug reactions in older patients: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Sci Rep 12(1):13189. 10.1038/s41598-022-17410-w
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41598-022-17410-w"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9341414"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="35915219"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Atmaja DS, Yulistiani S et al (2022) Detection tools for prediction and identification of adverse drug reactions in older patients: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Sci Rep 12(1):13189. 10.1038/s41598-022-17410-w"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR78"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bihan K, Lebrun-Vignes B, Funck-Brentano C et al (2020) Uses of pharmacovigilance databases: an overview. Therapie 75(6):591–598. 10.1016/j.therap.2020.02.022
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.therap.2020.02.022"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32169289"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Bihan K, Lebrun-Vignes B, Funck-Brentano C et al (2020) Uses of pharmacovigilance databases: an overview. Therapie 75(6):591–598. 10.1016/j.therap.2020.02.022"/></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></sec></sec><sec id="_ad93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="associated-data" disp-level="1"><title>Associated Data</title><sec id="_adsm93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="supplementary-materials" disp-level="2"><title>Supplementary Materials</title><supplementary-material id="db_ds_supplementary-material1_reqid_" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="228_2024_3738_MOESM1_ESM.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document"><?cloudpmc-path 9dd3/11458663/128ebec9fa77/228_2024_3738_MOESM1_ESM.docx?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 30307?><label>Supplemental Table 1</label><caption><p>(DOCX 29 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="db_ds_supplementary-material2_reqid_" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="228_2024_3738_MOESM2_ESM.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document"><?cloudpmc-path 9dd3/11458663/4ac9595df331/228_2024_3738_MOESM2_ESM.docx?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 14672?><label>Supplemental Table 2</label><caption><p>(DOCX 14 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="db_ds_supplementary-material3_reqid_" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="228_2024_3738_Fig4_ESM.png" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png"><?cloudpmc-path 9dd3/11458663/00210953b7bc/228_2024_3738_Fig4_ESM.png?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 156878?><label>Supplemental Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Isoniazid induced psychosis symptoms profile. Footnote: * Cases that were not isoniazid induced psychosis has been excluded from the case series. Abbreviation: Form_tht_dis: Formal thought disorder (PNG 153 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="db_ds_supplementary-material4_reqid_" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="228_2024_3738_MOESM3_ESM.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><?cloudpmc-path 9dd3/11458663/97ca827d5d7c/228_2024_3738_MOESM3_ESM.tif?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 709144?><caption><p>High resolution image (TIF 692 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="db_ds_supplementary-material5_reqid_" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="228_2024_3738_Fig5_ESM.png" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png"><?cloudpmc-path 9dd3/11458663/93a0e52ea24d/228_2024_3738_Fig5_ESM.png?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 137689?><label>Supplemental Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Quality assessment of included studies. Footnote: <sup>1</sup>Tool for evaluating the methodological quality of case reports and case series developed by Murad et al. <sup>2</sup>* Cases that were not isoniazid induced psychosis has been excluded from the case series. <sup>3</sup> Q1: Does the patient(s) represent(s) the whole experience of the investigator (centre) or is the selection method unclear to the extent that other patients with similar presentation may not have been reported? Q2: Was the exposure adequately ascertained? Q3: Was the outcome adequately ascertained? Q4: Were other alternative causes that may explain the observation ruled out? Q5: Was there a challenge/rechallenge phenomenon? Q6: Was there a dose-response effect? Q7: Is the case(s) described with sufficient details to allow other investigators to replicate the research or to allow practitioners make inferences related to their own practice? Abbreviation: Q: Question (PNG 134 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="db_ds_supplementary-material6_reqid_" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="228_2024_3738_MOESM4_ESM.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><?cloudpmc-path 9dd3/11458663/923131e6276e/228_2024_3738_MOESM4_ESM.tif?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 540718?><caption><p>High resolution image (TIF 528 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="_adda93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="data-availability-statement" disp-level="2"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>No datasets were generated or analyzed during the current study.</p></sec></sec></body></article>