<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><article xml:lang="en" article-type="review-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3800</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmcnutrition</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Nutrition</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title>BMC Nutr</abbrev-journal-title></journal-title-group><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12226867</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12226867</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12226867</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40616189</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40795-025-01107-0</article-id><title-group><article-title>Are there prophylactic effects of vitamin D among healthier adult patients? A systematic review of randomized controlled trials</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="author"><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Goswami</surname><given-names initials="C">Caroline</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="_fncrsp93pmc__">✉</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="_eqcntrb93pmc__">#</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Law</surname><given-names initials="S">Sherrice</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="_eqcntrb93pmc__">#</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="H">Hannah</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names initials="H">Hannah</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Maheta</surname><given-names initials="B">Bhagvat</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnott</surname><given-names initials="K">Katherine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names initials="M">Megan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Truong</surname><given-names initials="K">Kevin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheffield</surname><given-names initials="M">Mark</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Iqbal</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zahid</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Limanon</surname><given-names initials="C">Chainaronk</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Pai</surname><given-names initials="D">David</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>California Northstate University College of Medicine, 9700 W Taron Dr, Elk Grove, CA USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Sacramento Community Clinic, Sacramento, CA USA </aff><author-notes><fn id="_fncrsp93pmc__"><label>✉</label><p>Corresponding author.</p></fn><fn id="_eqcntrb93pmc__"><label>#</label><p>Contributed equally.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date><day>4</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><fpage>118</fpage><page-range>118</page-range><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>4</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><license><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/" ext-link-type="uri">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="40795_2025_Article_1107.pdf" content-type="pmc-pdf"><?cloudpmc-path 85ab/12226867/92f3997b196c/40795_2025_Article_1107.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 1191952?></self-uri><abstract id="Abs1"><title>Abstract</title><sec id="sec1" disp-level="2"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par1">In 2017, a study uncovered increasing trends in vitamin D supplementation, revealing that 18% of adults exceeded 1000 international units (IU) daily, and 3% surpassed the safe limit of 4000 IU, raising concern for severe hypercalcemia and associated pathological effects on the kidneys, heart, and vascular system. While vitamin D is well-established for prophylactic use against osteomalacia and osteoporosis, its extra-skeletal benefits for healthy individuals, such as improving insulin sensitivity and low-density lipoprotein, remain unclear. This study focuses on defining healthy adults and exploring the potential benefits and drawbacks of prophylactic vitamin D supplementation.</p></sec><sec id="sec2" disp-level="2"><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">Using PubMed, EMBASE, and Scopus databases, 10,155 articles on vitamin D prophylaxis were identified. Randomized controlled trials targeting healthy patients receiving vitamin D for prophylaxis were included, with exclusions based on language, absence of reported outcomes, and patient history. Articles were screened and evaluated by Covidence and the Cochrane Risk of Bias tool, respectively. Dosage, form, frequency, duration, follow-up care, outcomes, and complications of included articles were recorded. This study protocol has been registered to PROSPERO: CRD42023446944.</p></sec><sec id="sec3" disp-level="2"><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Out of 18 articles, 4,415 patients showed low bias risk by the Cochrane tool. Seven studies found significant improvements: protection against autoimmune reactions, elevated hematological and iron profiles, reduced influenza-like illness, and enhanced cognitive tasks. 5000 IU Vitamin D for four weeks significantly reduced cholesterol, unlike 1000 IU for 16 weeks. Conversely, 11 studies revealed no Vitamin D impact on outcomes including hemoglobin-A1c, lipoproteins, BMI, blood pressures, and respiratory infections.</p></sec><sec id="sec4" disp-level="2"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">Except for a few outcomes, most prophylactic Vitamin D supplementation was generally not found to have statistically significant benefits in the healthy adult population. Future directions can include additional prospective studies with larger sample sizes of healthy adults testing for benefits and adverse effects of prophylactic vitamin D use.</p></sec><sec id="sec5" disp-level="2"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s40795-025-01107-0.</p></sec><sec id="kwd-group1" xml:lang="en" sec-type="kwd-group" disp-level="2"><p><bold>Keywords:</bold> Vitamin D, Prophylaxis, Vitamin toxicity, Vitamin overprescription, Systematic review</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>status</meta-name><meta-value>released</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>display-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-journal-matter</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-scanned</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-retracted</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes notes-type="article-notes"><sec id="historyarticle-meta1" sec-type="history" disp-level="2"><p>Received 2024 Jun 19; Accepted 2025 May 30; Collection date 2025.</p></sec></notes></front><body><sec id="Sec1" disp-level="1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par5">Vitamin D is a prohormone that is important for maintaining bone health and calcium levels. Vitamin D is found in two forms: ergocalciferol (vitamin D2) and cholecalciferol (vitamin D3). Studies have shown that vitamin D3 is more effective than vitamin D2 in raising serum 25-hydroxyvitamin D (25OHD), an established marker of vitamin D status [<xref rid="CR1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Vitamin D3 deficiency is defined as &lt; 30 nmol/l 25(OH)D, while adequate levels are generally defined as 50 nmol/l 25(OH)D or above. Levels above 125 nmol/l are considered too high and are linked to potential adverse effects. Deficiency in vitamin D3 results in hypocalcemia and defective bone mineralization [<xref rid="CR2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. In addition, vitamin D3 deficiency may be associated with increased risks for autoimmune diseases, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, cancer, and metabolic syndrome [<xref rid="CR3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. A large consensus exists that vitamin D supplementation improves measures related to bone health, especially in individuals with poor vitamin D status, higher risk of osteoporosis, or insufficient exposure to sunlight. However, no relationship has been firmly established between vitamin D and other health outcomes, although extraskeletal effects have been suggested because of the wide expression of the vitamin D3 receptor in the human body, including in the immune, renal, nervous, and cardiovascular system [<xref rid="CR2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="CR4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].</p><p id="Par6">The recommended doses for vitamin D supplementation vary widely (from 200 IU to 2000 IU daily) and have changed as countries and scientific societies now recommend higher doses than before [<xref rid="CR5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Correspondingly, the use of vitamin D3 supplements has increased, and recent data shows that vitamin D3 was the 65th most commonly prescribed medication in the United States in 2021, with more than 10 million prescriptions [<xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. With the growing use of vitamin D by the general population, there is a need to examine the health effects of supplementation in vitamin D-replete patients. Although many studies have shown benefits of supplementation for the improvement of vitamin D3 deficiency and bone-related pathologies, far fewer have investigated the risks and benefits of supplementing vitamin D-replete adults. One such study found that supplementing vitamin D-replete adults demonstrated no overall health benefits on bone density, risk of falls, incidence of cancer, cardiovascular events, and type 2 diabetes mellitus [<xref rid="CR2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Further research is necessary to definitively establish the effects of vitamin D supplementation in healthy individuals, especially as increased supplementation may pose a risk for exogenous hypervitaminosis D with various findings, such as hypercalcemia [<xref rid="CR3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Thus, this systematic review aimed to discuss the efficacy and safety of vitamin D prophylaxis for diseases of the extraskeletal system in healthy adult patients.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22" disp-level="1"><title>Methods</title><p id="Par7">This review followed the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analysis Protocols (PRISMA-P) Statement and Enhancing the QUAlity and Transparency Of health Research (EQUATOR) guidelines. This protocol is registered in the PROSPERO database under the registration number CRD42023446944.</p><sec id="Sec2" disp-level="2"><title>Search strategy</title><p id="Par8">To complete this systematic review, articles were screened from several databases, including PubMed, Embase, and Scopus, using the Covidence Tool [<xref rid="CR7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Key search criteria for article retrieval included terms related to vitamin D, prevention or prophylaxis, and randomized controlled trials. The full search algorithm utilized can be found in Appendix <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">A</xref>. The initial search took place on June 28, 2023.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3" disp-level="2"><title>Article selection</title><p id="Par9">A total of 10,155 articles, investigating vitamin D prophylaxis in healthy patients were selected. Two reviewers independently reviewed the title and abstract based on the eligibility criteria. If any systematic reviews met the inclusion criteria, their reference lists were added to the screening process and the systematic reviews were rejected. Any conflicts in screening were resolved via consensus. Next, the resulting full-text articles were screened independently by two reviewers and reasons for exclusion of an article were provided. Conflicts during the full-text screening were resolved by the lead authors and the gold standard reviewers: D.P., nephrologist, M.S., endocrinologist, Z.I., internist.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4" disp-level="2"><title>Eligibility criteria</title><p id="Par10">Inclusion criteria included: healthy adult patients, randomized controlled trials (RCTs), all patients receiving vitamin D prophylaxis, peer-reviewed full-length articles, articles written in English, and outcomes are reported. Exclusion criteria included: patients with an ongoing history of hypercalcemia, patients with a diagnosis of bone pathology, patients that are considered unhealthy, and articles without outcomes. Pregnant patients were excluded, as the benefits of vitamin D on this population are well studied in literature. Eligibility criteria is further summarized in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> using a Population, Intervention, Comparator, Outcomes, Timing, and Setting (PICOTS) framework.</p><table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>PICOTS eligibility criteria</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Population</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>
<bold>Inclusion</bold>
</p><p> ● Adults (&gt; 18 years old) who are considered healthy</p><p> ● Patients are healthy (no history of chronic disease, end-organ damage, or pre-existing condition with proven benefits of vitamin D3 supplementation)</p><p> ● Peer-reviewed article</p><p>
<bold>Exclusion</bold>
</p><p> ● Pediatric (&lt; 18 years old) patients</p><p> ● Pregnant or postmenopausal patients</p><p> ● Patients had a history of ongoing hypercalcemia causing bone, kidney, gastrointestinal, or psychiatric related issues.</p><p> ● Patients had a diagnosis of rickets, osteoporosis, or osteomalacia</p><p> ● Patients who are unhealthy (have a history of chronic disease, end-organ damage, or pre-existing condition with proven benefits of vitamin D3 supplementation)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Intervention</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>
<bold>Inclusion</bold>
</p><p> ● All patients in the treatment arm received a prescription vitamin D3 prophylaxis.</p><p>
<bold>Exclusion</bold>
</p><p> ● All patients in the treatment arm did not receive a vitamin D3 prophylaxis.</p><p> ● Vitamin D3 prophylaxis was non-prescription (i.e. Over-the-counter).</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Comparator</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p> ● Only randomized controlled trials were included.</p><p> ● In general, the control group for eligible articles included patients receiving a placebo of equivalent route of administration rather than active vitamin D3. However, in the event that a placebo was not possible (i.e. UV-administered light) then the control group received no intervention.</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Outcomes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>
<bold>Inclusion</bold>
</p><p> ● Outcomes analyzed:</p><p>  ○ Varied depending on the disease for which the vitamin D was intended, but included such things prophylactic trends, laboratory values, symptom complaints, confirmed diagnosis of infection, hospital admission, and/or changes to symptoms following vitamin D3 supplementation.</p><p> ● Articles without outcomes were excluded.</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Timing</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ● Interventions with any timing, duration, and follow-up period were included.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Setting</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ● Interventions with any care setting (including in-patient or out-patient).</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="Sec5" disp-level="2"><title>Data extraction/analysis</title><p id="Par11">An abstraction form was developed to standardize data extraction (Appendix B). Two reviewers independently extracted data and did a study quality assessment for each study included using Covidence, and discrepancies were resolved through consensus. The Cochrane Risk of Bias tool [<xref rid="CR8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] was employed to assess the potential for bias in each RCT included. Information collected included study name, number of patients, patient demographics, age, comorbidities, dose of vitamin D3, frequency, and duration of vitamin D3 dose. The main outcomes collected were prophylactic trends, laboratory values, symptom complaints, and changes to symptoms following supplementation. Reviewers also considered the change in outcomes over time, quantified the number of studies with similar methods, and assessed the extent of follow-up within each study. Due to significant heterogeneity, the extracted data was analyzed through narrative synthesis.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec6" disp-level="1"><title>Results</title><p id="Par13">Out of 10,155 articles screened on Covidence, 18 studies met our inclusion criteria of being a randomized control trial that gave prophylactic vitamin D to a healthy patient population. All included studies had an overall low risk of bias assessment (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Within the included articles, 4,415 participants, ranging from age 18 to 70 years old, were studied. Variable doses of vitamin D ranging from 200 IU to 200,000 IU were given prophylactically, and all studies were categorized based on the primary organ system investigated (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The main outcomes extracted from these studies were organized by organ systems and the dose of vitamin D supplementation given (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The PRISMA flow chart illustrates the process of selecting articles in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Risk of bias of included studies</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Study</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sequence Generation</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Allocation Concealment</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Blinding of Participants and Personnel</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Blinding of Outcome Assessors</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Incomplete Outcome Data</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Selective Outcome Reporting</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other Source of Bias</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Madar 2014</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Muldowney 2014</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scragg 2014</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fourouhi 2016</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unclear</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Jastrzebski 2016</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Knutsen 2017</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Brisson 2017</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Barker 2012</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chandler 2014</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unclear</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bock 2011</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unclear</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unclear</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mielgo-Ayuso 2018</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unclear</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">High</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Knutsen 2014</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pettersen 2017</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">vanHelmond 2022</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unclear</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Murdoch 2012</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Goodall 2014</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Li-Ng 2009</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Laaksi 2010</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">High</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unclear</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Vitamin D supplementation and patient outcomes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Article</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dose (IU)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Form</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Duration</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patients (#)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patient Outcomes</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Cardiology</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Muldowney et al. 2012</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">200</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Capsule</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 weeks (wk)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">470</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No effect on parathyroid hormone, systolic and diastolic blood pressure, fasting lipids, glucose and insulin, HOMA-IR, high-sensitivity CRP, matrix metalloproteinase-9, tissue inhibitor metalloproteinase-1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>I. Madar et al. 2014</p><p>II. Muldowney et al. 2012</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">400</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>I: Tablet</p><p>II: Capsule</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>I: 16 wk</p><p>II: 22 wk</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>I: 84</p><p>II: 470</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>I: No change to glycated hemoglobin (HbA1c), fructosamine, serum lipids, and body mass index</p><p>II: No effect on biomarker risk</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Muldowney et al. 2012</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">600</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Capsule</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 wk</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">470</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No effect on parathyroid hormone, systolic and diastolic blood pressure, fasting lipids, glucose and insulin, HOMA-IR, high-sensitivity CRP, matrix metalloproteinase-9, tissue inhibitor metalloproteinase-1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Madar et al. 2014</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tablet</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 wk</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No change glycated hemoglobin (HbA1c), fructosamine, serum lipids, and body mass index</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Jastrzebski et al. 2016</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Droplet</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 wk</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Significant decrease in total cholesterol</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>I. Scragg et al. 2014</p><p>II. Forouhi et al. 2016</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100,000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>I: Tablet</p><p>II: Liquid</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>I*: 18 months (mo)</p><p>II*: 4 mo</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>I: 161</p><p>II: 226</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>I: No effect on systolic BP, diastolic BP, and HR</p><p>II: No effect on HbA1c with vitamin D2 or D3</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">
<bold>Endocrinology</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Knutsen et al. 2017</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">400</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tablet</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 wk</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">83</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No effect on TPOab and autoimmune thyroid disease prevention</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tablet</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 wk</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">85</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No effect on TPOab and autoimmune thyroid disease prevention</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">
<bold>Gynecology</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Brisson et al. 2017</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tablet</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 mo</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No reduction in breast density</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tablet</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 mo</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No reduction in breast density</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tablet</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 mo</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No reduction in breast density</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">
<bold>Immunology</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Barker et al. 2012</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">200</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not specified</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28 days (d)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prevented decrease in IL-5 response</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Chandler et al. 2014</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Capsules</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 mo</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">81</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No significant change in circulating levels of IL-6, IL-10, sTNF-R2, and CRP associated with treatment arms</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Capsules</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 mo</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">83</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No significant change in circulating levels of IL-6, IL-10, sTNF-R2, and CRP associated with treatment arms</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>I: Barker et al. 2012</p><p>II: Chandler et al. 2014</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>I: Not specified</p><p>II: Capsules</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>I: 28 d</p><p>II: 3 mo</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>I: 10</p><p>II: 83</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>I: Prevented decrease in serum IL-5</p><p>II. No significant change in circulating levels of IL-6, IL-10, sTNF-R2, and CRP associated with treatment arms</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bock et al. 2011</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">140,000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Droplet</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 wk *</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>- No significant change to C-peptide mean value</p><p>- Increase in mean percentage Tregs</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">
<bold>Musculoskeletal</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Knutsen et al. 2014</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">400</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tablet</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 wk</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">85</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No significant effect on the occurrence, anatomical localization, and degree of pain or headache compared to placebo</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tablet</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 wk</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No significant effect on the occurrence, anatomical localization, and degree of pain or headache compared to placebo</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mielgo-Ayuso et al. 2018</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Capsule</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 wk</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>- Prevented decline in hematological levels of hemoglobin and hematocrit, and improve transferrin</p><p>- No changes to testosterone and cortisol profile</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">
<bold>Neurology</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pettersen et al. 2017</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tablet</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18 wk</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>- Significant improvement on Paired Recognition Memory and nonverbal tasks</p><p>- No significant difference in verbal memory tasks</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">
<bold>Pulmonology</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Laaksi et al. 2010</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">400</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tablet</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 mo</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No significant difference in either the incidence, duration, or severity of upper respiratory tract infection (URTI) symptoms</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Li-Ng et al. 2009</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not specified</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 wk</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">78</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No benefit of vitamin D3 supplementation in decreasing the incidence or severity of symptomatic URTIs during winter</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">vanHelmond et al. 2022</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Capsule</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 mo</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">155</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Significant reduction in influenza-like illness incidence</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Goodall et al. 2014</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10,000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Capsule</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 mo**</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">150</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Significant reduction in URTI events</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Murdoch et al. 2012</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">200,000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tablet</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18 mo***</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">161</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No significant difference in URTI incidence</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="_fn_p79"><p>* Once monthly</p><p>** Once weekly</p><p>*** 200,000 IU oral vitamin D3, then 200,000 IU 1 month later, then 100,000 IU monthly</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig1" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>PRISMA Flow chart illustrating the process of selecting articles</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e398" xlink:href="40795_2025_1107_Fig1_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/85ab/12226867/187aa5dfb5f7/40795_2025_1107_Fig1_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1730?><?original-width 2008?><?scaled-height 576?><?scaled-width 669?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="40795_2025_1107_Fig1_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/85ab/12226867/4c16c086591e/40795_2025_1107_Fig1_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><sec id="Sec7" disp-level="2"><title>Cardiology</title><p id="Par17">Five out of the 18 studies studied the effects of prophylactic vitamin D on cardiovascular health. In three studies that assessed the effect of vitamin D supplementation on different biomarkers correlated with cardiovascular risk, there was no significant effect on hemoglobin A1c (HbA1c), fructosamine, and blood pressure in comparison to the placebo groups [<xref rid="CR9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="CR10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] Scragg et al. [<xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], there was a transient decrease in systolic and diastolic blood pressure at five months. Ultimately, no significant difference in blood pressure and pulse rate at the 18 month end point between those that were supplemented with 100,000 IU daily and the placebo group. In contrast, Jastrzebski et al. [<xref rid="CR12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] administered approximately 5000 IU of vitamin D daily for four weeks via a liquid form to determine its effect on total cholesterol levels and concluded a significant decrease in cholesterol levels in comparison to their placebo group. Notably, this study was limited by the study’s small sample size of 14 patients and lack of diet control. Forouhi et al. [<xref rid="CR12" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] was the only study to incorporate vitamin D2 for investigation (in addition to D3) and demonstrated a non-clinically significant reduction in arterial stiffness for both vitamin D2 and vitamin D3.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8" disp-level="2"><title>Respiratory</title><p id="Par18">Five of the included studies observed vitamin D supplementation in the prevention of respiratory infections and illness. Three of five studies observed the effects of varying doses of vitamin D supplementation in preventing upper respiratory infections (URIs). Goodall et al. [<xref rid="CR14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] and Li-Ng et al. <xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] administered 10,000 IU once a week for 2-months and 2000 IU daily for 3-months, respectively, yielding no statistical significance in the incidence of URIs. Similarly, Murdoch et al. [<xref rid="CR16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] did not observe any significant reductions in URTIs or differences in duration or severity of the URTI episodes when they administered a loading vitamin D dose of 200,000 IU initially and at one month, and subsequent 100,000 IU monthly doses for a total of 18 months. Laaksi et al. [<xref rid="CR17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] provided 400 IU of daily vitamin D supplementation and also reported no significant difference between the days those participants missed work due to a respiratory infection in comparison to their control group. However, Goodall et al. [<xref rid="CR14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] noted a significant decrease in secondary outcomes, including lab confirmed viral illness and mean viral load. Notably, van Helmond et al. [<xref rid="CR18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] demonstrated that supplementing their participants with 5000 IU of vitamin D daily for nine months helped to reduce incidence of influenza-like illness, with five patients experiencing adverse effects.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9" disp-level="2"><title>Immunology</title><p id="Par19">Three studies focused on the effects of prophylactic vitamin D on different aspects of the immune system. Barker et al. [<xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] utilized vitamin D in the prevention of IL-5 decline and noted both the 200 IU and 4000 IU daily doses for 28 days prevented a decrease in IL-5 levels. Contrarily, Chandler et al. [<xref rid="CR20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] supplemented their participants with 1000 IU, 2000 IU, and 4000 IU of vitamin D daily for three months reported that there were no statistically significant changes in levels of other interleukins and inflammatory markers, such as IL-6, IL-10, CRP, and soluble TNF-alpha receptor type 2 (sTNF-R2). Bock et al. [<xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] determined that short-term monthly dosage of 140,000 IU of vitamin D for three months resulted in a significantly increased regulatory T-cell (T-Reg) frequency, and suggested that it may be a useful therapeutic tool for certain autoimmune diseases.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10" disp-level="2"><title>Musculoskeletal</title><p id="Par20">The effect of vitamin D supplementation on the musculoskeletal system was observed in two studies. Mielgo-Ayuso et al. [<xref rid="CR22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] reported 3000 IU vitamin D supplementation for eight weeks, the decline in levels of hemoglobin and hematocrit were prevented. There were no notable improvements in the testosterone and cortisol levels compared to the control, providing evidence that supplementation did not enhance muscle recovery. Knutsen et al. [<xref rid="CR23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] reported no significant effect on the degree, location, and frequency of muscle pain.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11" disp-level="2"><title>Gynecology</title><p id="Par21">Breast cancer prophylaxis in conjunction with vitamin D supplementation was conducted by Brisson et al. [<xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] Specifically, doses ranging from 1000 to 3000 IU daily for one-year to determine any breast density reduction (previously correlated with a reduced risk of breast cancer). The 3000 IU daily dose of vitamin D resulted in less reduction in breast density in comparison to the placebo; however, the difference was not statistically significant.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12" disp-level="2"><title>Endocrinology</title><p id="Par22">Vitamin D supplementation was utilized for autoimmune thyroid disease prophylaxis by Knutsen et al. [<xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] They tested the effect of a 400 IU or 1000 IU daily dose for 16 weeks on thyroid immunity. In comparison to the placebo, they found no prophylactic benefits for autoimmune thyroid disease as determined by no significant changes in levels of thyroid peroxidase antibody (TPOAb), free thyroxine (FT4), or thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH).</p></sec><sec id="Sec13" disp-level="2"><title>Neurology</title><p id="Par23">In a study by Pettersen et al. [<xref rid="CR26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], the effects of vitamin D supplementation on the prevention of cognitive decline were observed. The control group received 400 IU while the intervention group with 4000 IU daily dose of vitamin D for 18-weeks, and noted the intervention group had significantly improved non-verbal memory (visuospatial) memory. There were no significant differences between the two groups in other cognitive domains, such as verbal memory. Interestingly, an improvement in mood was observed in the high-dose group by 2.8 points, as assessed by the Beck Depression Inventory.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14" disp-level="1"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par24">Although vitamin D has known therapeutic effects on bone health, there is a gap in knowledge about whether vitamin D supplementation can prevent diseases of the extraskeletal system. This systematic review analyzes 18 RCTs with 4,415 patients to further assess vitamin D prophylaxis in healthy adults from a multi-organ standpoint. Of the five cardiology-related articles included, 80% showed no preventative effect on cardiovascular biomarker risk, such as blood pressure, fasting lipids, and HbA1c, except for one study that found a significant decrease in total cholesterol. Vitamin D prophylaxis for URTI yielded mixed results, whereby 60% of the respiratory articles demonstrated no preventative effect with supplementation and 40% showed a significant decline in URTI incidence. While vitamin D had no significant impact on autoimmune thyroid disease and breast cancer prevention, there are promising benefits in terms of preventing immune, musculoskeletal, and neurological disease. Multiple studies found positive immune responses in 67% of the immune-related RCTs, improvement in hematological and iron metabolism profiles in 50% of musculoskeletal studies, and significant enhancement on memory and nonverbal tasks in one neurological study. Overall, this review found that vitamin D supplementation generally does not provide significant extraskeletal benefits among the healthier adult population and thus supports a personalized approach to physician prescription practices of vitamin D.</p><sec id="Sec15" disp-level="2"><title>Cardiovascular</title><p id="Par25">Interest in vitamin D’s potential association with cardio-metabolic health is on the rise, considering its relationship with cardio-metabolic markers like HbA1c, serum lipids, blood pressure, and several other factors. Overall, vitamin D supplementation has yet to demonstrate significant effects on a large-scale setting [<xref rid="CR27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Concerning glycemic control, there are well-described mechanisms by which vitamin D and glucose metabolism are linked; however, data from randomized controlled trials are relatively rare and mainly in patients with type 2 diabetes or other underlying disease, overweight, insulin resistant, or vitamin D deficient, notably discussed in the D2d study by Bess Dawson-Hughes et al. [<xref rid="CR51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] In this review, multiple studies have shown conflicting results when monitoring vitamin D’s effect on HbA1C, insulin resistance, and other diabetic markers (e.g. fructosamine). Previous studies have demonstrated positive effects through lowered LDL and increased HDL with the use of vitamin D3 supplementation [<xref rid="CR28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Jastrzebski et al. [<xref rid="CR12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] studied athletes who demonstrated a significant decrease in total cholesterol and HDL (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.02 and <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01, respectively), but non-significant decrease in LDL (<italic>p</italic> = 0.79) at 5000 IU supplementation [<xref rid="CR29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Regular exercise has been associated with an improved lipid profile, where athletes tend to demonstrate lower total and LDL cholesterol and higher HDL concentration compared to non-athletes [<xref rid="CR30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="CR31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. However, Madar et al. [<xref rid="CR9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] note that vitamin D supplementation may not induce clear effects on BMI or HbA1c in healthy individuals. Forouhi et al. [<xref rid="CR13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] found minor effects on some lipid levels with mixed evidence for effects of vitamin D supplementation [<xref rid="CR32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="CR33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. For blood pressure, both Scragg et al. [<xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] and Muldowney et al. [<xref rid="CR10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], indicate that long-term high or low dose vitamin D supplementation does not significantly lower blood pressure even at up to 100,000 IU supplementation. Forouhi et al. [<xref rid="CR12" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] reported a reduction in arterial stiffness, suggesting potential favorable effects on vascular health. However, the mechanisms behind this decline remain unclear and warrant further investigation. Thus, while there is significant interest in understanding the relationship between vitamin D and cardio-metabolic health, the current evidence from various studies yields mixed and inconclusive results. Notably, past trials with participants with high baseline levels of 25-hydroxyvitamin D were limited in meaningful effects. However, Wang et al. [<xref rid="CR52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>] found a nonlinear inverse relation in individuals with concentration below 20ng/mL and suggests focusing on populations with vitamin D deficiency to better evaluate benefits. Achieving and maintaining adequate serum 25(OH)D levels through supplementation may be associated with improved health outcomes [<xref rid="CR53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, <xref rid="CR54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec16" disp-level="2"><title>Respiratory</title><p id="Par26">Five studies that examined the use of vitamin D supplementation to prevent respiratory illness showed mixed results. Four of the five respiratory-related articles demonstrated no significant differences to protection against URIs when given vitamin D supplementation at varying doses [<xref rid="CR14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>–<xref rid="CR16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. In particular, Li-Ng et al. [<xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], participants of 25(OH)D demonstrated levels &gt; 20 ng/mL and supplementation did not affect URTIs. However, Goodall et al. [<xref rid="CR14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] had significant decrease in viral illnesses and mean viral loads, which may suggest protective effects. While van Helmond et al. [<xref rid="CR18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] demonstrated statistically significant reduction in respiratory infection, which was paralleled by Jolliffe et al. [<xref rid="CR34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], who found that treatment with vitamin D significantly lowered acute respiratory infection incidence with an odds ratio of 0.92 (<italic>p</italic> = 0.018). The protective effects were especially prominent with daily dose regimens as opposed to single-dose or intermittent treatments. Throughout this research, significant improvements were reported after administering 5000 IU daily and 10,000 IU weekly. These findings suggest that a regimen with higher, more frequent doses may be more effective as vitamin D prophylaxis for respiratory illnesses and may be affected to a patient’s baseline 25(OH)D serum levels, but further investigation is required [<xref rid="CR55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec17" disp-level="2"><title>Immunology</title><p id="Par27">Vitamin D receptors are found on T-cells, mast cells and eosinophils, which are influenced by inflammatory cytokines, including IL-5 [<xref rid="CR35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>–<xref rid="CR38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. GATA binding protein 3 (GATA-3) transcription factor promotes IL-5 gene expression [<xref rid="CR39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="CR40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Previous research have suggested suggest prophylactic effects on the immune system with vitamin D supplementation. Barker et al. [<xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] did not demonstrate an increase in IL-5 gene expression with 4000 IU supplementation and thought to be related to detecting errors within blood sampling protocols. Chandler et al. [<xref rid="CR20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] and Muldowney et al. [<xref rid="CR10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] found no significant impact on multiple proinflammatory markers with a range of 1000 to 4000 IU of vitamin D supplementation. However, Bock et al. [<xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] determined that 140,000 IU vitamin D supplementation over three months resulted in a significantly increased Tregs frequency (<italic>p</italic> ≤ 0.001), suggesting vitamin D3 may be a useful therapeutic agent in autoimmune diseases exerting immune modulatory effects involving stimulatory actions on Tregs; however, Bock et al. [<xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] reported only one-third of the subjects had incidentally been found to be vitamin D deficient (&lt; 20 ng/mL). These conflicting results serve as a rationale for future trials with large populations and more stringent testing environments.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18" disp-level="2"><title>Musculoskeletal</title><p id="Par28">One study measuring musculoskeletal pain and headaches observed that daily vitamin D supplementation of 400 or 1000 IU did not have a significant effect on patients [<xref rid="CR23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], echoing similar trials. Other RCTs showed no significant pain reduction with vitamin D for chronic lower back pain [<xref rid="CR41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] and knee pain in osteoarthritis patients [<xref rid="CR42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="CR43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], while a study in fibromyalgia patients noted reduced pain, however, with limited power [<xref rid="CR44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Contrarily, a study in male athletes revealed positive effects on hemoglobin (<italic>p =</italic> 0.009), hematocrit (<italic>p =</italic> 0.019), and transferrin (<italic>p =</italic> 0.007), potentially enhancing oxygen transport efficiency [<xref rid="CR22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], supported by improved musculoskeletal performance in another study [<xref rid="CR45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], suggesting that higher dosages may offer more pronounced benefits regardless of treatment duration. These results indicate that vitamin D may induce improvement primarily in hematological values rather than musculoskeletal pain and recovery in healthy adults.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19" disp-level="2"><title>Gynecology</title><p id="Par29">Vitamin D’s association with breast cancer prevention and risk continues to be under investigation. Recent literature suggests that vitamin D signaling may have a protective effect against breast cancer risk, with an inverse association between vitamin D and breast cancer risk, especially for BRCA1 gene mutation carriers [<xref rid="CR46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="CR47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Brisson et al’s [<xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] study did not demonstrate a significant decrease in breast density with medium to high doses of vitamin D supplementation for one-year. Rather, the 3000 IU dose showed less reduction in breast density. The serum 25(OH)D varied between intervention arms, and some &lt; 20 ng/mol. Outside of our inclusion criteria, McDonnell et al. contradicted these findings when holding higher serum 25(OH)D concentrations of ≥ 40 ng/mL, which were associated with a significant reduction in cancer risk compared to lower levels [<xref rid="CR56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Future research should explore the link between plasma vitamin D levels, calcium level changes, and breast cancer risk.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20" disp-level="2"><title>Endocrine</title><p id="Par30">Vitamin D deficiency has been previously linked to autoimmune thyroid disease such as Hashimoto’s thyroiditis and Grave’s disease [<xref rid="CR48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Yet, it is unclear whether supplementation of vitamin D can reduce thyroid autoantibody levels. One RCT tested this idea and showed that vitamin D supplementation did not have a significant effect on TPOAb, TSH, or free fraction of thyroxine levels in healthy adult patients [<xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. These findings differ from another trial that conveyed a greater decline in TPOAb in a group of patients treated with both vitamin D and calcium compared to only calcium supplements (<italic>p =</italic> 0.028) [<xref rid="CR49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. This difference was particularly significant among those with baseline serum TSH of ≤ 10 mIU/L, suggesting that vitamin D supplementation may optimally benefit patients with newly diagnosed autoimmune thyroid disease. However, the advantages of supplementation were not replicated in Knutsen et al.’s [<xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] RCT included in this study. Because there are limited studies using vitamin D as therapeutic doses, more studies with healthy adult patients are necessary to identify the health effects of vitamin D on preventing thyroid autoimmunity.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21" disp-level="2"><title>Neurology</title><p id="Par31">Vitamin D supplementation may take over 16 weeks to show certain effects [<xref rid="CR50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Petterson et al. [<xref rid="CR26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] demonstrate 3000 IU vitamin D supplementation appears to improve cognition, especially nonverbal memory via Pattern Recognition Memory tasks and Paired Associates Learning Tasks (<italic>p =</italic> 0.043 and <italic>p =</italic> 0.044, respectively). This finding aligns with recent studies linking 25(OH)D levels and nonverbal memory, possibly due to the increased cognitive demands of visual memory [<xref rid="CR26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. This study also speculates that nonverbal, but not verbal memory, require increased cognitive demands and reliance on executive functioning processes of visual memory. Thus, Petterson et al. [<xref rid="CR26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] suggest that higher levels of vitamin D supplementation may be more beneficial.</p></sec><sec id="Sec29" disp-level="2"><title>Limitations and future studies</title><p id="Par32">Our findings can be considered in light of the following limitations. Included studies had inconsistent doses of vitamin D supplementation, differing follow up periods, unique outcomes, do not consider intake from diet and sun exposure, and some had limited sample sizes (&lt; 500 participants), making a meta-analysis infeasible. In addition, there was also an inconsistency in duration between interventions from days-to-weeks-to-years, which introduced confounding factors between acute versus chronic use of supplementation. Recognition of these limitations can help future studies address these constraints to progress for a more comprehensive and articulate connection between vitamin D supplementation and [potential] health consequences. Future studies should consider studies with larger sample sizes of healthy adults testing for benefits and adverse effects of prophylactic vitamin D use, and adjustable vitamin D supplementation based on interval serum 25(OH)D concentrations to achieve target 25(OH)D levels [<xref rid="CR57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec23" disp-level="1"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par33">In summary, this systematic review evaluated 18 RCTs and 4,415 patients to explore prophylactic vitamin D supplementation in the healthy adult population. Out of the 18 studies, 11 demonstrated a positive response in at least one marker with supplementation, whereas seven found no significant effects. Overall, vitamin D prophylaxis generally was not found to have statistically significant benefits when considering seven extra-skeletal organ systems. Few adverse events (e.g. nausea, abdominal pain) were noted; however, no severe complications (e.g. hypercalcemia) or exacerbation of disease were observed. While certain studies, particularly the immune and neurological RCTs, hint at potential benefits, the extensive limitation of sample size, variable doses, inconsistent duration, and unaccounted for dietary or solar sources highlight the need for more rigorous research to establish a clearer understanding of the health consequences of vitamin D supplementation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec24" disp-level="1"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p>
<supplementary-material id="MOESM1" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="40795_2025_1107_MOESM1_ESM.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document"><?cloudpmc-path 85ab/12226867/ff4241fc29fc/40795_2025_1107_MOESM1_ESM.docx?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 200349?><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</sec><sec id="ack1" sec-type="ack" disp-level="1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="glossary1" sec-type="glossary" disp-level="1"><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>Vit D3</term><def><p id="Par37">Vitamin D3</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UVB</term><def><p id="Par38">Ultraviolet B</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PTH</term><def><p id="Par39">Parathyroid hormone</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Ca</term><def><p id="Par40">Calcium</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>25(OH)D</term><def><p id="Par41">25–Hydroxyvitamin D</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>1,25(OH)2D</term><def><p id="Par42">1,25–Dihydroxyvitamin D</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BMD</term><def><p id="Par43">Bone mineral density</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RCT</term><def><p id="Par44">Randomized controlled trial</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BMI</term><def><p id="Par45">Body mass index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CI</term><def><p id="Par46">Confidence interval</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SD</term><def><p id="Par47">Standard deviation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SE</term><def><p id="Par48">Standard error</p></def></def-item></def-list></sec><sec id="notes1" disp-level="1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>CG (co-author) - primary intellectual contribution of the project, set timelines and ensure all team members have adequate support to meet the deadlines, contribute to all aspects of data collection and will draft the discussion, assist in the results, and contributed to manuscript development. SL (co-author) - set timelines and ensure all team members have adequate support to meet the deadlines, contribute to all aspects of data collection and will draft the discussion, assist in the results, interpretation of data, and contributed to manuscript development. HZ - heavily contributed to acquisition and analysis, drafted results section.HP - contributed to acquisition and analysis, drafted introduction, assisted in results section drafts.BM - design of the work with methods, contributed to acquisition and analysis, substantively revised drafts. KA - contributed to acquisition and analysis, drafted methods section, assisted in results section drafts. MH - contributed to acquisition and analysis, substantively revised drafts, and contributed to references formatting and in-text citations.KT - contributed to acquisition and analysis; and revised drafts. MS - design of the work and provided direction towards purpose; substantively revised drafts. ZI - design of the work and provided direction towards purpose; substantively revised drafts. CL - provided inspiration to this project based on clinical experience, design of the work, and substantively revised drafts. DP - design of the work and provided direction towards purpose; substantively revised drafts; approved the submitted version; agreed both to be personally accountable for the author’s own contributions and to ensure that questions related to the accuracy or integrity of any part of the work, even ones in which the author was not personally involved, are appropriately investigated, resolved, and the resolution documented in the literature.</p></sec><sec id="notes2" disp-level="1"><title>Funding</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="notes3" disp-level="1"><title>Data availability</title><p>No datasets were generated or analysed during the current study.</p></sec><sec id="notes4" disp-level="1"><title>Declarations</title><sec id="FPar1" disp-level="2"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par34">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2" disp-level="2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par35">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3" disp-level="2"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par36">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></sec><sec id="fn-group1" sec-type="fn-group" disp-level="1"><title>Footnotes</title><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><p>Caroline Goswami and Sherrice Law share co-first authorship.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="Bib1" sec-type="ref-list" disp-level="1"><title>References</title><sec id="Bib1_sec2" disp-level="2"><ref-list><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Tripkovic L, Helen L, Kathryn H, et al. Comparison of vitamin D2 and vitamin D3 supplementation in raising serum 25-hydroxyvitamin D status: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Am J Clin Nutr. June 2012;95(6):1357-64.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3945/ajcn.111.031070"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC3349454"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="22552031"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bouillon R, Manousaki D, Rosen C. J, Trajanoska K, Rivadeneira F, &amp; Richards J. B. The health effects of Vitamin D3 supplementation: Evidence from human studies. Nature Reviews Endocrinology. 2022;18(2):96–110.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41574-021-00593-z"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC8609267"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34815552"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Marcinowska-Suchowierska E, Kupisz-Urbanska M, Łukaszkiewicz J, Płudowski P, Jones G. Vitamin D3 toxicity–A clinical Perspective. Frontiers in Endocrinology. 2018; 9.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3389/fendo.2018.00550"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC6158375"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="30294301"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zmijewski. MA Vitamin D3 and human health. Int J Mol Sci. 2019;20(1), 145.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/ijms20010145"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC6337085"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="30609781"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bouillon R. Comparative analysis of nutritional guidelines for vitamin D. Nature Reviews Endocrinology. 2017;13:466–479.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/nrendo.2017.31"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="28387318"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Kane S. P. Cholecalciferol [Internet]. Rockville, MD: ClinCalc. 2022 [updated 2024 January 1; cited 2024 January 8]. Available from: https://clincalc.com/DrugStats/Drugs/Cholecalciferol.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Covidence systematic review software, Veritas Health Innovation, Melbourne, Australia. Available at www.covidence.org.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Higgins J P T, Altman D G, GÃ¸tzsche P C, JÃ¼ni P, Moher D, Oxman A D et al. The Cochrane Collaboration’s tool for assessing risk of bias in randomised trials BMJ. 2011;343:d5928. doi:10.1136/bmj.d5928</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1136/bmj.d5928"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC3196245"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="22008217"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Madar A. A, Knutsen K. V, Stene L. C, Brekke M, Meyer H. E, &amp; Lagerløv P. Effect of vitamin D3 supplementation on glycated hemoglobin (HbA1c), fructosamine, serum lipids, and body mass index: a randomized, double-blinded, placebo-controlled trial among healthy immigrants living in Norway. BMJ Open Diabetes Research and Care. 2014;2(1):e000026.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1136/bmjdrc-2014-000026"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC4212570"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="25452867"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Muldowney S, Lucey A. J, Hill T. R, Seamans K. M, Taylor N, Wallace J. M,… &amp; Kiely M. Incremental cholecalciferol supplementation up to 15 ∝g/d throughout winter at 51–55 N has no effect on biomarkers of cardiovascular risk in healthy young and older adults. The Journal of nutrition. 2012;142(8):1519–1525.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3945/jn.111.154005"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="22739371"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Scragg R, Slow S, Stewart A. W, Jennings L. C, Chambers S. T, Priest P. C,… &amp; Murdoch D. R. Long-term high-dose vitamin D3 supplementation and blood pressure in healthy adults: a randomized controlled trial. Hypertension. 2014;64(4):725–730.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.114.03466"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="24980662"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Jastrzebski Z, Kortas J, Kaczor K, &amp; Antosiewicz J. Vitamin D supplementation causes a decrease in blood cholesterol in professional rowers. Journal of nutritional science and vitaminology. 2016;62(2):88–92.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3177/jnsv.62.88"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="27264092"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Forouhi N. G, Menon R. K, Sharp S. J, Mannan N, Timms P. M, Martineau A. R,… &amp; Hitman G. A. Effects of vitamin D2 or D3 supplementation on glycaemic control and cardiometabolic risk among people at risk of type 2 diabetes: results of a randomized double-blind placebo‐controlled trial. Diabetes, Obesity and Metabolism. 2016;18(4):392–400.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/dom.12625"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC4950066"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="26700109"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Goodall E. C, Granados A. C, Luinstra K, Pullenayegum E, Coleman B. L, Loeb M, &amp; Smieja M. Vitamin D3and gargling for the prevention of upper respiratory tract infections: A randomized controlled trial. BMC infectious diseases. 2014;14(1):1–8.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1186/1471-2334-14-273"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC4041358"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="24885201"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Li-Ng M, Aloia J. F, Pollack S, Cunha B. A, Mikhail M, Yeh J, &amp; Berbari N. A randomized controlled trial of vitamin D3 supplementation for the prevention of symptomatic upper respiratory tract infections. Epidemiology &amp; Infection. 2009;137(10):1396–1404.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1017/S0950268809002404"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="19296870"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Murdoch D. R, Slow S, Chambers S. T, Jennings L. C, Stewart A. W, Priest P. C,… &amp; Scragg R. Effect of vitamin D3 supplementation on upper respiratory tract infections in healthy adults: the VIDARIS randomized controlled trial. Jama. 2012;308(13):1333–1339.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1001/jama.2012.12505"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="23032549"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Laaksi I, Ruohola J. P, Mattila V, Auvinen A, Ylikomi T, &amp; Pihlajamäki H. Vitamin D supplementation for the prevention of acute respiratory tract infection: a randomized, double-blinded trial among young Finnish men. The Journal of infectious diseases. 2010;202(5):809–814.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1086/654881"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="20632889"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">van Helmond N, Brobyn T. L, LaRiccia P. J, Cafaro T, Hunter K, Roy S,… &amp; Chung M. K. Vitamin D3 Supplementation at 5000 IU Daily for the Prevention of Influenza-like Illness in Healthcare Workers: A Pragmatic Randomized Clinical Trial. Nutrients. 2022;15(1):180.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/nu15010180"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9823308"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36615837"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Barker T, Martins T. B, Hill H. R, Kjeldsberg C. R, Henriksen V. T, Dixon B. M,… &amp; Weaver L. K. Different doses of supplemental vitamin D maintain interleukin-5 without altering skeletal muscle strength: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study in vitamin D sufficient adults. Nutrition &amp; metabolism. 2012;9(1):1–12.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1186/1743-7075-9-16"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC3325895"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="22405472"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Chandler P. D, Scott J. B, Drake B. F, Ng K, Manson J. E, Rifai N,… &amp; Fuchs C. S. Impact of vitamin D supplementation on inflammatory markers in African Americans: results of a four-arm, randomized, placebo-controlled trial. Cancer prevention research. 2014;7(2):218–225.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1158/1940-6207.CAPR-13-0338-T"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC4038929"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="24327720"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bock G, Prietl B, Mader J. K, Höller E, Wolf M, Pilz S,… &amp; Pieber T. R. The effect of vitamin D supplementation on peripheral regulatory T cells and β cell function in healthy humans: a randomized controlled trial. Diabetes/metabolism research and reviews. 2011;27(8):942–945.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1002/dmrr.1276"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="22069289"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Mielgo-Ayuso J, Calleja-González J, Urdampilleta A, León-Guereño P, Córdova A, Caballero-García A, &amp; Fernandez-Lázaro D. Effects of vitamin D supplementation on hae. 2018.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/nu10121968"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC6315465"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="30545134"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Knutsen K. V, Madar A. A, Brekke M, Meyer H. E, Natvig B, Mdala I, &amp; Lagerløv P. Effect of vitamin D on musculoskeletal pain and headache: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial among adult ethnic minorities in Norway. Pain<sup>®</sup>. 2014;155(12):2591–2598.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.pain.2014.09.024"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="25261164"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Brisson J, Bérubé S, Diorio C, Mâsse B, Lemieux J, Duchesne T,… &amp; Chiquette J. A randomized double-blind placebo-controlled trial of the effect of vitamin D3 supplementation on breast density in premenopausal women. Cancer Epidemiology, Biomarkers &amp; Prevention. 2017;26(8):1233–1241.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-17-0249"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="28515107"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Knutsen K. V, Madar A. A, Brekke M, Meyer H. E, Eggemoen Å. R, Mdala I, &amp; Lagerløv P. Effect of vitamin D on thyroid autoimmunity: a randomized, double-blind, controlled trial among ethnic minorities. Journal of the Endocrine Society. 2017;1(5):470–479.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1210/js.2017-00037"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC5686597"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="29264502"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Pettersen, J. A. Does high dose vitamin D supplementation enhance cognition? A randomized trial in healthy adults. Experimental gerontology. 2017;90;90–97.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.exger.2017.01.019"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="28167237"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">George PS, Pearson ER, Witham MD. Effect of vitamin D supplementation on glycaemic control and insulin resistance: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Diabet Med. 2012;29:e142–50.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/j.1464-5491.2012.03672.x"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="22486204"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Soares MJ, Chan She Ping-Delfos W, Ghanbari MH. Calcium and vitamin D for obesity: a review of randomized controlled trials. Eur J Clin Nutr. 2011;65:994–1004.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/ejcn.2011.106"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="21731038"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Auwerx J, Bouillon R, Kesteloot H. Relation between 25-hydroxyvitamin D3, apolipoprotein A-I, and high density lipoprotein cholesterol. Arterioscler Thromb. 1992;12:671–674.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1161/01.atv.12.6.671"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="1350464"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zorba E, Cengiz T, Karacabey K. Exercise train- ing improves body composition, blood lipid profile and serum insulin levels in obese children. J Sports Med Phys Fitness. 2011;51:664–669.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="22212270"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zanella AM, Nakazone MA, Pinhel MA, Souza DR. Lipid profile, apolipoprotein A-I and oxidative stress in professional footballers, sedentary individuals, and their relatives. Arq Bras Endocrinol Metabol. 2011;55:121–126.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1590/S0004-27302011000200004"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="21584429"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sollid ST, Hutchinson MY, Fuskevag OM et al. No effect of high-dose vitamin D supplementation on glycemic status or cardiovascular risk factors in subjects with prediabetes. Diabetes Care. 2014;37:2123–2131.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.2337/dc14-0218"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="24947792"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Schnatz PF, Jiang X, Vila-Wright S et al. Calcium/vitamin D supplementation, serum 25-hydroxyvitamin D concentrations, and cholesterol profiles in the Women’s Health Initiative calcium/vitamin D randomized trial. Menopause. 2014;21: 823–833.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1097/GME.0000000000000188"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC5234488"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="24594863"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Jolliffe D. A, Camargo C. A, Sluyter J, Aglipay M, Aloia J. F, Ganmaa D, Bergman P, Bischoff-Ferrari H. A, Borzutzky A, Damsgaard C. T, Dubnov‐Raz G, Esposito S, Gilham C, Ginde A. A, Golan‐Tripto I, Goodall E. C, Grant C, Bandyopadhyay D, Hibbs A. M, Martineau A. R. Vitamin D supplementation to prevent acute respiratory infections: a systematic review and meta-analysis of aggregate data from randomised controlled trials. The Lancet Diabetes &amp; Endocrinology. 2021;9(5):276–292. 10.1016/s2213-8587(21)00051-6</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/S2213-8587(21)00051-6"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33798465"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Arnson Y, Itzhaky D, Mosseri M, Barak V, Tzur B, Agmon-Levin N, &amp; Amital H. Vitamin D inflammatory cytokines and coronary events: a comprehensive review. Clinical reviews in allergy &amp; immunology. 2013;45:236–247.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s12016-013-8356-0"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="23314982"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Henry, E. K., Inclan-Rico, J. M., &amp; Siracusa, M. C. Type 2 cytokine responses: regulating immunity to helminth parasites and allergic inflammation. Current pharmacology reports. (2017);3:346–359.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s40495-017-0114-1"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC5794032"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="29399438"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Shimbara A, Christodoulopoulos P, Soussi-Gounni A, Olivenstein R, Nakamura Y, Levitt RC, et al. IL-9 and its receptor in allergic and nonallergic lung disease: increased expression in asthma. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2000;105:108–115.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/s0091-6749(00)90185-4"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="10629460"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Verheyen J, Bonig H, Kim YM, Banning U, Mauz-Korholz C, Kramm C, et al. Regulation of interleukin-2 induced interleukin-5 and interleukin-13 production in human peripheral blood mononuclear cells. Scand J Immunol. 2000;51:45–53.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1046/j.1365-3083.2000.00643.x"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="10632975"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Yusupov E, Li-Ng M, Pollack S, Yeh JK, Mikhail M. Aloia JF: Vitamin d and serum cytokines in a randomized clinical trial. Int J Endocrinol. 2010;2010:1–7.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1155/2010/305054"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC2943086"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="20871847"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lamm ME: Interaction of antigens and antibodies at mucosal surfaces. Annu Rev Microbiol. 1997;51:311–340.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1146/annurev.micro.51.1.311"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="9343353"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sandoughi M, Zakeri Z, Mirhosainee Z, Mohammadi M, &amp; Shahbakhsh S. The effect of vitamin D on nonspecific low back pain. International Journal of Rheumatic Diseases. 2013:18(8):854–858. 10.1111/1756-185x.12172</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/1756-185X.12172"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="24119149"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sanghi D, Mishra A, Sharma A, Singh A, Natu S, Agarwal S, &amp; Srivastava R. N. Does vitamin D improve osteoarthritis of the knee: a randomized controlled pilot trial. Clinical Orthopaedics and Related Research. 2013;471(11):3556–3562. 10.1007/s11999-013-3201-6</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s11999-013-3201-6"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC3792285"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="23904246"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">McAlindon T. E, LaValley M. P, Schneider E, Nuite M, Lee J. Y, Price L. L, Lo G. H, &amp; Dawson-Hughes B. Effect of vitamin D supplementation on progression of knee pain and cartilage volume loss in patients with symptomatic osteoarthritis. JAMA. 2013;309(2):155. 10.1001/jama.2012.164487</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1001/jama.2012.164487"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC3984919"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="23299607"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wepner F, Scheuer R, Schuetz-Wieser B, Machácek P, Pieler-Bruha E, Cross H. S, Hahne J, &amp; Fortin M. Effects of vitamin D on patients with fibromyalgia syndrome: A randomized placebo-controlled trial. PAIN. 2014;155(2):261–268. 10.1016/j.pain.2013.10.002</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.pain.2013.10.002"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="24438771"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Carswell A, Oliver S. J, Wentz L. M, Kashi D, Roberts R, Tang J, Izard R, Jackson S, Allan D, Rhodes L. E, Fraser W. D, Greeves J. P, &amp; Walsh N. P. Influence of vitamin D supplementation by sunlight or oral D3 on exercise performance. Medicine and Science in Sports and Exercise. 2018;50(12):2555–2564. 10.1249/mss.0000000000001721</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1249/MSS.0000000000001721"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC6282681"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="30048414"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Patel S. R, Patel K. D, Patel J. B, Patel P. S, &amp; Shah F. D. Association of vitamin D receptor gene polymorphisms with breast cancer risk. Journal of Cancer Research and Therapeutics. 2023.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.4103/jcrt.jcrt_60_22"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38384038"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Guyonnet E, Kim S. J, Pullella K, Zhang C. X, McCuaig J. M, Armel S,… &amp; Kotsopoulos J. Vitamin D and Calcium Supplement Use and High-Risk Breast Cancer: A Case–Control Study among BRCA1 and BRCA2 Mutation Carriers. Cancers. 2023;15(10):2790.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/cancers15102790"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC10216325"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37345127"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wang J, Lv S, Guo C, Gao C, He J, Zhong H, &amp; Xu Y. Meta-analysis of the association between vitamin D and autoimmune thyroid disease. Nutrients. 2015;7(4):2485–2498. 10.3390/nu7042485</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/nu7042485"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC4425156"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="25854833"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Chaudhary S, Dutta D, Kumar M, Saha S, Mondal S. A, Kumar A, &amp; Mukhopadhyay S. Vitamin D supplementation reduces thyroid peroxidase antibody levels in patients with autoimmune thyroid disease: An open-labeled randomized controlled trial. Indian Journal of Endocrinology and Metabolism. 2016b;20(3):391. 10.4103/2230-8210.179997</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.4103/2230-8210.179997"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC4855971"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="27186560"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Annweiler C, &amp; Beauchet O. Vitamin D-mentia: randomized clinical trials should be the next step. Neuroepidemiology. 2011;37(3–4):249–258.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1159/000334177"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="22156654"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Dawson-Hughes B, Staten M. A, Knowler W. C, Nelson J, Vickery E. M, LeBlanc E. S, Neff L. M, Park J, Pittas A. G. &amp; D2d research group. Intratrial exposure to vitamin D and new-onset diabetes among adults with prediabetes: A secondary analysis from the Vitamin D and Type 2 Diabetes (D2d) study. Diabetes Care. 2020;43(12):2916–2922. 10.2337/dc20-1765</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.2337/dc20-1765"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7770274"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33020052"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wang L, Song Y, Manson J. E, Pilz S, März W, Michaëlsson K, Lundqvist A, Jassal S. K, Barrett-Connor E, Zhang C, Eaton C. B, May H. T, Anderson J. L, &amp; Sesso H. D. Circulating 25-hydroxy-vitamin D and risk of cardiovascular disease: A meta-analysis of prospective studies. Circulation: Cardiovascular Quality and Outcomes. 2012;5(6):819–829. 10.1161/CIRCOUTCOMES.112.967604</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1161/CIRCOUTCOMES.112.967604"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC3510675"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="23149428"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Acharya P, Dalia T, Ranka S, Sethi P, Oni O. A, Safarova M. S, Parashara D, Gupta K, &amp; Barua R. S. The effects of vitamin D supplementation and 25-hydroxyvitamin D levels on the risk of myocardial infarction and mortality. Journal of the Endocrine Society. 2021;5(10):bvab124. 10.1210/jendso/bvab124</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1210/jendso/bvab124"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC8358990"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34396023"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Mirhosseini N, Vatanparast H, &amp; Kimball S. M. The association between serum 25(OH)D status and blood pressure in participants of a community-based program taking vitamin D supplements. Nutrients. 2017;9(11):1244. 10.3390/nu911124</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/nu9111244"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC5707716"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="29135923"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Oristrell J, Oliva J. C, Casado E, Subirana I, Domínguez D, Toloba A, Balado A, &amp; Grau M. Vitamin D supplementation and COVID-19 risk: A population-based cohort study. Journal of Endocrinological Investigation. 2022:45(1), 167–179. 10.1007/s40618-021-01639-9</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s40618-021-01639-9"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC8285728"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34273098"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">McDonnell S. L, Baggerly K. A, Baggerly C. A, Aliano J. L, French C. B, Baggerly L. L, Ebeling M. D, Rittenberg C. S, Goodier, C. G., Mateus Niño, J. F., Wineland, R. J., Newman, R. B., Hollis, B. W., &amp; Wagner, C. L. Maternal 25(OH)D concentrations ≥ 40 ng/mL associated with 60% lower preterm birth risk among general obstetrical patients at an urban medical center. PLoS ONE. 2017;12(7):e0180483. 10.1371/journal.pone.0180483</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pone.0180483"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC5524288"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="28738090"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Grant W. B, Boucher B. J, Al Anouti F, &amp; Pilz S. Comparing the evidence from observational studies and randomized controlled trials for nonskeletal health effects of vitamin D. Nutrients. 2022;14(18):3811. 10.3390/nu14183811</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/nu14183811"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9501276"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36145186"/></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></sec></sec><sec id="_ad93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="associated-data" disp-level="1"><title>Associated Data</title><sec id="_adsm93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="supplementary-materials" disp-level="2"><title>Supplementary Materials</title><supplementary-material id="db_ds_supplementary-material1_reqid_" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="40795_2025_1107_MOESM1_ESM.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document"><?cloudpmc-path 85ab/12226867/ff4241fc29fc/40795_2025_1107_MOESM1_ESM.docx?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 200349?><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="_adda93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="data-availability-statement" disp-level="2"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>No datasets were generated or analysed during the current study.</p></sec></sec></body></article>