<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">937</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">cambridgeopen</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The British Journal of Nutrition</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title>Br J Nutr</abbrev-journal-title></journal-title-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11646675</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11646675</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11646675</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39494607</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0007114524002757</article-id><title-group><article-title>Improved gastrointestinal tolerance and iron status via probiotic use in iron deficiency anaemia patients initiating oral iron replacement: a randomised controlled trial</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="author"><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Koker</surname><given-names initials="G">Gokhan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahinturk</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yasin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="author-notes">✉</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Ozcelik Koker</surname><given-names initials="G">Gulhan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Coskuner</surname><given-names initials="MA">Muhammed Ali</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Eren Durmus</surname><given-names initials="M">Merve</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Catli</surname><given-names initials="MM">Mehmet Mutlu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Cekin</surname><given-names initials="AH">Ayhan Hilmi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="a1"><label>1</label>Department of Internal Medicine, University of Health Sciences Antalya Training and Research Hospital, Antalya, Turkey</aff><aff id="a2"><label>2</label>Department of Gastroenterology, University of Health Sciences Antalya Training and Research Hospital, 07100 Muratpaşa, Antalya, Turkey</aff><author-notes><fn id="cor1"><label>✉</label><p><bold>Corresponding author:</bold> Yasin Sahinturk; Email: <email>drsahinturk@yahoo.com</email></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date><day>4</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>132</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1308</fpage><page-range>1308–1316</page-range><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><license><license-p>This is an Open Access article, distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution licence (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ext-link-type="uri">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted re-use, distribution and reproduction, provided the original article is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="S0007114524002757a.pdf" content-type="pmc-pdf"><?cloudpmc-path fd4d/11646675/41a258e5d443/S0007114524002757a.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 311326?></self-uri><abstract id="abstract1"><title>Abstract</title><p>This study aimed to investigate gastrointestinal tolerability, treatment persistence and iron status markers in patients with iron deficiency anaemia (IDA) who received oral iron replacement therapy (IRT) with <italic>v</italic>. without concomitant Lactobacillus plantarum 299v (<italic>L. plantarum 299v</italic>) probiotic supplementation. A total of 295 patents with newly diagnosed IDA were randomly assigned to receive either IRT alone (<italic>n</italic> 157, IRT-only group) or IRT plus <italic>L. plantarum 299v</italic> (<italic>n</italic> 138, IRT-Pro group) in this prospective randomised non-placebo-controlled study (ClinicalTrials.gov Identifier: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT06521879" ext-link-type="uri">NCT06521879</ext-link>). Gastrointestinal intolerance symptoms (at baseline, within the first 30 d of IRT and at any time during 3-month IRT), serum Hb levels (at baseline and 3rd month of IRT) and iron status markers (at baseline and 3rd month of IRT) were recorded. IRT-Pro group, when compared with IRT-only group, experienced significantly lower rates of gastrointestinal intolerance over the course of IRT (13·0 % <italic>v</italic>. 46·5 %, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·001) and treatment discontinuation within the first 30 d (3·6 % <italic>v</italic>. 15·9 %, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·001). At 3rd month of therapy, IRT-Pro <italic>v</italic>. IRT-only group had significantly higher serum levels for iron (76·0 (51·0–96·0) <italic>v</italic>. 60·0(43·0–70·0) µg/dl, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·001) and transferrin saturation (20·1 (12·5–28·5) <italic>v</italic>. 14·5 (10·5–19·0) %, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·001) and higher change from baseline Hb (0·9 (0·3–1·3) <italic>v</italic>. 0·4 (–0·1–1·1) g/dl, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·001) levels. Use of <italic>L. plantarum 299v</italic> probiotic supplementation during the first 30 d of IRT in IDA patients significantly reduces the gastrointestinal burden of IRT (particularly abdominal pain and bloating), the likelihood of intolerance development (by ∼3 times) and treatment discontinuation (by∼5 times), as accompanied by improved serum Hb levels and serum iron markers.</p><sec id="kwd-group1" sec-type="kwd-group" disp-level="2"><p><bold>Keywords:</bold> Iron deficiency anaemia, Oral iron replacement, Probiotic supplementation, Lactobacillus plantarum 299v, Gastrointestinal tolerability, Iron status markers</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>status</meta-name><meta-value>released</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>display-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-in-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-journal-matter</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-scanned</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-retracted</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes notes-type="article-notes"><sec id="historyarticle-meta1" sec-type="history" disp-level="2"><p>Received 2024 Jul 15; Revised 2024 Oct 11; Accepted 2024 Oct 28; Issue date 2024 Nov 28.</p></sec></notes></front><body><p>Iron deficiency anaemia (IDA) is one of the most prevalent micronutrient deficiencies and a global health concern<sup>(<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>)</sup>. IDA has detrimental health consequences such as severe fatigue, dyspnoea and impaired thermoregulatory, neurocognitive and immune functions, in addition to its association with adverse outcomes in chronic kidney disease or chronic heart failure<sup>(<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>–<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>Considering its hazard for the worldwide population, prevention and treatment of iron deficiency and IDA is of critical importance, while the strategies are mainly based on combination of dietary improvement, iron fortification of food, and iron supplementation<sup>(<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>–<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>)</sup>. Amongst these, oral iron supplementation (i.e. ferrous sulphate, gluconate and fumarate) is the most widely available and affordable method but its effectiveness is considerably limited by gastrointestinal side effects (in up to 70 % of patients), markedly impairing adherence to treatment and repletion of iron stores<sup>(<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>–<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>Besides the inadequate iron intake, low iron bioavailability and absorption are also implicated in IDA pathogenesis and are highly affected by the gut microbiota composition<sup>(<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>)</sup>. The absorption of iron from diet or oral supplements is a complex mechanism, while oral iron supplements may also alter the composition of the gut microbiota towards a more pro-inflammatory milieu and decrease iron bioavailability<sup>(<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>)</sup>. Hence, strategies that consider enhancing iron absorption and reducing the risk of gastrointestinal side effects are important for effective iron replacement in patients with IDA<sup>(<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>The gut microbiota enhances the host’s access to dietary iron by reducing the concentration of iron-binding compounds in the gut, and by converting Fe3+ to Fe2+, the absorbable ion form<sup>(<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>)</sup>. Due to the role of gut microbiota in regulating iron balance, probiotics have been suggested as a potential strategy to enhance iron absorption and alleviate deficiency, enabling a higher reduction of ferric iron to a bioavailable form, improved iron uptake by enterocytes, and an anti-inflammatory immune response<sup>(<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>Use of probiotics, mostly the Lactobacillus and Bifidobacterium strains, as live microorganisms that improve composition of the gut microbiota, has gained public popularity because of their wide range of preventative and therapeutic potentials<sup>(<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>Lactic acid-forming bacteria (lactobacilli) can increase iron absorption by lowering intestinal pH, activating phytases, causing shifts in gut microbiota metabolism and inducing anti-inflammatory immunomodulation<sup>(<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>)</sup>. This suggests that utilisation of probiotic bacteria may be a valuable clinical tool in prevention and amelioration of IDA, by optimising dietary iron bioavailability and thus improving iron status without the gastrointestinal burden of additional supplemental iron<sup>(<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>–<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>)</sup>. Specifically, the strain <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic> 299v (<italic>L. plantarum 299v</italic>) with the ability to survive the passage through acid stomach and colonise the intestine<sup>(<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>)</sup> has been shown to reduce bloating and abdominal pain in irritable bowel syndrome patients<sup>(<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>)</sup> and to increase iron absorption and dietary iron bioavailability in IDA patients<sup>(<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>)</sup>. However, while probiotics were reported to be associated with amelioration of gastrointestinal intolerance symptoms in different settings<sup>(<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>–<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>)</sup>, their effects on gastrointestinal burden of iron replacement therapy (IRT) as well as on body iron status are less extensively studied in patients with IDA<sup>(<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>–<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>Therefore, this study aimed to investigate the effects of <italic>L. plantarum 299v</italic> probiotic supplementation added to oral IRT on gastrointestinal burden, tolerability, treatment compliance and serum iron status markers in patients with newly diagnosed IDA.</p><sec id="s1" disp-level="1"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s1-1" disp-level="2"><title>Study population</title><p>A total of 295 patients with newly diagnosed IDA who were planned to receive routine oral IRT were included in this prospective randomised non-placebo, controlled 3-month follow-up study (ClinicalTrials.gov Identifier: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT06521879" ext-link-type="uri">NCT06521879</ext-link>) conducted between September 2020 and March 2022 at a tertiary care internal medicine clinic. Patients were randomly assigned via simple randomisation method (computer-generated random number sequence) to receive either IRT alone (<italic>n</italic> 157, IRT-only group) or IRT plus <italic>L. plantarum 299v</italic> probiotic support (<italic>n</italic> 138, IRT-Pro group). Adult (aged &gt; 18 years) treatment-naïve patients diagnosed with newly diagnosed IDA without previous IRT were included in the study, while those with irritable bowel syndrome, previous IRT therapy or intolerance to IRT and those with a known chronic disease (i.e. inflammatory bowel disease and celiac disease) or untreated active menometrorrhagia and haemorrhoid were excluded from the study.</p><p>Written informed consent was obtained from each subject following a detailed explanation of the objectives and protocol of the study which was conducted in accordance with the ethical principles stated in the ‘Declaration of Helsinki’ and approved by the Clinical Research and Ethics Committee of University of Health Sciences Antalya Training and Research Hospital (Date of Approval: 27/08/2020; Protocol No: 13/15).</p></sec><sec id="s1-2" disp-level="2"><title>IDA definition</title><p>IDA was defined as having ferritin levels of &lt; 20 ng/ml or transferrin saturation &lt; 15 %, while the Hb levels were below 12 mg/dl<sup>(<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>)</sup>.</p></sec><sec id="s1-3" disp-level="2"><title>Treatments</title><p>All patients received IRT with ferrous sulphate (Fe2<sup>+</sup>: 304·2 mg ferrous fumarate in pellet form, equivalent to 100 mg elemental iron) preparation (100 mg, once daily) for 3 months, while those in the IRT-Pro group also received daily (10B CFU) <italic>L. plantarum 299v</italic> (Probest®, Abdi Ibrahim, Turkey) probiotic supplementation for 30 d starting from the first day of IRT.</p></sec><sec id="s1-4" disp-level="2"><title>Assessments</title><p>Data on gastrointestinal intolerance symptoms (loss of appetite, nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain, diarrhoea, constipation and bloating) were recorded at three time points including baseline, within the first 30 d of IRT and at any time during 3-month IRT. Overall, intolerance symptoms were evaluated based on new-onset (not present at baseline but appeared on IRT), ameliorated (present at baseline but disappeared on IRT) and total ((baseline + new onset) – (ameliorated)) symptom rates. A seven-item questionnaire was used to assess the presence of gastrointestinal intolerance symptoms during the past week on a binary scale (Yes or No), including the six items (nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain, bloating, constipation, diarrhoea) of Gastrointestinal Symptom Rating Scale<sup>(<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>)</sup> and the loss of appetite (poor or very poor appetite) as the seventh item using the first question of the Appetite and Dietary Assessment Tool<sup>(<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>Serum Hb levels (g/dl) and serum iron status markers including ferritin (ng/ml), iron (µg/dl), total iron-binding capacity (TIBC, µg/dl) and transferrin saturation (%) were recorded at baseline and at 3rd month of IRT. Samples for complete blood count were collected in K3EDTA tubes and analysed with an automated haematology analyser including Beckman-Coulter for Hb measurement and LISA 500 Plus automated chemical analyser (Hycell Diagnostics, Paris, France) for serum iron markers. Transferrin saturation was calculated by dividing serum iron by TIBC X 100.</p><p>Data on treatment discontinuation (persistence to IRT) were also recorded in study groups along with comparison of study variables in patients with <italic>v</italic>. without treatment discontinuation within the first 30 d of IRT.</p></sec><sec id="s1-5" disp-level="2"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>At least 189 patients were calculated to be included via sample size estimation (G * Power 3·1·9 program) based on a power of 80 % at a type I error of 0·05 and an effect size (w = 0·261) calculated using data from a previous study by Cekin et al.<sup>(<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>)</sup>. Given the high likelihood of missing data, a total of 200 patients were planned to be included in the study population with the use of 25 % lost to follow-up ratio.</p><p>Statistical analysis was made using IBM SPSS Statistics for Windows, Version 22.0 (IBM Corp.). Pearson’s chi-square test, Fisher’s exact test and McNemar test were used for analysis of categorical variables. Mann–Whitney U test was used for analysis of non-normally distributed numerical data while independent sample <italic>t</italic> test was used for normally distributed data. The number needed to treat (NNT) analysis was performed to determine how many patients must receive IRT-Pro instead of IRT to prevent one additional treatment discontinuation. Data are expressed as mean (<sc>sd</sc>, median, interquartile range, minimum-maximum and per cent (%) where appropriate. <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s2" disp-level="1"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2-1" disp-level="2"><title>Patient demographics, intolerance development and treatment discontinuation</title><p>A total of 295 patents with newly diagnosed IDA were included in the study as randomly assigned to IRT-only (<italic>n</italic> 157) or IRT-Pro (<italic>n</italic> 138) groups. Mean (<sc>sd</sc>) patient age was 36·1(10·7) years and 96·3 % of patients were females. Both in the overall study population (<italic>n</italic> 295) and in patients with gastrointestinal intolerance symptoms (<italic>n</italic> 91), IRT-only and IRT-Pro groups were homogenous in terms of patient demographics (Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Patient demographics, intolerance development and treatment discontinuation (Numbers and percentages; mean values and <sc>sd</sc>)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Total (<italic>n</italic> 295)</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">IRT-only (<italic>n</italic> 157)</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">IRT-Pro (<italic>n</italic> 138)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>n</italic>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>n</italic>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>n</italic>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patient demographics – overall</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Age (year)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Mean</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">36·1</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">36·3</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">35·9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·775</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><sc>s</sc>
<sc>d</sc>
</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">10·7</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">10·5</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">10·9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gender, <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Male</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3·7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5·1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2·2</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0·186</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Female</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">284</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">96·3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">149</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">94·9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">135</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">97·8</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Intolerance within 3 months IRT, <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Absent</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">204</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">69·2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">84</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">53·5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">120</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">87·0</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">&lt; 0·001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Present</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">91</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">30·8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">73</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">46·5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13·0</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patient demographics – intolerance group (<italic>n</italic> 91)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Age (year)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Mean</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">37·2</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">37·4</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">36·9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·755</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><sc>sd</sc>
</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">10·6</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">10·6</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">10·9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gender, <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Male</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3·3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2·8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5·8</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0·102</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Female</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">88</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">96·7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">71</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">97·2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">94·2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Treatment discontinuation, <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Total</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">36</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12·2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">28</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17·8*</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5·8</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0·002</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Within 30 d</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">30</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10·2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15·9**</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3·6</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Day of discontinuation</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Median</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">11</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">11</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">13</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·237</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> min-max</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">7–15</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">7–16</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">7–13</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Symptoms within 30 d in discontinuers (<italic>n</italic> 30), <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Loss of appetite</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6·7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6·7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·0</td><td rowspan="7" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Nausea</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23·3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16·7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6·7</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Vomiting</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3·3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3·3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·0</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Abdominal pain</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16·7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3·3</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Diarrhoea</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6·7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6·7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·0</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Constipation</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">30·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23·3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6·7</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Bloating</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="_fn_p21"><p>IRT: Iron replacement therapy; IRT-only: received IRT alone; IRT-Pro: received IRT plus <italic>L. plantarum 299v.</italic>
</p><p>Independent <italic>t</italic> test, Mann–Whitney U test, Pearson’s chi-square test, Fisher’s exact test.</p><p>*<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·01 and **<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·001 compared with IRT-Pro group.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Overall, 91 (30·8 %) of 295 patients reported gastrointestinal intolerance symptoms within 3 months of IRT. Patients in the IRT-Pro group compared with those in the IRT-only group had significantly lower rate of gastrointestinal intolerance development within 3 months of IRT (13·0 % <italic>v</italic>. 46·5 %, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·001) (Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><p>Treatment discontinuation within 3 months of IRT occurred in 36 (12·2 %) of 295 patients, while it was within the first 30 d of IRT in 30 (10·2 %) patients. Overall (17·8 <italic>v</italic>. 5·8 %, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·01) and first 30-day (15·9 % <italic>v</italic>. 3·6 %, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·001) treatment discontinuation rates were significantly higher in the IRT-only group than in the IRT-Pro group (Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><p>IRT-Pro had an NNT of 3, indicating that 3 patients have to be treated with IRT-Pro instead of IRT-only to prevent one additional treatment discontinuation.</p><p>Among patients who discontinued IRT within the first 30 d, constipation was the leading symptom (30·0 %), followed by nausea (23·3 %) and abdominal pain (20·0 %), all of which were particularly noted in the IRT-only group (23·3 %, 16·7 % and 16·7 %, respectively) (Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-2" disp-level="2"><title>Intolerance data at baseline and within 3 months of iron replacement in study groups</title><p>Baseline rates for abdominal pain (17·4 <italic>v</italic>. 4·5 %, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·001) and diarrhoea (5·8 <italic>v</italic>. 1·3 %, <italic>P</italic> = 0·049) were significantly higher in the IRT-Pro group (<italic>n</italic> 138) than in the IRT-only (<italic>n</italic> 157) group (Table <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Intolerance symptoms at baseline and during 3 months of IRT in study groups (Numbers and percentages)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">IRT</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">IRT-Pro</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Intolerance symptoms</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>n</italic>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>n</italic>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>n</italic>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>n</italic>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>n</italic>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>P</italic> value*</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Loss of appetite</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Baseline</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">157</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1·3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">138</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·500</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">During IRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">New onset</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">132</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6·1</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">133</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0·019</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>Ameliorated</italic>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>1</italic>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>0·8</italic>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>–</italic>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6·8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0·010</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<italic>P</italic> value (baseline <italic>v</italic>. total)<sup>†</sup>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0·008</bold>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1·000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Nausea</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Baseline</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">157</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">138</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">During IRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">New onset</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">132</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17·4</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">133</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3·8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0·001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>Ameliorated</italic>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17·4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3·8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0·001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<italic>P</italic> value (baseline <italic>v</italic>. total)<sup>†</sup>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0·001</bold>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·063</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Vomiting</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Baseline</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">157</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">138</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">During IRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">New onset</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">132</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2·3</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">133</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·122</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>Ameliorated</italic>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>–</bold>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2·3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·122</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<italic>P</italic> value (baseline <italic>v</italic>. total)<sup>†</sup>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·250</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Abdominal pain</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Baseline</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">157</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4·5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">138</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17·4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0·001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">During IRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">New onset</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">132</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15·2</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">133</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0·001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>Ameliorated</italic>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>1</italic>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>0·8</italic>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>20</italic>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>15·0</italic>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">26</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19·7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0·001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<italic>P</italic> value (baseline <italic>v</italic>. total)<sup>†</sup>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0·001</bold>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0·001</bold>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Diarrhoea</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Baseline</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">157</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1·3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">138</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5·8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0·049</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">During IRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">New onset</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">132</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3·8</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">133</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·749</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>Ameliorated</italic>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>–</bold>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>6</italic>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>4·5</italic>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5·3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4·5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·765</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<italic>P</italic> value (baseline <italic>v</italic>. total)<sup>†</sup>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·063</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·754</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Constipation</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Baseline</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">157</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1·3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">138</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4·3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·153</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">During IRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">New onset</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">132</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13·6</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">133</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4·5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0·010</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>Ameliorated</italic>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>1</italic>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>0·8</italic>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>2</italic>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>1·5</italic>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14·4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7·5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·073</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<italic>P</italic> value (baseline <italic>v</italic>. total)<sup>†</sup>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0·001</bold>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0·031</bold>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Bloating</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Baseline</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">157</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">38</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24·2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">138</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">28</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20·3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·421</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">During IRT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">New onset</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">132</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6·8</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">133</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5·2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·585</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>Ameliorated</italic>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>15</italic>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>11·4</italic>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>24</italic>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>18·1</italic>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24·2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8·3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0·001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<italic>P</italic> value (baseline <italic>v</italic>. total)<sup>†</sup>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·267</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0·006</bold>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="_fn_p31"><p>IRT: Iron replacement therapy; IRT-only: received IRT alone; IRT-Pro: received IRT plus <italic>L. plantarum 299v.</italic>
</p><p>New-onset: not present at baseline but appeared on IRT; ameliorated: present at baseline but disappeared on IRT; total: ((baseline + new onset) – (ameliorated)).</p><p>*Fisher exact test, Pearson’s chi-square test, <sup>†</sup>McNemar test (<italic>baseline v. during 3 months of IRT).</italic>
</p><p>All relevant values were formatted in italic and bold face.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In the IRT-only group, symptom rates significantly increased from baseline over the course of iron replacement (<italic>n</italic> 132), including loss of appetite (1·3 <italic>v</italic>. 6·8 %, <italic>P</italic> = 0·008), nausea (0·0 <italic>v</italic>. 17·4 %, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·001), abdominal pain (4·5 <italic>v</italic>. 19·7 %, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·001) and constipation (1·3 <italic>v</italic>. 14·4 %, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·001). In the IRT-pro group (<italic>n</italic> 133), significant decrease from baseline rates was noted in the abdominal pain (17·4 <italic>v</italic>. 13·3 %, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·001) and bloating (20·3 <italic>v</italic>. 8·3 %, <italic>P</italic> = 0·006), while constipation (4·3 <italic>v</italic>. 7·5 %) showed significant increase from baseline (Table <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><p>Loss of appetite (0·8 <italic>v</italic>. 6·8 %, <italic>P</italic> = 0·010), nausea (3·8 <italic>v</italic>. 17·4 %, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·001), abdominal pain (3·0 <italic>v</italic>. 19·7 %, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·001) and bloating (8·3 <italic>v</italic>. 24·2 %, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·001) were significantly less common in the IRT-Pro group than in the IRT-only group (Table <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><p>Considering the intolerance symptoms newly emerged under IRT, the likelihood of developing de novo loss of appetite (6·1 <italic>v</italic>. 0·8 %, <italic>P</italic> = 0·019), nausea (17·4 <italic>v</italic>. 3·8 %, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·001), abdominal pain (15·2 <italic>v</italic>. 0·0 %, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·001) and constipation (13·6 <italic>v</italic>. 4·5 %, <italic>P</italic> = 0·010) were significantly higher in the IRT group than in the IRT-Pro group (Table <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-3" disp-level="2"><title>Serum iron status markers</title><p>At baseline, serum ferritin levels (5·0 (3·0–7·0) <italic>v</italic>. 7·0 (4·0–12·0) ng/ml, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·001) and transferrin saturation (10·05 (5·2–16·0) <italic>v</italic>. 12·1 (8·1–17·1)%, <italic>P</italic> = 0·029) were significantly lower in the IRT-Pro group (<italic>n</italic> 138) than in the IRT-only (<italic>n</italic> 157) group (Table <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Serum iron status markers from baseline to 3rd month of iron replacement therapy (Median values and interquartile ranges)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Total</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">IRT</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">IRT-Pro</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Serum iron status</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>n</italic>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Median</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">IQR</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>n</italic>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Median</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">IQR</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>n</italic>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Median</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">IQR</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ferritin (ng/ml)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Baseline</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">295</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4·0–9·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">157</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4·0–12·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">138</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3·0–7·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0·001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 3rd month</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">259</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11·0–24·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">129</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8–24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">130</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17·5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15–23</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·094</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Change from baseline</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2·0–17·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–1·0–15·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8·0–17·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0·001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Iron (µg/dl)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Baseline</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">295</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">45·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">28·0–64·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">157</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">47·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">34·0–64·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">138</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">39·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24·0–64·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·087</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 3rd month</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">259</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">65·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">44·0–87·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">129</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">60·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">43·0–70·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">130</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">76·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">51·0–96·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0·001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Change from baseline</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–2·0–33·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–6·0–23·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23·5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5·0–48·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0·001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">TIBC (µg/dl)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Baseline</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">295</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">403·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">374·0–444·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">157</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">406·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">38·01–438·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">138</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">403</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">374·0–446·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·869</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 3rd month</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">259</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">385·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">355–421·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">129</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">396·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">374·0–421·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">130</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">368·5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">327·0–402·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0·001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Change from baseline</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–24·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–60·0–11·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–11·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–40·0–24·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–45·5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–76·0–(–3·0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0·001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Transferrin saturation (%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Baseline</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">295</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11·3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6·8–16·7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">157</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12·1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8·1–17·1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">138</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10·1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5·2–16·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0·029</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 3rd month</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">259</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16·3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11·5–23·8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">129</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14·5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10·5–19·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">130</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20·1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12·5–28·5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0·001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Change from baseline</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4·3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–0·6–9·8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2·1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–1·5–6·3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8·2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2·7–14·1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0·001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hb (g/dl)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Baseline</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">295</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11·9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10·5–12·6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">157</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11·9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10·5–12·7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">138</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11·7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10·5–12·6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·245</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 3rd month</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">259</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12·4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11·5–13·2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">129</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12·2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11·7–13·1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">130</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12·6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11·5–13·2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·229</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Change from baseline</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·2–1·2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–0·1–1·1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·3–1·3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0·001</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="_fn_p41"><p>IRT-only: received IRT alone; IRT-Pro: received IRT plus <italic>L. plantarum 299v</italic>; IQR: Interquartile range; TIBC: Total iron-binding capacity.</p><p>Mann–Whitney U test.</p><p>All relevant values were formatted in bold face.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>At 3rd month of therapy, IRT-Pro (<italic>n</italic> 130) <italic>v</italic>. IRT-only (<italic>n</italic> 129) group had significantly higher serum levels for iron (76·0 (51·0–96·0) <italic>v</italic>. 60·0 (43·0–70·0) µg/dl, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·001) and transferrin saturation (20·1 (12·5–28·5) <italic>v</italic>. 14·5 (10·5–19·0)%, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·001) as well as higher change from baseline ferritin (13·0 (8·0–17·0) <italic>v</italic>. 5·0 (–1·0–15·0 ng/ml, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·001), iron (23·5(5·0–48·0) <italic>v</italic>. 8·0 (–6·0–23·0) µg/dl, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·001), transferrin saturation (8·2 (2·7–14·1) <italic>v</italic>. 2·1 (–1·5–6·3)%, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·001) and Hb (0·9 (0·3–1·3) <italic>v</italic>. 0·4 (–0·1–1·1) g/dl, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·001) (Table <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p><p>The 3<sup>rd</sup>-month TIBC levels were significantly lower (368·5 (327·0–402·0) <italic>v</italic>. 396·0 (374·0–421·0) µg/dl, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·001) in the IRT-Pro group, as well as more remarkable decrease from baseline TIBC (–45·5 (–76·0/ −3·0) <italic>v</italic>. −11·0 (–40·0/24·0) µg/dl, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0·001) (Table <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-4" disp-level="2"><title>Patient demographics and baseline serum iron markers according to treatment discontinuation</title><p>No significant difference was noted in patients who discontinued treatment within 30 d and those who continued therapy in terms of patient demographics or baseline serum iron status markers (Table <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tbl4" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>Patient demographics and baseline serum iron status markers according to treatment discontinuation within 30 d (Mean values and <sc>sd</sc>; median values and minimum and maximum values)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="5" rowspan="1">Treatment discontinuation within 30 d</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Yes (<italic>n</italic> 30)</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">No (<italic>n</italic> 265)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<sc>sd</sc>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<sc>sd</sc>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patient demographics</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age, Mean(<sc>sd</sc>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">35·2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10·1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">36·3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10·7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·611*</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>n</italic>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>n</italic>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gender, <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Male</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3·3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3·8</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0·690<sup>†</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Female</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">96·7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">255</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">96·2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Median</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">min-max</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Median</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">min-max</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Baseline serum iron status markers, median(min-max)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Ferritin (ng/ml)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2–36</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–36</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·116<sup>‡</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Iron (Fe, µg/dl)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">52·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15–24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">45·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7–200</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·368<sup>‡</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> TIBC (µg/dl)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">424·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">281–481</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">402·0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">248–585</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·842<sup>‡</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Transferrin sat (%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13·20</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3·4–27·1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11·2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1·3–42·3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·354<sup>‡</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Hb (g/dl)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11·5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9·1–13·7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11·9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6·5–14·9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0·344<sup>‡</sup>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="_fn_p49"><p>IRT-only: received IRT alone; IRT-Pro: received IRT plus <italic>L. plantarum 299v.</italic>
</p><p>*Independent <italic>t</italic> test, <sup>†</sup>Fisher exact test, <sup>‡</sup>Mann–Whitney U test.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="s3" disp-level="1"><title>Discussion</title><p>Our findings revealed that at least one-third of patients developed gastrointestinal intolerance within 3 months of IRT, while the first 30 d of IRT was the most critical period for treatment discontinuation. Importantly, concomitant use of <italic>L. plantarum 299v</italic> probiotic supplementation during this critical period significantly reduced the likelihood of intolerance development (by ∼3 times) and treatment discontinuation (by∼5 times), increasing the gastrointestinal tolerability of the IRT, which also enabled the significantly improved serum iron status markers.</p><p>In addition, patients in the IRT-Pro group were more advantageous not only in terms of prevention of intolerance symptoms emerging over the course of IRT (loss of appetite, nausea, abdominal pain and constipation) but also in terms of amelioration of symptoms recorded at baseline (loss of appetite, nausea, abdominal pain and bloating), which seemed to positively affect their adherence to IRT. In contrast, IDA patients who received only IRT experienced significant increase of symptoms recorded at baseline such as loss of appetite, nausea and abdominal pain as well as a greater increase in constipation (∼10-fold <italic>v</italic>. ∼2-fold in IRT-Pro group). These findings seem notable given that constipation, nausea and abdominal pain were also the leading symptoms in patients who discontinued IRT within the first 30 d, and all were particularly noted in the IRT group.</p><p>Consistent with our findings, <italic>L. plantarum 299v</italic> supplementation has been reported to have many clinically confirmed positive effects such as improving gastrointestinal wellbeing in a healthy population, symptom relief by decreasing bloating and abdominal pain and normalisation of stool frequency as early as in the 2nd week of consumption in irritable bowel syndrome patients and decreasing the incidence of diarrhoea among patients receiving antibiotics<sup>(<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>
<italic>L. plantarum 299v</italic> has also the ability to survive passage through gastrointestinal tract and to inhibit the growth of potentially pathogenic bacteria in the intestine in addition to anti-inflammatory effects<sup>(<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>)</sup>. Notably, many studies indicated a link between gut microbiota (dysbiosis) and IDA as well as the association of iron therapy with the diversity and composition of the intestinal flora<sup>(<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>–<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>While iron therapy is considered to normalise Hb within 2 months of treatment onset, and to build up iron stores within the next 2–3 months, many patients face considerable challenges in adhering to and persisting with the full iron replacement regimen<sup>(<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>)</sup>. Our results showed that IRT-Pro regimen had an NNT of 3, indicating that 3 patients have to be treated with IRT-Pro instead of IRT alone to prevent one additional treatment discontinuation Hence, use of <italic>L. plantarum 299v</italic> for the first 30 d of iron replacement seems to be a favourable treatment approach in IDA patients in terms of preventing the considerable gastrointestinal burden, including the amelioration of the symptoms already existent before IRT, and increasing patient adherence to IRT<sup>(<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>The iron replacement aims not only to correct the Hb deficit but also to provide enough iron for measurable iron stores<sup>(<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>)</sup>. Our findings emphasise the potential benefit of using <italic>L. plantarum 299v</italic> supplementation in provision of more adequate supply of iron for Hb synthesis and in increasing the iron stores (improved iron status markers such as serum iron, ferritin, TIBC and transferrin saturation) and thus improving the effectiveness of oral iron replacement in patients with IDA.</p><p>The positive effects of using <italic>L. plantarum 299v</italic> supplementation for the first 30 d of IRT seem to indicate the likelihood of this probiotic strain to counteract the adverse effects of residual iron supplement that remains largely unabsorbed in the digestive tract, commonly causing adverse gastrointestinal events, reduced compliance and inefficient repletion of iron stores<sup>(<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>In fact, given the improved tolerability and iron status markers within 3 months of therapy, use of <italic>L. plantarum 299v</italic> may also decrease the need for longer-term use of oral iron replacement or use of IV replacement, as well as the related gastrointestinal burden, offering a potentially cost-effective alternative in the management of IDA patients.</p><p>Data from clinical studies also revealed the association of <italic>L. plantarum 299v</italic> supplementation with increased bioavailability and absorption of iron in different types of iron deficiencies<sup>(<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>)</sup>. The exact mechanism behind the beneficial effects of <italic>L. plantarum 299v</italic> on dietary non-heme iron absorption is not known. Nonetheless, the process is considered likely to be mediated by the formation of bioavailable ferrous form by reduction of ferric iron (increasing iron uptake by enterocytes), the enhanced mucin production at the intestinal surface (promoting enterocyte iron uptake) and the immunomodulation promoting an anti-inflammatory immune response that suppresses the inflammatory cytokine-mediated increase in circulating hepcidin which otherwise blocks the passage of iron from the intestinal cell to the plasma (enhancing iron bioavailability)<sup>(<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>)</sup>. Hence, <italic>L. plantarum 299v</italic> supplementation seems to ensure adequate iron absorption by affecting multitude of factors implicated in the iron bioavailability, such as the choice of iron compound, the physiological state of the consumer (i.e. iron status, other nutritional deficiencies and inflammatory disorders) and the presence of enhancers and inhibitors of absorption in the food matrix<sup>(<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>Similar to our results, in a recent randomised clinical trial in iron-deficient athletes, intake of <italic>L. plantarum 299v</italic> plus 20 mg of iron was considered likely to result in a more substantial and rapid improvement in iron status compared with 20 mg of iron alone<sup>(<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>)</sup>. In addition, <italic>L. plantarum 299v</italic> (plus sucrosomial iron and vitamin C) was reported to have a positive effect on the treatment and prevention of IDA, which causes higher iron blood levels (by 11 %) because of increased iron absorption compared with use of only sucrosomial iron and vitamin C<sup>(<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>)</sup>. Studies in pregnant women also showed the association of <italic>L. plantarum 299v</italic> with slower decline in maternal haematological and iron parameters across pregnancy in non-anaemic women as well as in those who are at risk for IDA in pregnancy<sup>(<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>In a meta-analysis of eight studies on the effect of the probiotic <italic>L. plantarum 299v</italic> on iron absorption in healthy women of childbearing age, pregnant women and patients with IDA, <italic>L. plantarum 299v</italic> was concluded to significantly improve non-heme dietary iron absorption in humans<sup>(<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>)</sup>, while only one of eight studies reported improvement in iron status-related indices<sup>(<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>)</sup>. Importantly, providing data on the beneficial effects of <italic>L. plantarum 299v</italic> probiotic strain in IDA patients also in terms of iron status markers, our results indicate the likelihood of using <italic>L. plantarum 299v</italic> probiotic supplementation within the first 30 d of IRT to enable two sine qua non of the proper medication adherence and persistence, namely the perceived efficacy (reduced symptoms of iron deficiency) and the improved tolerability<sup>(<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>)</sup>. Nonetheless, there remains a need for further research toward filling gaps in the existing literature given that the effect of probiotics on body iron status remains to be less certain than their effects on iron absorption<sup>(<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>Certain limitations to this study should be considered. First, single-centre study design, preponderance of female participants and exclusion of patients with known intolerance to oral iron or those with chronic diseases (i.e. İBS and inflammatory bowel disease) limit the generalisability of the findings to broader populations, including males, diverse ethnic groups and unselected patient populations. This might have also caused a selection bias toward a favourable tolerability for oral iron and affected our tolerability and treatment discontinuation results. Second, given the potential psychological effects of probiotic support, the lack of a placebo group seems to be another limitation of the present study in terms of the likelihood of a placebo effect with potential impact on the subjective symptom reporting. Nonetheless, the marked differences between treatment groups in gastrointestinal intolerance and treatment discontinuation seem to indicate a strong impact of probiotic therapy which cannot be explained solely by the placebo effect. Also, NNT analysis, which was performed particularly for this reason (lack of placebo arm), did not reveal a high NNT value which otherwise would indicate the likelihood of placebo effect. Third, assessment of symptom frequency was based on subjective reporting along with lack of items on symptom severity. Fourth, use of only the persistence (treatment discontinuation) measure of compliance with lack of adherence data is another important limitation of the study. Fifth, lack of data on iron regulation, including hepcidin, erythropoietin and erythroferrone, as the potential players, as well as the lack of data on purity testing of probiotic and no stool collection to demonstrate LP299V colonisation in gut or changes to microbiome are other limitations. Nevertheless, despite these certain limitations, given the restricted amount of data on iron status changes in IDA patients treated with probiotic plus IRT, our findings represent a valuable contribution to the literature.</p><sec id="s3-1" disp-level="2"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In conclusion, our findings in IDA patients revealed that using <italic>L. plantarum 299v</italic> probiotic supplementation during the first 30 d of IRT significantly reduced the gastrointestinal burden (particularly abdominal pain and bloating) related to IRT, the likelihood of developing de novo symptoms (loss of appetite, nausea, abdominal pain and constipation) under IRT and the likelihood of intolerance development (by ∼3 times) within 3 months of therapy and treatment discontinuation (by∼5 times) within 30 d of therapy. The improved gastrointestinal tolerability and patient adherence to oral IRT was also accompanied by a more remarkable improvement in serum iron markers in patients who received <italic>L. plantarum 299v</italic>. Hence, using <italic>L. plantarum 299v</italic> probiotic supplementation for the first 30 d of iron replacement seems to be a favourable treatment approach in IDA patients, given that oral IRT is limited by gastrointestinal side effects and noncompliance. Given the complex interplay between gut microbiota and iron bioavailability, and the research gap regarding the effects of probiotics on iron status, the long-term effects of different probiotic strains in combination with different iron preparations on iron status markers should further be investigated in unselected IDA populations.</p></sec></sec><sec id="ack1" sec-type="ack" disp-level="1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>None.</p><p>The authors did not receive support from any organisation for the submitted work.</p><p>Y. S. and G. K. contributed to conception and design. Y. S., G. K., G. O. K., A. C., M. E. D., M. M. C. and A. H. C. contributed to data acquisition. Y. S., G. K., G. O. K., A. C., M. E. D., M. M. C. and A. H. C. performed data analysis and interpretation. Y. S. performed drafting the manuscript. A. H. C. performed critical revision of the manuscript for important intellectual additions. All authors approved the final version of the manuscript for publication.</p><p>The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest.</p></sec><sec id="reflist1" sec-type="ref-list" disp-level="1"><title>References</title><sec id="reflist1_sec2" disp-level="2"><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation id="r1"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Stevens GA, Finucane MM, Nutrition Impact Model Study Group (Anaemia), et al.  (2013) Global, regional, and national trends in haemoglobin concentration and prevalence of total and severe anaemia in children and pregnant and non-pregnant women for 1995–2011: a systematic analysis of population-representative data. Lancet Glob Health
1, e16–e25.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/S2214-109X(13)70001-9"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC4547326"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="25103581"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Lancet Glob Health&amp;title=Global, regional, and national trends in haemoglobin concentration and prevalence of total and severe anaemia in children and pregnant and non-pregnant women for 1995–2011: a systematic analysis of population-representative data&amp;author=GA Stevens&amp;author=MM Finucane&amp;volume=1&amp;publication_year=2013&amp;pages=e16-e25&amp;pmid=25103581&amp;doi=10.1016/S2214-109X(13)70001-9&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation id="r2"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Kumar SB, Arnipalli SR, Mehta P, et al.  (2022) Iron deficiency anemia: efficacy and limitations of nutritional and comprehensive mitigation strategies. Nutrients
14, 2976.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/nu14142976"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9315959"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="35889932"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Nutrients&amp;title=Iron deficiency anemia: efficacy and limitations of nutritional and comprehensive mitigation strategies&amp;author=SB Kumar&amp;author=SR Arnipalli&amp;author=P Mehta&amp;volume=14&amp;publication_year=2022&amp;pages=2976&amp;pmid=35889932&amp;doi=10.3390/nu14142976&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation id="r3"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Seo H, Yoon SY, Ul-Haq A, et al.  (2023) The effects of iron deficiency on the gut microbiota in women of childbearing age. Nutrients
15, 691.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/nu15030691"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9919165"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36771397"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Nutrients&amp;title=The effects of iron deficiency on the gut microbiota in women of childbearing age&amp;author=H Seo&amp;author=SY Yoon&amp;author=A Ul-Haq&amp;volume=15&amp;publication_year=2023&amp;pages=691&amp;pmid=36771397&amp;doi=10.3390/nu15030691&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation id="r4"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Zakrzewska Z, Zawartka A, Schab M, et al.  (2022) Prebiotics, probiotics, and postbiotics in the prevention and treatment of anemia. Microorganisms
10, 1330.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/microorganisms10071330"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9317605"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="35889049"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Microorganisms&amp;title=Prebiotics, probiotics, and postbiotics in the prevention and treatment of anemia&amp;author=Z Zakrzewska&amp;author=A Zawartka&amp;author=M Schab&amp;volume=10&amp;publication_year=2022&amp;pages=1330&amp;pmid=35889049&amp;doi=10.3390/microorganisms10071330&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation id="r5"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Goodnough LT, Nemeth E &amp; Ganz T (2010) Detection, evaluation, and management of iron-restricted erythropoiesis. Blood
116, 4754–4761.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1182/blood-2010-05-286260"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="20826717"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Blood&amp;title=Detection, evaluation, and management of iron-restricted erythropoiesis&amp;author=LT Goodnough&amp;author=E Nemeth&amp;author=T Ganz&amp;volume=116&amp;publication_year=2010&amp;pages=4754-4761&amp;pmid=20826717&amp;doi=10.1182/blood-2010-05-286260&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation id="r6"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Vonderheid SC, Tussing-Humphreys L, Park C, et al.  (2019) A systematic review and meta-analysis on the effects of probiotic species on iron absorption and iron status. Nutrients
11, 2938.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/nu11122938"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC6949908"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="31816981"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Nutrients&amp;title=A systematic review and meta-analysis on the effects of probiotic species on iron absorption and iron status&amp;author=SC Vonderheid&amp;author=L Tussing-Humphreys&amp;author=C Park&amp;volume=11&amp;publication_year=2019&amp;pages=2938&amp;pmid=31816981&amp;doi=10.3390/nu11122938&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation id="r7"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Korčok DJ, Tršić-Milanović NA, Ivanović ND, et al.  (2018) Development of probiotic formulation for the treatment of iron deficiency anemia. Chem Pharm Bull (Tokyo)
66, 347–352.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1248/cpb.c17-00634"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="29353864"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Chem Pharm Bull (Tokyo)&amp;title=Development of probiotic formulation for the treatment of iron deficiency anemia&amp;author=DJ Korčok&amp;author=NA Tršić-Milanović&amp;author=ND Ivanović&amp;volume=66&amp;publication_year=2018&amp;pages=347-352&amp;pmid=29353864&amp;doi=10.1248/cpb.c17-00634&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation id="r8"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Rusu IG, Suharoschi R, Vodnar DC, et al.  (2020) Iron supplementation influence on the gut microbiota and probiotic intake effect in iron deficiency-a literature-based review. Nutrients
12, 1993.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/nu12071993"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7400826"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32635533"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Nutrients&amp;title=Iron supplementation influence on the gut microbiota and probiotic intake effect in iron deficiency-a literature-based review&amp;author=IG Rusu&amp;author=R Suharoschi&amp;author=DC Vodnar&amp;volume=12&amp;publication_year=2020&amp;pages=1993&amp;pmid=32635533&amp;doi=10.3390/nu12071993&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation id="r9"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Bazeley JW &amp; Wish JB (2022) Recent and emerging therapies for iron deficiency in anemia of CKD: a review. Am J Kidney Dis
79, 868–876.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1053/j.ajkd.2021.09.017"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34758368"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Am J Kidney Dis&amp;title=Recent and emerging therapies for iron deficiency in anemia of CKD: a review&amp;author=JW Bazeley&amp;author=JB Wish&amp;volume=79&amp;publication_year=2022&amp;pages=868-876&amp;pmid=34758368&amp;doi=10.1053/j.ajkd.2021.09.017&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation id="r10"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Kumar A, Sharma E, Marley A, et al.  (2022) Iron deficiency anaemia: pathophysiology, assessment, practical management. BMJ Open Gastroenterol
9, e000759.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1136/bmjgast-2021-000759"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC8744124"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34996762"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=BMJ Open Gastroenterol&amp;title=Iron deficiency anaemia: pathophysiology, assessment, practical management&amp;author=A Kumar&amp;author=E Sharma&amp;author=A Marley&amp;volume=9&amp;publication_year=2022&amp;pages=e000759&amp;pmid=34996762&amp;doi=10.1136/bmjgast-2021-000759&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation id="r11"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Gómez-Ramírez S, Brilli E, Tarantino G, et al.  (2018) Sucrosomial® iron: a new generation iron for improving oral supplementation. Pharmaceuticals (Basel)
11, 97.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/ph11040097"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC6316120"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="30287781"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Pharmaceuticals (Basel)&amp;title=Sucrosomial® iron: a new generation iron for improving oral supplementation&amp;author=S Gómez-Ramírez&amp;author=E Brilli&amp;author=G Tarantino&amp;volume=11&amp;publication_year=2018&amp;pages=97&amp;pmid=30287781&amp;doi=10.3390/ph11040097&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation id="r12"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Auerbach M &amp; Adamson JW (2016) How we diagnose and treat iron deficiency anemia. Am J Hematol
91, 31–38.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1002/ajh.24201"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="26408108"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Am J Hematol&amp;title=How we diagnose and treat iron deficiency anemia&amp;author=M Auerbach&amp;author=JW Adamson&amp;volume=91&amp;publication_year=2016&amp;pages=31-38&amp;pmid=26408108&amp;doi=10.1002/ajh.24201&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation id="r13"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Tolkien Z, Stecher L, Mander AP, et al.  (2015) Ferrous sulfate supplementation causes significant gastrointestinal side-effects in adults: a systematic review and meta-analysis. PLoS One
10, e0117383.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pone.0117383"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC4336293"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="25700159"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=PLoS One&amp;title=Ferrous sulfate supplementation causes significant gastrointestinal side-effects in adults: a systematic review and meta-analysis&amp;author=Z Tolkien&amp;author=L Stecher&amp;author=AP Mander&amp;volume=10&amp;publication_year=2015&amp;pages=e0117383&amp;pmid=25700159&amp;doi=10.1371/journal.pone.0117383&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation id="r14"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Deschemin JC, Noordine ML, Remot A, et al.  (2016) The microbiota shifts the iron sensing of intestinal cells. FASEB J
30, 252–261.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1096/fj.15-276840"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="26370847"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=FASEB J&amp;title=The microbiota shifts the iron sensing of intestinal cells&amp;author=JC Deschemin&amp;author=ML Noordine&amp;author=A Remot&amp;volume=30&amp;publication_year=2016&amp;pages=252-261&amp;pmid=26370847&amp;doi=10.1096/fj.15-276840&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation id="r15"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Jaeggi T, Kortman GA, Moretti D, et al.  (2015) Iron fortification adversely affects the gut microbiome, increases pathogen abundance and induces intestinal inflammation in Kenyan infants. Gut
64, 731–742.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1136/gutjnl-2014-307720"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="25143342"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Gut&amp;title=Iron fortification adversely affects the gut microbiome, increases pathogen abundance and induces intestinal inflammation in Kenyan infants&amp;author=T Jaeggi&amp;author=GA Kortman&amp;author=D Moretti&amp;volume=64&amp;publication_year=2015&amp;pages=731-742&amp;pmid=25143342&amp;doi=10.1136/gutjnl-2014-307720&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation id="r16"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Hoppe M, Önning G, Berggren A, et al.  (2015) Probiotic strain lactobacillus plantarum 299v increases iron absorption from an iron-supplemented fruit drink: a double-isotope cross-over single-blind study in women of reproductive age. Br J Nutr
114, 1195–1202.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1017/S000711451500241X"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC4594053"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="26428277"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Br J Nutr&amp;title=Probiotic strain lactobacillus plantarum 299v increases iron absorption from an iron-supplemented fruit drink: a double-isotope cross-over single-blind study in women of reproductive age&amp;author=M Hoppe&amp;author=G Önning&amp;author=A Berggren&amp;volume=114&amp;publication_year=2015&amp;pages=1195-1202&amp;pmid=26428277&amp;doi=10.1017/S000711451500241X&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation id="r17"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Skrypnik K, Bogdański P, Schmidt M, et al.  (2019) The effect of multispecies probiotic supplementation on iron status in rats. Biol Trace Elem Res
19, 234–243.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s12011-019-1658-1"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC6820595"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="30746586"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Biol Trace Elem Res&amp;title=The effect of multispecies probiotic supplementation on iron status in rats&amp;author=K Skrypnik&amp;author=P Bogdański&amp;author=M Schmidt&amp;volume=19&amp;publication_year=2019&amp;pages=234-243&amp;pmid=30746586&amp;doi=10.1007/s12011-019-1658-1&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation id="r18"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Wells JM (2011) Immunomodulatory mechanisms of lactobacilli. Microb Cell Fact
10, S17.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1186/1475-2859-10-S1-S17"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC3231924"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="21995674"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Microb Cell Fact&amp;title=Immunomodulatory mechanisms of lactobacilli&amp;author=JM Wells&amp;volume=10&amp;publication_year=2011&amp;pages=S17&amp;pmid=21995674&amp;doi=10.1186/1475-2859-10-S1-S17&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation id="r19"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Goossens D, Jonkers D, Russel M, et al.  (2005) Survival of the probiotic, L. plantarum 299v and its effects on the faecal bacterial flora, with and without gastric acid inhibition. Dig Liver Dis
37, 44–50.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.dld.2004.07.018"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="15702859"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Dig Liver Dis&amp;title=Survival of the probiotic, L. plantarum 299v and its effects on the faecal bacterial flora, with and without gastric acid inhibition&amp;author=D Goossens&amp;author=D Jonkers&amp;author=M Russel&amp;volume=37&amp;publication_year=2005&amp;pages=44-50&amp;pmid=15702859&amp;doi=10.1016/j.dld.2004.07.018&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation id="r20"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Ducrotté P, Sawant P &amp; Jayanthi V (2012) Clinical trial: lactobacillus plantarum 299v (DSM 9843) improves symptoms of irritable bowel syndrome. World J Gastroenterol
18, 4012–4018.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3748/wjg.v18.i30.4012"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC3419998"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="22912552"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=World J Gastroenterol&amp;title=Clinical trial: lactobacillus plantarum 299v (DSM 9843) improves symptoms of irritable bowel syndrome&amp;author=P Ducrotté&amp;author=P Sawant&amp;author=V Jayanthi&amp;volume=18&amp;publication_year=2012&amp;pages=4012-4018&amp;pmid=22912552&amp;doi=10.3748/wjg.v18.i30.4012&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation id="r21"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Niedzielin K, Kordecki H &amp; Birkenfeld B (2001) A controlled, double-blind, randomized study on the efficacy of Lactobacillus plantarum 299V in patients with irritable bowel syndrome. Eur J Gastroenterol Hepatol
13, 1143–1147.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1097/00042737-200110000-00004"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="11711768"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Eur J Gastroenterol Hepatol&amp;title=A controlled, double-blind, randomized study on the efficacy of Lactobacillus plantarum 299V in patients with irritable bowel syndrome&amp;author=K Niedzielin&amp;author=H Kordecki&amp;author=B Birkenfeld&amp;volume=13&amp;publication_year=2001&amp;pages=1143-1147&amp;pmid=11711768&amp;doi=10.1097/00042737-200110000-00004&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation id="r22"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Bering S, Sjøltov L, Wrisberg SS, et al.  (2007) Viable, lyophilized lactobacilli do not increase iron absorption from a lactic acid-fermented meal in healthy young women, and no iron absorption occurs in the distal intestine. Br J Nutr
98, 991–997.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1017/S0007114507761809"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="17764597"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Br J Nutr&amp;title=Viable, lyophilized lactobacilli do not increase iron absorption from a lactic acid-fermented meal in healthy young women, and no iron absorption occurs in the distal intestine&amp;author=S Bering&amp;author=L Sjøltov&amp;author=SS Wrisberg&amp;volume=98&amp;publication_year=2007&amp;pages=991-997&amp;pmid=17764597&amp;doi=10.1017/S0007114507761809&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation id="r23"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Scheers N, Rossander-Hulthen L, Torsdottir I, et al.  (2016) Increased iron bioavailability from lactic-fermented vegetables is likely an effect of promoting the formation of ferric iron (Fe(3+)). Eur J Nutr
55, 373–382.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s00394-015-0857-6"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC4737790"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="25672527"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Eur J Nutr&amp;title=Increased iron bioavailability from lactic-fermented vegetables is likely an effect of promoting the formation of ferric iron (Fe(3+))&amp;author=N Scheers&amp;author=L Rossander-Hulthen&amp;author=I Torsdottir&amp;volume=55&amp;publication_year=2016&amp;pages=373-382&amp;pmid=25672527&amp;doi=10.1007/s00394-015-0857-6&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation id="r24"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Şahin K, Şahintürk Y, Köker G, et al.  (2022) Metformin with <italic>v.</italic> without concomitant probiotic therapy in newly diagnosed patients with type 2 diabetes or prediabetes: a comparative analysis in relation to glycemic control, gastrointestinal side effects, and treatment compliance. Turk J Gastroenterol
33, 925–933.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.5152/tjg.2022.211063"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9797791"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36098362"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Turk J Gastroenterol&amp;title=Metformin with v. without concomitant probiotic therapy in newly diagnosed patients with type 2 diabetes or prediabetes: a comparative analysis in relation to glycemic control, gastrointestinal side effects, and treatment compliance&amp;author=K Şahin&amp;author=Y Şahintürk&amp;author=G Köker&amp;volume=33&amp;publication_year=2022&amp;pages=925-933&amp;pmid=36098362&amp;doi=10.5152/tjg.2022.211063&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation id="r25"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Çekin AH, Şahintürk Y, Akbay Harmandar F, et al.  (2017) Use of probiotics as an adjuvant to sequential H. pylori eradication therapy: impact on eradication rates, treatment resistance, treatment-related side effects, and patient compliance. Turk J Gastroenterol
28, 3–11.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.5152/tjg.2016.0278"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="28007678"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Turk J Gastroenterol&amp;title=Use of probiotics as an adjuvant to sequential H. pylori eradication therapy: impact on eradication rates, treatment resistance, treatment-related side effects, and patient compliance&amp;author=AH Çekin&amp;author=Y Şahintürk&amp;author=F Akbay Harmandar&amp;volume=28&amp;publication_year=2017&amp;pages=3-11&amp;pmid=28007678&amp;doi=10.5152/tjg.2016.0278&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation id="r26"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Endo H, Higurashi T, Hosono K, et al.  (2011) Efficacy of Lactobacillus casei treatment on small bowel injury in chronic low-dose aspirin users: a pilot randomized controlled study. J Gastroenterol
46, 894–905.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s00535-011-0410-1"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="21556830"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=J Gastroenterol&amp;title=Efficacy of Lactobacillus casei treatment on small bowel injury in chronic low-dose aspirin users: a pilot randomized controlled study&amp;author=H Endo&amp;author=T Higurashi&amp;author=K Hosono&amp;volume=46&amp;publication_year=2011&amp;pages=894-905&amp;pmid=21556830&amp;doi=10.1007/s00535-011-0410-1&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation id="r27"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Asemi Z, Bahmani S, Shakeri H, et al.  (2015) Effect of multispecies probiotic supplements on serum minerals, liver enzymes and blood pressure in patients with type 2 diabetes. Int J Diabetes Dev Ctries
35, 90–95.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Int J Diabetes Dev Ctries&amp;title=Effect of multispecies probiotic supplements on serum minerals, liver enzymes and blood pressure in patients with type 2 diabetes&amp;author=Z Asemi&amp;author=S Bahmani&amp;author=H Shakeri&amp;volume=35&amp;publication_year=2015&amp;pages=90-95&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation id="r28"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Axling U, Önning G, Martinsson Niskanen T, et al.  (2021) The effect of Lactiplantibacillus plantarum 299v together with a low dose of iron on iron status in healthy pregnant women: a randomized clinical trial. Acta Obstet Gynecol Scand
100, 1602–1610.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/aogs.14153"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC8453534"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33880752"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Acta Obstet Gynecol Scand&amp;title=The effect of Lactiplantibacillus plantarum 299v together with a low dose of iron on iron status in healthy pregnant women: a randomized clinical trial&amp;author=U Axling&amp;author=G Önning&amp;author=T Martinsson Niskanen&amp;volume=100&amp;publication_year=2021&amp;pages=1602-1610&amp;pmid=33880752&amp;doi=10.1111/aogs.14153&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation id="r29"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
OjiNjideka Hemphill N, Pezley L, Steffen A, et al.  (2023) Feasibility study of <italic>Lactobacillus Plantarum</italic> 299v probiotic supplementation in an urban academic facility among diverse pregnant individuals. Nutrients
15, 875.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/nu15040875"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9966742"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36839232"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Nutrients&amp;author=N OjiNjideka Hemphill&amp;author=L Pezley&amp;author=A Steffen&amp;volume=15&amp;publication_year=2023&amp;pages=875&amp;pmid=36839232&amp;doi=10.3390/nu15040875&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation id="r30"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Buttarello M, Pajola R, Novello E, et al.  (2016) Evaluation of the hypochromic erythrocyte and reticulocyte hemoglobin content provided by the Sysmex XE-5000 analyzer in diagnosis of iron deficiency erythropoiesis. Clin Chem Lab Med
54, 1939–1945.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1515/cclm-2016-0041"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="27658146"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Clin Chem Lab Med&amp;title=Evaluation of the hypochromic erythrocyte and reticulocyte hemoglobin content provided by the Sysmex XE-5000 analyzer in diagnosis of iron deficiency erythropoiesis&amp;author=M Buttarello&amp;author=R Pajola&amp;author=E Novello&amp;volume=54&amp;publication_year=2016&amp;pages=1939-1945&amp;pmid=27658146&amp;doi=10.1515/cclm-2016-0041&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation id="r31"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Kulich KR, Madisch A, Pacini F, et al.  (2008) Reliability and validity of the Gastrointestinal Symptom Rating Scale (GSRS) and Quality of Life in Reflux and Dyspepsia (QOLRAD) questionnaire in dyspepsia: a six-country study. Health Qual Life Outcomes
6, 12.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1186/1477-7525-6-12"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC2276197"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="18237386"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Health Qual Life Outcomes&amp;title=Reliability and validity of the Gastrointestinal Symptom Rating Scale (GSRS) and Quality of Life in Reflux and Dyspepsia (QOLRAD) questionnaire in dyspepsia: a six-country study&amp;author=KR Kulich&amp;author=A Madisch&amp;author=F Pacini&amp;volume=6&amp;publication_year=2008&amp;pages=12&amp;pmid=18237386&amp;doi=10.1186/1477-7525-6-12&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation id="r32"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Burrowes JD, Powers SN, Cockram DB, et al.  (1996) Use of an appetite and diet assessment tool in the pilot phase of a hemodialysis clinical trial: mortality and morbidity in hemodialysis study. J Renal Nutr
6, 229–232.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=J Renal Nutr&amp;title=Use of an appetite and diet assessment tool in the pilot phase of a hemodialysis clinical trial: mortality and morbidity in hemodialysis study&amp;author=JD Burrowes&amp;author=SN Powers&amp;author=DB Cockram&amp;volume=6&amp;publication_year=1996&amp;pages=229-232&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation id="r33"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Kujawa-Szewieczek A, Adamczak M, Kwiecień K, et al.  (2015) The effect of lactobacillus plantarum 299v on the incidence of clostridium difficile infection in high risk patients treated with antibiotics. Nutrients
7, 10179–10188.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/nu7125526"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC4690078"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="26690209"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Nutrients&amp;title=The effect of lactobacillus plantarum 299v on the incidence of clostridium difficile infection in high risk patients treated with antibiotics&amp;author=A Kujawa-Szewieczek&amp;author=M Adamczak&amp;author=K Kwiecień&amp;volume=7&amp;publication_year=2015&amp;pages=10179-10188&amp;pmid=26690209&amp;doi=10.3390/nu7125526&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation id="r34"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Kaźmierczak-Siedlecka K, Daca A, Folwarski M, et al.  (2020) The role of <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic> 299v in supporting treatment of selected diseases. Cent Eur J Immunol
45, 488–493.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.5114/ceji.2020.101515"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7882405"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33613097"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Cent Eur J Immunol&amp;title=The role of Lactobacillus plantarum 299v in supporting treatment of selected diseases&amp;author=K Kaźmierczak-Siedlecka&amp;author=A Daca&amp;author=M Folwarski&amp;volume=45&amp;publication_year=2020&amp;pages=488-493&amp;pmid=33613097&amp;doi=10.5114/ceji.2020.101515&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation id="r35"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Sandberg AS, Önning G, Engström N, et al.  (2018) Iron supplements containing <italic>Lactobacillus Plantarum</italic> 299v increase ferric iron and up-regulate the ferric reductase DCYTB in human Caco-2/HT29 MTX co-cultures. Nutrients
10, 1949.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/nu10121949"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC6315724"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="30544799"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Nutrients&amp;title=Iron supplements containing Lactobacillus Plantarum 299v increase ferric iron and up-regulate the ferric reductase DCYTB in human Caco-2/HT29 MTX co-cultures&amp;author=AS Sandberg&amp;author=G Önning&amp;author=N Engström&amp;volume=10&amp;publication_year=2018&amp;pages=1949&amp;pmid=30544799&amp;doi=10.3390/nu10121949&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation id="r36"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Jaramillo Á, Briones L, Andrews M, et al.  (2015) Effect of phytic acid, tannic acid and pectin on fasting iron bioavailability both in the presence and absence of calcium. J Trace Elem Med Biol
30, 112–117.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.jtemb.2014.11.005"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="25544113"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=J Trace Elem Med Biol&amp;title=Effect of phytic acid, tannic acid and pectin on fasting iron bioavailability both in the presence and absence of calcium&amp;author=Á Jaramillo&amp;author=L Briones&amp;author=M Andrews&amp;volume=30&amp;publication_year=2015&amp;pages=112-117&amp;pmid=25544113&amp;doi=10.1016/j.jtemb.2014.11.005&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation id="r37"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Liu H, Wu W &amp; Luo Y (2023) Oral and intravenous iron treatment alter the gut microbiome differentially in dialysis patients. Int Urol Nephrol
55, 759–767.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s11255-022-03377-0"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9957911"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36166104"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Int Urol Nephrol&amp;title=Oral and intravenous iron treatment alter the gut microbiome differentially in dialysis patients&amp;author=H Liu&amp;author=W Wu&amp;author=Y Luo&amp;volume=55&amp;publication_year=2023&amp;pages=759-767&amp;pmid=36166104&amp;doi=10.1007/s11255-022-03377-0&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation id="r38"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Serati M &amp; Torella M (2019) Preventing complications by persistence with iron replacement therapy: a comprehensive literature review. Curr Med Res Opin
35, 1065–1072.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1080/03007995.2018.1552850"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="30477352"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Curr Med Res Opin&amp;title=Preventing complications by persistence with iron replacement therapy: a comprehensive literature review&amp;author=M Serati&amp;author=M Torella&amp;volume=35&amp;publication_year=2019&amp;pages=1065-1072&amp;pmid=30477352&amp;doi=10.1080/03007995.2018.1552850&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation id="r39"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Finlayson-Trick EC, Fischer JA, Goldfarb DM, et al.  (2020) The effects of iron supplementation and fortification on the gut microbiota: a review. Gastrointest Disord
2, 327–340.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Gastrointest Disord&amp;title=The effects of iron supplementation and fortification on the gut microbiota: a review&amp;author=EC Finlayson-Trick&amp;author=JA Fischer&amp;author=DM Goldfarb&amp;volume=2&amp;publication_year=2020&amp;pages=327-340&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation id="r40"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Richards T, Breymann C, Brookes MJ, et al.  (2021) Questions and answers on iron deficiency treatment selection and the use of intravenous iron in routine clinical practice. Ann Med
53, 274–285.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1080/07853890.2020.1867323"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7877947"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33426933"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Ann Med&amp;title=Questions and answers on iron deficiency treatment selection and the use of intravenous iron in routine clinical practice&amp;author=T Richards&amp;author=C Breymann&amp;author=MJ Brookes&amp;volume=53&amp;publication_year=2021&amp;pages=274-285&amp;pmid=33426933&amp;doi=10.1080/07853890.2020.1867323&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation id="r41"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Bering S, Suchdev S, Sjøltov L, et al.  (2006) A lactic acid-fermented oat gruel increases non-haem iron absorption from a phytate-rich meal in healthy women of childbearing age. Br J Nutr
96, 80–85.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1079/bjn20061683"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="16869994"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Br J Nutr&amp;title=A lactic acid-fermented oat gruel increases non-haem iron absorption from a phytate-rich meal in healthy women of childbearing age&amp;author=S Bering&amp;author=S Suchdev&amp;author=L Sjøltov&amp;volume=96&amp;publication_year=2006&amp;pages=80-85&amp;pmid=16869994&amp;doi=10.1079/bjn20061683&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation id="r42"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Hurrell RF (2012) Influence of inflammatory disorders and infection on iron absorption and efficacy of iron-fortified foods. Nestle Nutr Inst Workshop Ser
70, 107–116.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1159/000337673"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC4353607"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="25762975"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Nestle Nutr Inst Workshop Ser&amp;author=RF Hurrell&amp;volume=70&amp;publication_year=2012&amp;pages=107-116&amp;pmid=25762975&amp;doi=10.1159/000337673&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation id="r43"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Suchdev PS, Williams AM, Mei Z, et al.  (2017) Assessment of iron status in settings of inflammation: challenges and potential approaches. Am J Clin Nutr
106, 1626S–1633S.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3945/ajcn.117.155937"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC5701714"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="29070567"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Am J Clin Nutr&amp;title=Assessment of iron status in settings of inflammation: challenges and potential approaches&amp;author=PS Suchdev&amp;author=AM Williams&amp;author=Z Mei&amp;volume=106&amp;publication_year=2017&amp;pages=1626S-1633S&amp;pmid=29070567&amp;doi=10.3945/ajcn.117.155937&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation id="r44"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Axling U, Önning G, Combs MA, et al.  (2020) The effect of <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic> 299v on iron status and physical performance in female iron-deficient athletes: a randomized controlled trial. Nutrients
12, 1279.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/nu12051279"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7282001"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32365981"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Nutrients&amp;title=The effect of Lactobacillus plantarum 299v on iron status and physical performance in female iron-deficient athletes: a randomized controlled trial&amp;author=U Axling&amp;author=G Önning&amp;author=MA Combs&amp;volume=12&amp;publication_year=2020&amp;pages=1279&amp;pmid=32365981&amp;doi=10.3390/nu12051279&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation id="r45"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Fikri B, Ridha NR, Putri SH, et al.  (2022) Effects of probiotics on immunity and iron homeostasis: a mini-review. Clin Nutr ESPEN
49, 24–27.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.clnesp.2022.03.031"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="35623819"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Clin Nutr ESPEN&amp;title=Effects of probiotics on immunity and iron homeostasis: a mini-review&amp;author=B Fikri&amp;author=NR Ridha&amp;author=SH Putri&amp;volume=49&amp;publication_year=2022&amp;pages=24-27&amp;pmid=35623819&amp;doi=10.1016/j.clnesp.2022.03.031&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></sec></sec></body></article>